<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Summary of Findings - Managing the Best Practice for Open Source Communities</title>
    <para> </para>
    <section>
        <title>The Current State of Healthcare Knowledge Management</title>
        <para>Over the last decade, billion dollars have been poured into achieving interoperability
            in the healthcare industry. Patients, providers, and healthcare agencies have
            collectively identified the need for a more harmonized, integrated health system to
            solve the challenges surrounding clinical data, such as its interpretability and
            accuracy. The current structure of the healthcare ecosystem continues to fail in
            providing adequate structures conducive to collaborative, community-based solutioning. A
            review in 2021 of American Hospital Association Information Technology survey data found
            that by 2018, 98.3% of hospitals have adopted Electronic Health Record (EHR) systems –
            the primary creators and curators of digital health data. Yet, across the board, health
            systems have struggled to move beyond simple adoption and implement advanced use in
            patient engagement and clinical data analytics [1]. Notably, critical access hospitals
            in rural areas were less likely to demonstrate advanced usage with an expanding deficit
            to their counterparts in clinical data analytics since 2015, leading to gaps in patient
            access of quality healthcare. </para>
        <para>Today, many hospital systems have the goal of improving data interoperability within
            and beyond their system. To be truly useful, clinical data must move through numerous
            systems without loss of meaning. In an idealized situation, data transfers would
            complete a single round-trip with total integrity intact. In reality, only 22% - 68% of
            data integrity is successfully preserved through its transfer journey [2]. A patient’s
            record may correctly showcase the correct numerical result from a test but could lose
            the context and meaning surrounding the test. Ever-increasing system complexity and
            resulting low-quality data, however, has ultimately impacted the quality of care across
            the healthcare ecosystem, such as inefficiencies of redundant testing and procedures
            being ordered, expanding the timeframe of care for patients. Additionally, the very
            systems that have been designed to integrate EHRs into the health space can create
            barriers to interoperability through closed, proprietary systems. Multiple, sometimes
            competing, encoding standards have been developed over the last few decades to address
            the varying formats clinical data embodies. Some clinical standardization forms,
            however, are very broad in its acceptance criteria resulting in large amounts of
            variation between encodement while others are too restrictive, limiting the situations
            in which they can be utilized. As a result, the need for a consistent form to map
            standards to and between other standards in creation of a common model is required for
            improvement of interoperability within the healthcare landscape where clinical decisions
            can be captured regardless of what point they originate in patient care. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Defining a Key Issue: Restrictive Healthcare Licenses</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>The root cause of insufficiencies within health IT is not limited solely to a group of
            vendors or organizations but is rather a foundational issue that permeates throughout
            the ecosystem. Restrictive licenses are just one of these causes and are used in varying
            forms across the landscape. This, however, spurs unintended consequences of limiting
            harmonization. Instead of just treating the symptomatic results of poor data quality,
            attention should also be spent understanding the reasons beneath recurring pain points.
            Various standards have been developed to compete and improve upon the limitations of
            other encoding standards. As multiple organizations, such as by clinicians,
            laboratorians, and providers integrate patient data together, the need of various
            standards to transfer openly and completely becomes even more apparent. Yet, however, a
            piecemeal approach has occurred where different standards carry licensing restrictions
            to protect against modifications and extensions of their code for proprietary oversight,
            creating confusion on how and to what extent standards can be shared. Understandably,
            healthcare data standard organizations seek to protect their software and standards, by
            design, from unauthorized subversion, modification, and duplication of their work
            through their licensing agreements. These restrictions often allow for direct oversight
            of derivative works from the issuing body as well as monetization from commercial usage
            of their product. In a highly profitable landscape, restrictive licenses allow
            organizations to prevent their work from being duplicated by rivals and seek longevity
            in the marketplace. Yet, it cannot be denied that proprietary licensing leads to siloed
            operations by providers and developers, as well as higher implementation costs, limiting
            stronger adoption. These restrictive licenses can pose challenges on the ease of
            transfers within and between systems and are creators of insufficiencies within health
            IT. For example, issuing standards do not always fit into the exact context
            practitioners need and require adaption into localized knowledge. Licenses often prevent
            against local knowledge being shared between system and require a mapping to an existing
            code for meaningful data usage. This, however, is where data integrity can be impacted
            as there may be no exact match that encompasses all the information from local codes and
            be transferred incompletely. Tools to aid in standardization may be restricted due to
            modification and extension restrictions within proprietary licenses. </para>
        <para><emphasis>The current restrictive and proprietary natures of licensing within the
                healthcare ecosystem significantly hinders interoperability. To achieve lossless
                data exchanges between systems, the Health IT community must consider movement
                towards open-source software and open-source licensing models.</emphasis> Gaps
            created by varying rates of adoption and implementation requires various avenues of
            collaboration within the IKM community to address these issues within the entire Health
            IT ecosystem. </para>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Case for a More Open Future in Healthcare</title>
        <para>The rapid expansion of technology and connectivity has created ill-defined guidelines
            on management and ownership of data. As a result, researchers and users find themselves
            navigating different and competing guidance on utilizing and adapting software for their
            own needs. One of the main movements on expanding access and resolving conflict between
            proprietary systems is that of granting wide, sweeping rights through the open-source
            movement. Notably, open-source software like Mozilla Firefox has enabled web access
            utilized by millions every year. Additionally, open software systems, like Apache 2.0,
            have had broad adoptive use because it allows software to be used for any purpose,
            modified or otherwise. </para>
        <para>The following sections aim to define the open-source software and licensing more
            clearly: </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Open-Source Software (OSS) </emphasis></para>
        <para>Fundamentally, there are two branches of software utilized by individuals and
            companies: open-source software and proprietary, or closed-source, software. At the most
            theoretical level, in an open-source environment, the source code is freely available
            and accessible to its end-users regardless of their intent, be it for personal or
            commercial use. The term “free” is under debate regarding the cost of accessing the
            software and under contention on if the source code can be monetized for access. Here,
            free is used as in libre, or freedom, and not necessarily in cost. Meaning, the
            discussion of free licensing extends to freedoms guaranteed through the licensing for
            the software, and not in the context of the monetary cost to access the software. Many
            software systems are considered to be open-source but are not free in cost to the
            implementation. There are third-party costs with integrating and maintaining
            open-source. </para>
        <para>The Free Software Foundation (FSF) defines free as in: </para>
        <para> The freedom to run the program as you wish, for any purpose (freedom 0)</para>
        <para> The freedom to study how the program works and change it so it does your computing
            as you wish (freedom 1). Access to the source code is a precondition for this</para>
        <para> The freedom to redistribute copies so you can help others (freedom 2); and</para>
        <para> The freedom to distribute copies of your modified versions to others (freedom 3).
            [3] </para>
        <para>This is controlled in the forms of licenses and is discussed further below.
            Contrastingly, a closed source system protects the source code and modifications cannot
            be made where the end-user can only execute the code within the confines of the original
            intent of the creator. </para>
        <para>In open-source, no one group is solely responsible for the software because it allows
            for a peer-to-peer production of codes and documentation. However, in practice, a
            governing body may exist to oversee and maintain the software as long as no one group
            holds special rights to the software. Additionally, due to the decentralization of
            software, errors and bugs are found much quicker because the code is utilized in a
            variety of contexts and stretched much farther. Here, instead of a single development
            team being tasked with identifying and repairing errors as they are found, users can
            also be developers and contribute to identifying errors much faster. As a result,
            open-source software utilizes a high degree of modularity where it can be adaptive and
            flexible to the diverse needs of its users. </para>
        <para><emphasis>In its purest form, open-source software lowers the burden of buy-in
                required by consumers where they can build on the work of others through a
                collaborative community without reinvention</emphasis>. There is a lower cost to
            implement and maintain open-source software, expanding the possible consumer base. It is
            not merely restricted to those who can devote the time and resources to stand up the
            required infrastructure and knowledge base. Instead, end-users can guide and shape the
            software to their niche rather than be limited to the specific intended usage at its
            inception. The creation of open-source leads to a symbiotic ecosystem where software is
            more robust and applicable than its closed counterparts. </para>
        <para>Many software systems today utilize qualities of open-source software but lie in a
            gray area where they maintain proprietary techniques. These limits are imposed by their
            licensing models through their end-user agreements. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Open-Source Licensing (OSL) </emphasis></para>
        <para>The implementation of open-source software is managed in-hand through open-source
            licensing (OSL). The license of the software sets out the guidelines on the usage and
            implementation of the specific version of software being used. The license acts as a
            copyright agreement where organizations and creators can control the distribution,
            duplication, and modification of their work. </para>
        <para>There are many different types of licenses, as seen in Figure 1 below, and are often
            created to be intentionally vague to apply to a multitude of situations and preserve the
            rights of the licensor: </para><figure xml:id="RestrictionsImposed">
                <title>Restrictions Imposed by License Type</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/2.2.4%20Restrctions%20posed.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Public-Domain</emphasis>: Public domain refers to any
            information, software, or intellectual property that carries no restrictions in regard
            to copyright law. It is free to use by any individual. No one group can exercise control
            over it. In a software setting, source code must be provided. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Permissive License</emphasis>: It is also known as an
            open-source license. This type of license carries minimal restriction over adaption,
            modification, and distribution of intellectual property of organizations. An issuing
            body may impose some restrictions, such as the monetization, but it does not exert
            special rights to derivative works. In a software setting, source code must be provided. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Protective License</emphasis>: This type of license, also called
            a copyleft license, grants rights on modification and redistribution but also requires
            derivative works to include and grants the same rights of the original license. Similar
            to public domain and permissive licenses, source code must also be accessible. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Noncommercial</emphasis>: The license only grants special rights
            to be used in a noncommercial setting where an external entity may exercise proprietary
            control or monetization of the applicable intellectual property. This can also decrease
            the cost of access, especially for organizations for academic or research purposes. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Proprietary</emphasis>: The most traditional form of licensing
            where no rights must be granted to other entities. There are varying significant
            restrictions on modification and distribution, where it is often disallowed completely. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Trade Secret</emphasis>: Often left unpublished, information is
            not open to the public or non-entity members in any form. It is the most restrictive,
            private type of licensing. In software, no source code is available. </para>
        <para>Open-source licensing is seen as a method to resolve the dispute between unauthorized
            copying and distribution of content as well as the copyright laws that have been created
            to protect individual and businesses of their own work [4]. Instead of users finding
            ways to circumvent barriers of access to content, the license serves as a pathway on how
            to freely access and modify software to the needs of users while protecting the
            proprietary interests of the originator. In this context, discussion surrounding the
            term of “free” applies here as well as it does in open-source software. Many software
            systems are considered to be open-source and utilize an open-source license but are not
            free in cost to the licensee. </para>
        <para>Open-source licensing agreements give access to software that may have been prevented
            under copyright law. These types of licenses enable use regardless of intent and the
            ability to modify, adapt, and extend software with minimal restrictions. The license
            establishes rules of the road and codifies best practices to enable adoptability and
            ease of use for both the initial user and the broader downstream community. For example,
            many licenses require modifications to be disclosed and thoroughly documented for
            third-party individuals to avoid endorsements and confusion regarding what has been
            published directly from organizations themselves. </para>
        <para>In practice, many licenses are not considered open-source due to certain conditions
            like distribution, access, and modification being prohibited. It is important to note
            that the quality of software and source code is not inherently affected by the structure
            of the license. A balance, however, is required ensuring that the licenses do not cause
            unintended consequences surrounding the proper development and evolution of the code by
            the user [5]. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Examining License Agreements in Action</title>
        <para>For many organizations, it is unrealistic to fully adopt all parts of open-source
            software and licensing. Organization’s structure licenses dependent on the intended
            usage of software and codes and aim to embody qualities of open-source. For example, an
            individual may be able to access software and source code for no-cost or at a greatly
            reduced cost if it is meant for an academic usage. Notably, the moment where the user
            would like to adapt, transmute, and distribute software, they will often need a
            different license such as a commercial one. Rather than being purely open or closed
            source, in application, many organizations lie somewhere in the middle where
            commercialization of parts of their software support the ongoing research, development,
            and maintenance of itself. Organizations argue that the monetization of their software
            also allows them to create detailed guidance for implementation as well as more direct
            support to its customers while also protecting the proprietary source and implementation
            of its product. It can, however, contribute to unintended downstream effects that
            require a multistep approach to solving. Advocacy towards open-source, permissive
            licenses is one aspect to solutioning. </para>
        <para>Users are often left to determine their obligations to different licenses, especially
            when wanting to combine related software. How do researchers, laboratorians, and health
            providers navigate the intentional vague complexity of licenses when attempting to solve
            interoperability? Instead, they experience restrictions and lock-in from standards that
            act as a hinderance to solving patient problems. Two related but distinguishable
            implication of licenses are [6]: </para>
        <para>1. The explicit terms and rights maintained on content derived from software, and </para>
        <para>2. The incompatibility of licensing in competing and related standards. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The current siloed approach of licensing models prevents
                interoperability within health IT and results in lower quality data with unattended,
                downstream patient effects.</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para><emphasis>Case-Study: LOINC® and SNOMED International Licensing
            Agreements</emphasis></para>
        <para>Logical Observation Identifiers Names and Code® (LOINC®) and Systemized Nomenclature
            of Medicine – Clinical Terms® (SNOMED CT®) are two of the most widely used health data
            standards in the U.S. for clinical terminology. LOINC® is overseen by the Regenstrief
            Institute and utilizes a global team for maintaining, developing, and updating guidance
            on its terminology with the vision of promoting open terminology standards across every
            clinical information system [7]. LOINC® advocates for open terminology standards but
            does not issue an open-source license. Instead, all users are required to hold a license
            to utilize LOINC®, with some licenses requiring a fee to implement and utilize the full
            functionality of LOINC®. Similarly, SNOMED-CT® is overseen by SNOMED International with
            the intent to support, maintain, and implement SNOMED CT®. All users are required to
            accept SNOMED International’s licensing agreement through an end-user agreement and are
            issued a proprietary license with some requiring a fee depending on the usage and intent
            of the license. Both organizations issue guidance on new and existing codes to reflect
            current events and needs at least biannually by engaging in a rigorous feedback function
            where users can engage. SNOMED International is moving towards more timely standard
            updates, not limited to the biannual timeline, especially for rapid developing arenas,
            such as COVID-19. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Where Licenses Break Interoperability: Redistribution and
                Modification </emphasis></para>
        <para>The Regenstrief institute highlights guiding principles such as openness and agility
            in improving and widening LOINC®’s implementation. Notably, however, Regenstrief does
            not allow the distribution of modified codes under their license. Often, health systems
            will adapt an existing code to better represent their localized environment where there
            is no one-for-one match. As a result, users must create their own solution limited to
            the licensing agreement, engage in a feedback process with the Regenstrief Institute,
            and wait until a new code is issued directly from Regenstrief to be able to share
            between systems. </para>
        <para>Similarly, SNOMED International does not allow for derivative work or extensions to be
            created if it has not already been issued a Namespace Identifier. Additionally,
            modifications are disallowed under their SNOMED CT® Affiliate license and must go
            through a feedback process where users can petition for added codes in a future release
            cycle. This is to avoid confusion and ambiguity of SNOMED International codes and
            prevent against inconsistencies between systems [8]. As a result, however, there will be
            many forms of similarly derived codes in a localized format. </para>
        <para>This waiting cycle creates gaps that directly impact the quality and interoperability
            of data. While organizations petition to have new codes created, they must continue to
            standardize their codes before their data is transferred to another system. During this
            step, data can be lost during the transfer from a local code to a standard LOINC® or
            SNOMED® code. As a result of this, doctors may lose the much-needed context surrounding
            patient care, leading to redundancy in additional ordered tests and referrals. Moreover,
            the issuance of new codes does not circumvent the usage of localized knowledge. New
            codes can be used in place of local knowledge, but it can also be further adapted into
            knowledge for the specific needs of practitioners. This does not solve the transfer
            errors that can occur when local codes are standardized. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Putting a More Open Healthcare Ecosystem Into Practice</title>
        <para>The IKM community has been longing to address proper standardization encodement of
            healthcare information across ever changing system. Many avenues of collaboration would
            help solve the data quality and interoperability issue that the healthcare IT ecosystem
            is facing. The meaningful semantic difference within terminologies requires preservation
            to prevent against varying clinical interpretation and treatment. An <emphasis
                role="bold">Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM)</emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">approach</emphasis> can act as a method to standardize clinical
            statements and terminologies by providing abstraction and elimination of unnecessary
            complexity. Instead of a local code being incorrectly mapped to a standard code, the IKM
            platform would provide guidance on the most applicable codes and reduce data loss by
            ensuring a consistent, reproducible format allowing for the same test to be represented
            the same way, every time. Proper achievement requires collaboration across government
            regulatory bodies, public health laboratories, private healthcare systems, and
            In-Vitro-Diagnostic (IVD) device manufacturers. This also extends to the bodies that
            oversee terminology standards and the licensing agreements governing them. </para>
        <para>For successful implementation of an integrated knowledge ecosystem, licensing bodies
            should implement components of open-source licensing, specifically on modification and
            distribution of copyrighted standards. Currently, the process that exists on how
            licenses work together in common spaces and the subsequent requirements are ambiguous.
            Would the implementation of a third-party software trigger licensing restrictions and
            inhibit the willingness of organizations to adopt them? Is the usage of an IKM platform
            by an organization to reconcile local codes considered to be an extension of a modified
            code, disallowed under the existing licensing structure? Some licenses consider any work
            to be referential to be a “derivative” without fully specifying the scope of the
            reference. This is seen, for example, in the form of the GNU's Not Unix (GNU) General
            Public License (GPL) and in references to GPL licensed libraries [9]. The navigation of
            differing licenses and determining the varying responsibilities imposed by them can be a
            costly, time-consuming burden that often acts as a barrier for meaningful progress. It
            can quickly become a convoluted process that inhibits success of implementation,
            unintended by the licensor and their vision of interoperability as seen in LOINC®.
            Licenses must walk a tightline on preventing extension of standards, thereby slowing
            down the evolution of these standards, and allowing full extensions that can subvert the
            standard in and of itself, creating confusion where modifications look to be
            endorsements by the issuing body [5]. </para>
        <para>In practice, a strong open-source licenses can encourage the development and evolution
            of standards without subversion of standards through guardrails on community
            contributions. Instead, of a few chosen contributors, solutions can be developed openly
            with the collaboration of multiple stakeholders where solutioning becomes more robust
            and agile to the various needs of its users. Reasonable guidelines, such as extensive
            documentation procedures especially in extensions for example, enhances the trust within
            open-source solutions and allow for the benefits of open-source without allowing an
            “anything goes” mentality where confusion ensues. Additionally, open-source licenses can
            continue to protect against impersonations and false endorsements through their
            agreements. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Open-Source Licensing Within a Knowledge
            Architecture</emphasis></para>
        <para>A Knowledge Architecture is a framework for clinical information that is organized
            into distinct layers such that each higher layer relies upon artifacts from the lower
            layer. It aims to define a standardized form of clinical statements and harmonize
            existing terminologies together into a single system. </para>
        <para>A knowledge architecture intended for use in the current health IT ecosystem is listed
            below: </para>
        <figure xml:id="LayersWithinKnowledgeArchitecture">
            <title>Layers Within Knowledge Architecture</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/PASTF%20Model%203.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Rather than a broad transformation of existing licenses in a purely open-source model,
            not all components of software and standard licensing require a pivot away from
            proprietary oversight to lead to successful implementation of an IKM ecosystem. The
            commercial usage of aspects of licenses allows for ongoing support and maintenance of
            software and standards. The move towards a permissive license does not require a seismic
            shift in organization structure or its ability monetize its commercial license,
            especially for organizations already promoting open-standards. <emphasis>Allowing for
                open-licensing encourages improvements of terminology and standards by ancillary
                bodies and creates a more robust, flexible system that can further adapt into the
                varying needs of organizations. </emphasis></para>
        <para>Data harmonization improves when foundational layers of Knowledge Architecture are
            integrated into common, collective sources of data. If utilized correctly, under a
            Knowledge Architecture, a single-data journey can be completed with integrity intact
            every time. Permissive licensing throughout the foundational architecture, terminology
            knowledge, and statement model layers removes barriers imposed on modifications and
            extensions and instead aids in the creation of common understandings of knowledge. The
            Terminology Knowledge layer within Knowledge Architecture oversees the structure of
            medical terminologies, such as the language and semantic hierarchy within data. It is in
            this layer where the IKM platform arbitrates the valid codes and expressions to be used
            in higher layers. Currently, the usage of terminology standards like SNOMED CT®, LOINC®,
            and additional standards pose questions regarding compatibility due to modification and
            extensions limitations. The complexity widens when further standards based on other
            standards are integrated further in the terminology layer, like the Laboratory
            Interoperability Data Repository (LIDR) and the TermINology Knowledge Architecture
            (Tinkar). The loss of data often occurs in this layer and breaks the functionality of
            standards where local codes are mapped to the incorrect standard codes. The IKM platform
            aims to solve this issue by harmonizing standards but cannot be successfully implemented
            unless the underlying licenses allow an IKM platform to reconcile variances. In the
            Statement Model, the artifacts as defined below are reused and demonstrate how the data
            elements should be packaged into clinical statements through clinical formatting, such
            as Health Level 7 Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (HL7 FHIR) or Clinical
            Informational Modeling Initiative (CIMI). The shift towards a permissive license in
            regard to terminologies and standards improves the compatibility of how different
            terminologies work together and thereby is integral to the functionality of  higher
            layers and interoperability overall. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>Achievement of interoperability within healthcare systems requires a multi-faceted approach through the extensive collaboration of various stakeholders involved. In its current form, many licenses serve as unintended barriers to interoperability where downstream patient harm can occur. The increasingly interconnectedness of industries and partners require a reevaluation of existing licensing structures that impose barriers often antithetical to goals set out by issuing organizations themselves. For solutions like an Integrated Knowledge Platform to succeed, licensing must be structured to support and encourage growth of ancillary bodies. The adoption of open-source licensing encourages diversity of thought where stronger software often results to the benefit of organizations. As a result, advocacy towards open-source licensing must also occur internally by managing teams. Together, common solutioning reduces siloed company operations, moving one step closer to harmonization across the health IT landscape. 
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Appendix</title> 
        <para>
            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry><emphasis role="italic">LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="italic">SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="italic">What is the type of license
                                    utilized?</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>LOINC® utilizes proprietary licenses throughout. It is not
                                    considered to be open-source, especially under the commercial
                                    agreement. </para>
                                <para> </para>
                                <para>Notably, all users are required to hold a license to utilize
                                    LOINC®.</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>SNOMED CT® is not considered open-source and instead issues
                                    proprietary licenses. SNOMED CT® has a variety of licenses
                                    dependent on the usage and intent, with some requiring a fee. </para>
                                <para> </para>
                                <para>SNOMED CT® requires all users to have a license. </para>
                                <para> </para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="italic">Who owns and maintains the
                                    standard?</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para> </para>
                                <para>Regenstrief Institute oversees LOINC® and utilizes a global
                                    team to contribute to LOINC®. They oversee and are responsible
                                    for the maintenance of LOINC®, as well as issuing up-to-date
                                    guidance. </para>
                                <para> </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>SNOMED International oversees SNOMED CT® and is supported in part
                                by the International Health Terminology Standards Development
                                Organization (IHTSDO) to maintain and implement SNOMED CT®.
                                Additional licensing for non-IHTSDO countries is available. </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="italic">What is the cost associated with
                                    usage?</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® is not completely free to use and is specified by its
                                intent of the license holder. Nonprofit, academic, and individual
                                licenses are available under a free license; however, a commercial
                                license requires a fee to implement. There may be third-party costs
                                associated with implementing and supporting LOINC® external to the
                                licensing. </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>SNOMED International, which includes SNOMED CT®, has fees
                                    associated with its licensee depending on the usage by the
                                    holder. For non-commercial use, such as by academic bodies,
                                    there is no fee for SNOMED International licensing, but are
                                    limited on redistribution. </para>
                                <para> </para>
                                <para>For commercial use, however, like adding into existing
                                    healthcare systems for usage, then a fee is incurred for the
                                    license. There are multiple licenses to best support the varying
                                    needs of users. There are also fees associated with non-IHTSDO
                                    member countries.</para>
                                <para> </para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="italic">What does redistribution look
                                    like?</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>LOINC® allows for distribution of their original code without
                                restriction as long as their original license is included in it.
                                Limitations exist for modified codes and cannot be redistributed
                                without the consent of LOINC® copyright holders. If the distribution
                                is intended for commercial usage, a commercial license may be
                                required with associated fees. </entry>
                            <entry>SNOMED International redistribution is only allowed under a
                                commercial license as part of their license and cannot be done as a
                                standalone extension. Additionally, the licensee must still protect
                                the proprietary requirements as listed in their license to
                                distribute. Redistribution cannot be done in non-commercial
                                licenses. Modifications of SNOMED International codes are allowed
                                under certain distribution licenses but must maintain compatibility
                                with the original SNOMED CT® as well as be clearly documented and
                                labeled. </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="italic">How often do releases occur? Who
                                    contributes to what is updated?</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Releases occur twice a year, typically every 6 months. LOINC®
                                utilizes a feedback function where users can request new codes as
                                well as gathering feedback from stakeholders, regardless of license
                                status. They additionally test these codes and update guidance on
                                existing codes to reflect current events (ex. COVID-19). </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Releases occur in January and July every year and contain
                                    updated guidance for their codes to reflect current events,
                                    similar to LOINC®. </para>
                                <para> </para>
                                <para> </para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>1. Apathy, N. C., Holmgren, A. J., and Adler-Milstein, J. (2021, September). A decade
            post-HITECH: Critical access hospitals have electronic health records but struggle to
            keep up with other advanced functions. Journal of the American Medical Informatics
            Association, 1947-19554. Retrieved from https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocab102 </para>
        <para>2. Bernstam, E. V., Warner, J. L., Krauss, J. C., Ambinder, E., Rubinstein, W. S.,
            Komastsoulis, G., and Miller, R. S. (2022, May). Quantitating and assessing
            interoperability between electronic health records. Journal of the American Medical
            Informatics Association, 29(5), 753-760. doi:https://doi.org/10.1093/jamia/ocab289 </para>
        <para>3. Free Software Foundation. (n.d.). What is Free Software? Retrieved from GNU
            Operating System: https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html#copyleft </para>
        <para>4. Wilbanks, J. (2008). Public domain, copyright licenses and the freedom to integrate
            science. Journal of Science Communication, 7(2). doi:https://doi.org/10.22323/2.07020304 </para>
        <para>5. Reynolds, C. J., and Wyatt, J. C. (2011, February). Open Source, Open Standards,
            and Health Care Information Systems. Journal of Medical Internet Research.
            doi:https://doi.org/10.2196/jmir.1521 </para>
        <para>6. Hosking, R., and Gahegan, M. (2013). The Effects of Licensing on Open Data:
            Computing a Measure of Health for Our Scholarly Record. International Semantic Web
            Conference, 432-439. doi:https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-41338-4_28 </para>
        <para>7. Mission, Vision, and Principles for Open Terminology Development. (n.d.). Retrieved
            from LOINC®: https://loinc.org/principles/ </para>
        <para>8. SNOMED CT Affiliate License Agreement. (n.d.). Retrieved from SNOMED CT®:
            https://www.snomed.org/_files/ugd/900274_689013e9e0c74d23892abe9caee02612.pdf </para>
        <para>9. Scheibner, J. (2017). What price freedom (of software)? A guide for Australian
            legal practitioners on open source licensing. Retrieved from Australian Lawyers
            Alliance: http://classic.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/PrecedentAULA/2017/23.html#fnB3 </para>
    </section>
    </chapter>
