<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Summary of Findings - Current State of Safety Systems</title>
    <section>
        <title>Motivation</title>
    <para>Clinical laboratories are a key element in the overall healthcare ecosystem and play a
            role in most healthcare decisions today. Clinical laboratories are responsible for
            generating highly reliable laboratory data (orders, results, and interpretations) to
            drive effective care delivery. Clinical data must transverse many connected systems
            while maintaining context and precise semantic meaning. While each sending and receiving
            system of clinical data is configured individually to understand data inputs, the loss
            of meaning between systems is difficult to avoid, impacts patient safety, and hinders
            data science opportunities like machine learning and artificial intelligence. Plausible
            efforts to control for the nuances of laboratory data exchange have existed for decades.
            The advancement of technology increasingly emphasizes the need for standardization
            across the ecosystem as data science methods and capabilities mature. Safety and quality
            controls exist in every layer of the laboratory ecosystem, starting at the top of the
            ecosystem with Federal policymakers down to the individual patients receiving care.
            While the use of idiosyncratic (i.e., local institution–specific) identifiers for
            laboratory tests is recommended by Standards Development Organizations (SDO), such as
            Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine International (SNOMED International), entities in
            the laboratory data ecosystem must implement precise data mappings to a universal
            terminology. Idiosyncratic local identifiers alone hinder seamless sharing of laboratory
            observations between disparate health systems. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Background</title>
        <para>According to the Health Information Management (HIM) Body of Knowledge™ by the
            American Health Information Management Association (AHIMA), Health Data Standards (HDS)
            are documented agreements on representations, formats, and definitions of common data.
            [1] To achieve interoperability, health data entities must conform to industry standards
            and specifications which act as a source of truth for methods of codifying information
            captured and exchanged. Data standards are developed and maintained by SDOs who are
            member-supported organizations which act like a legislative body with detailed internal
            processes to ensure consistency and fairness among the entities subject to them. </para>
        <para>Two of the major Health Information Technology (IT) SDOs in our analysis are
            Regenstrief Institute, Inc. and Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine International
            (SNOMED International). Regenstrief Institute, Inc. organized LOINC® in 1994 to
            standardize a common terminology for laboratory and clinical observations as trends in
            electronic clinical data exchange were taking form. [2] Today, LOINC® encodings are most
            often exchanged via Health Level 7 (HL7) International Version 2 transactions between
            health systems. SNOMED Clinical Terms® (SNOMED CT®) is an international standard for
            several purposes including problem list and public health reporting and is required by
            many countries’ certification criteria for EHRs. It is a computer-processable collection
            of medical terms, codes, synonyms, and definitions used in clinical documentation and
            reporting. Both SNOMED CT® and LOINC® can be used as a common terminology to represent
            clinical information consistently and comprehensively in the electronic exchange of
            health data. However, two or more common terminologies which serve near-identical
            purposes is oxymoronic and leaves room for improvement, consolidation, and
            harmonization. For lab data exchange, SNOMED CT® is typically used to encode test
            results and observations and LOINC® is often used to encode tests (however, LOINC® does
            also represent some test results) and these relationships, overlaps, and contradictions
            present implementers with the need to use these terminologies in more integrated ways. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Objectives and Approach</title>
        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="rgeorgacopoulos" timestamp="20231130T124851-0500" comment="Removed &quot;In collaboration with Synensys, LLC, under the body of work for the SHIELD program&quot; from beginning of the sentence. 

If you want to include original phrasing please use &quot;In collaboration with Synensys, LLC, under the body of work for the SHIELD program, this analysis aims to provide foundational safety research and development support to reduce diagnostic errors and assist with proficiency testing and compliance by integrating systems theory and safety engineering methods used by other high-risk industries, such as aviation, military special operations, and nuclear power into laboratory testing and management processes and systems.&quot;"?>This<?oxy_comment_end?>
            analysis aims to provide foundational safety research and development support to reduce
            diagnostic errors and assist with proficiency testing and compliance by integrating
            systems theory and safety engineering methods used by other high-risk industries, such
            as aviation, military special operations, and nuclear power into laboratory testing and
            management processes and systems. This research will apply a System Safety approach to
            assess, measure, document, and analyze the safety and quality of the whole laboratory
            data ecosystem. </para>
        <para>One of the initial tasks is to assess and evaluate the safety of the current
            laboratory data ecosystem using a System Safety Engineering Approach to identify safety
            hazards, map the design, and model control structures of the current system. This
            research aim uses the System Theoretic Process Analysis (STPA) safety assessment process
            to identify hazards affecting data reliability, interoperability, data integrity, and
            data quality across the ecosystem, as well as providing an understanding of the clinical
            laboratory ecosystem controls, constraints, actuators, processes, and feedback loops for
            safe and effective operation. [3] By modeling a control structure, we can assess every
            relationship therein to measure the effectiveness of control actions and identify those
            which are unsafe to the system operation, human operators, and ultimately, patients. </para>
        <para>This document analyzes an initial control structure to identify and evaluate safety
            and quality controls and loss scenarios within the laboratory data ecosystem.
            Specifically, we focus on describing entities, behaviors, and business requirements to
            complement the current model of the control structure that supports interoperability,
            use of terminology systems, and industry coding standards such as LOINC® and SNOMED CT®.
            Within the control structure diagrams that have been developed, we are enumerating
            requirements for the "Data Flow for Encoding" to describe how data is encoded from labs
            and Laboratory Information System (LIS) systems to standards, how data is encoded
            between manufacturers and standards, and how new test names and codes are distributed by
            SDOs. These requirements will help to clarify and articulate control action scenarios.
            They further pinpoint specific scenarios in the safety assessment analysis by
            identifying unsafe control actions and loss scenarios related to the standards
            development, implementation, and maintenance processes in laboratories, devices, and
            standards. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="rgeorgacopoulos" timestamp="20231130T125558-0500" comment="This section makes mention of the Synensis contract and FDA work. Needs rewrite "?>
        <title><?oxy_comment_end?>Current Draft Model of the Laboratory Ecosystem Control
            Structure</title>
        <para>The initial modeling and analyses of the laboratory ecosystem control structure
            visualize the influences between ecosystem entities such as policy set by the federal
            government and the relationship that hospitals and laboratories form to design and
            peform the care delivery in collaboration with tech companies. The current analysis
            emphasizes audits performed by a public entity on in vitro diagnostic (IVD)
            manufacturers and laboratories.
            <?oxy_comment_start author="naylee" timestamp="20231210T214535-0600" comment="Somehwat re-wrote this paragraph on 12/11 after reading Rania&apos; comments above. This highlighted sentence needs to be removed entirely. It&apos;s not adding any value here, and the paragraph makes sense even without this sentence. "?>While
            the initial feedback with our stakeholders is positive, it could be made more
            comprehensive with the inclusion of SDOs’ process such as the interactions and
            influences between the various players with LOINC® and SNOMED International.
            <?oxy_comment_end?>Our documentation describes the context and business requirements to
            supplement these diagrams. </para>
        <para><xref linkend="DraftModeloftheDetailedLaboratoryEcosystemControlStructure"/> below
            illustrates the current draft model of the laboratory ecosystem control structure and
                <xref
                linkend="DraftInsetModeloftheEncodingforDataFlowintheLaboratoryEcosystemControlStructure"
            /> includes a specific draft depiction of the data flow for encoding. </para>
        <figure xml:id="DraftModeloftheDetailedLaboratoryEcosystemControlStructure">
            <title>Draft Model of the Detailed Laboratory Ecosystem Control Structure </title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/4.1.1%20image%201.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>In <xref
                linkend="DraftInsetModeloftheEncodingforDataFlowintheLaboratoryEcosystemControlStructure"
            />, “middleware” is currently in the model as an interface between devices and LIS/LIMS;
            however middleware can and does exist in between several other systems in this
            ecosystem. Additionally, “LIMS” are typically the source for reporting to public health
            agencies. </para>
        <figure
            xml:id="DraftInsetModeloftheEncodingforDataFlowintheLaboratoryEcosystemControlStructure">
            <title>Draft Inset Model of the Encoding for Data Flow in the Laboratory Ecosystem
                Control Structure </title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/4.1.1%20imgae%202.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Requirements</title>
        <para>This section details business requirements related to the data flow for encoding data
            in laboratory information for LISs, IVD vendors, and SDOs. These requirements are
            intended to help articulate control action scenarios and pinpoint specific scenarios in
            the safety assessment analysis in identifying unsafe control actions and loss scenarios
            related to the standards development, implementation, and maintenance processes in
            laboratories, devices, and standards. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Laboratories must document a comprehensive list of tests that
                they perform.</emphasis> Laboratories maintain a comprehensive test menu (also
            referred to ask a test catalog or laboratory test compendiums). These test menus contain
            the list of all tests performed by a particular lab and tests that are offered to
            consumers. The test menus are often delineated to include a list of tests that a
            particular analytical instrument is capable of performing. There are many details about
            tests that are important for laboratorians to understand and represent in test menus.
            These details are not limited to the following: name of the test, the component (or
            analyte) being measured, the specimen type, the property being measured, the timing of
            the measurement, the system (usually sample type for laboratory measurements), the scale
            of measurement, the method used to produce the observation, rejection and acceptance
            criteria, type of instrument used, specific make and model of instrument or kit used,
            testing priority, performing site, interpretation criteria, the individual responsible
            for interpretation, related diagnosis and other additional contextual information. </para>
        <para>Of these data elements, the name of each test is of particular importance because the
            name of the test is typically displayed in user interfaces and electronic messages and
            reports. Consequently, many of the contextual details listed above are reduced to and
            obfuscated by only being represented by the name of each test alone. </para>
        <para>The name of every test can be stored in laboratory information systems using local,
            institution-specific naming conventions. Ideally, laboratories can use a textual
            description with an unlimited number of characters to accurately describe each
            laboratory order and result. However, this can result in challenges due to field space
            restrictions and character limits of databases in the information system. Alternatively,
            “short names” may be pragmatically implemented to limit the characters allowed in
            textual names/descriptions of tests but can be complex with abbreviations that result in
            descriptions that are very difficult to interpret (e.g., albumin ser-plr fld-MCDiff,
            which refers to the mass concentration difference in grams per liter of albumin in serum
            and pleural fluid). [2] Rather than only having textual descriptions, laboratory
            information systems also use unique local identifiers (i.e., codes) to identify and
            store tests and results. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Laboratories are expected and, in many cases, required by the
                government to share data with public health institutions, medical centers, and
                disease registries to support population-based care, precision medicine,
            </emphasis>and research. </para>
        <para>Laboratories must be able to receive information about orders for tests and ensure
            that they are performing the equivalent test. Additionally, laboratories must be able to
            send information about tests performed and associated results and ensure they are
            sending results for the correct test that was ordered. However, use of local
            institution-specific names and local codes in LISs results in difficulty with
            interpreting the data and identifying equivalence between tests and results without a
            precise mapping to a common, universal terminology. </para>
        <para>Therefore, industry coding standards have been developed and required for use to
            standardize the codes and terms embedded in data exchange messages. Federal agencies,
            such as Center for Medicaid and Medicare Services (CMS) and Office of the National
            Coordinator for Health Information Technology (ONC), have worked in close coordination
            to define requirements in a joint effort to promote interoperability. The Health
            Information Technology for Economic and Clinical Health (HITECH) Act of 2009 grants ONC
            the authority to establish programs to promote the adoption of health technologies such
            as electronic health records and secure data exchange. Additional laws, including the
            ONC 21st Century Cures Act and CMS Interoperability and Patient Access Rule, identify
            specific standards as shown in HL7’s Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR)
            Release 4.0.1 to be adopted by industry. Many of these regulations are required for use
            in hospitals, but non-hospital laboratories are not as strictly required to adhere to
            the use of industry coding standards. </para>
        <para>The adoption of standards like LOINC® aid in distinguishing laboratory data among
            disparate health systems. However, reliance on standard laboratory test names alone does
            not go far enough in realizing the benefit of interoperability or minimizing loss
            scenarios. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Laboratories should reproducibly encode their test data using
                industry coding standards and assignment of standard codes should be subjected to a
                defined process across the code lifecycle. </emphasis></para>
        <para>Laboratories assign LOINC® codes to the local laboratory tests contained in their test
            menu. The LOINC® codes need to be mapped in the test definition dictionaries in the LIS.
            Typically, each laboratory makes its own decisions regarding assignment of LOINC® codes.
            If different teams are defining LOINC® codes for the LIS and the EHR, or using and
            storing codes outside of the EHR, there may be discrepancies even within the same
            institution. [2] </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Laboratories need to understand and be aware of the subtleties
                and pitfalls of test code selection that greatly impact the ability to map codes
                accurately to local test code compendiums.</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>For the best practice, a laboratory professional well-versed in LOINC® from the
            laboratory that is performing the testing should select the optimal LOINC® test order
            and result codes, as this person best knows the nuances of how the testing is performed.
            Downstream or upstream individuals often do not have the complete test details available
            to them, particularly with regards to testing performed at reference laboratories. In
            addition, nonlaboratory physicians and technical team members typically do not have
            adequate information to choose the optimal LOINC® codes correctly (unless the codes are
            provided by the performing laboratory). From a safety systems perspective, this is
            potentially a weak control that solely depends on a human controller to prevent loss
            scenarios and potential harms. </para>
        <para>Laboratory personnel responsible for mapping a laboratory’s local test compendium to
            LOINC® codes often do not possess adequate understanding or expertise for LOINC®,
            available full encoding options, and nuances between similar codes. For this reason,
            among others, the task of mapping a local test compendium to LOINC® is frequently
            delegated to information technology staff who, too, are inadequately trained in
            laboratory data standards and the implementation. [2] Electronic Health Record vendors
            and their staff interface engineers to build and test HL7 interfaces alongside lab
            personnel. However, the level of coordination between lab personnel and interface
            engineers varies from case to case. During interface testing for laboratory interfaces,
            the most common system errors result from incorrect LOINC® encodings within the OBR and
            OBX segments of an HL7 Version 2 transaction. The errors are most commonly addressed by
            information technology staff who in some cases prioritize time and effort over accurate,
            precise data mappings which can lead to poor due diligence and downstream loss
            scenarios. Similar process-shortcomings can apply to additional laboratory data elements
            which demand a certain level of domain expertise, like units of measure and specimen
            type. </para>
        <para>Despite having mapped their unique laboratory tests to LOINC®, laboratories may still
            need to rely on creating their own internal names and codes for test results. For
            example, laboratories may need to use a test code to distinguish glucose measurements
            performed in a core laboratory from those in their satellite facilities. [2] However,
            all these individual test codes will still need to be mapped to the appropriate, but
            identical, LOINC® code. Changes to LOINC® codes create challenges for maintenance in
            LISs, EHRs, and other systems, particularly when the LOINC® code changes for a test that
            has already been mapped. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Laboratories need to maintain code sets and mappings over time,
                which is an error-prone and manual, laborious process. </emphasis></para>
        <para>Requests for new codes can be made to Regenstrief Institute, the curator of the LOINC®
            database, through a simple process, and updates to LOINC® are made biannually. </para>
        <para>The LIS laboratory test definitions and dictionaries are dynamic and frequently
            changing, thus requiring a formal process for ensuring uniformity of coding among
            different instruments or methods and, if applicable, the capacity to accommodate
            different codes that are correctly applied depending on the specific methodology used
            for that particular result. There should also be a formal audit process and maintenance
            to keep up with the changes that occur with each LOINC® release to ensure the accuracy
            and appropriateness of previous code selection as the database continues to mature. [2] </para>
        <para>LOINC’s® limitations are poorly understood outside of the laboratory domain, reducing
            the potential utility for it. Critics of LOINC® will point out the laborious process for
            assigning the most correct code to each laboratory test offered, and that in practice,
            LOINC® codes are not uniformly assigned across laboratories. The complexities require a
            certain level of domain-expertise to understand two tests that may have the same
            correctly assigned LOINC® code may not necessarily have equivalence to allow for
            interoperability of their result data. </para>
        <para>Ideally, scripting and other automated methods must be developed to facilitate the
            task of assigning standard codes to local tests. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">IVD Manufacturers </emphasis></para>
        <para>The production of IVDs requires the assignment of the appropriate LOINC® code(s) for
            the specific tests which a given device can perform. LOINC® codes are typically in a
            manufacturer’s package insert, as well as their database. If an appropriate LOINC® code
            does not exist for a lab test, a manufacturer may submit a request to Regenstrief
            Institute to create a new LOINC® code. </para>
        <para>Many laboratory instrument and reagent vendors that are aware of the immense
            challenges associated with interoperability have begun to include LOINC® definitions in
            their package inserts. Such package inserts have become a logical source to provide
            information that can help laboratories map tests with an appropriate LOINC® code because
            these vendors are well equipped to identify the appropriate LOINC® code for their
            specific laboratory test. Moreover, for the introduction of novel laboratory test
            technology, IVD vendors are the logical respondent to new LOINC® code requests. </para>
        <para>The LOINC® to Vendor IVD specification provides LOINC® maps to IVD test results and
            includes the following important data attributes: the manufacturer, instrument model,
            unique device identifier, vendor transmission code, vendor specimen description, vendor
            result description, and test name. Optional data elements are also included to be
            helpful for laboratory professionals' mapping to LOINC®. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <para>The absence of laboratory semantic interoperability for IVD data has been cited as a
            significant impediment to safe and effective public healthcare. The erosion of accuracy
            for IVD test data due to interoperability failures can have patient safety consequences
            and impede timely access to and analysis of lab data on a nationwide or global scale.
            Differences in encoding laboratory data may have substantive differences in the level of
            granular detail they convey and contribute to challenges when operationalizing these
            data into patient care, data exchange, interoperability messages, and data aggregation.
            The aggregation and compounding of these types of interoperability failures can lead to
            erroneous conclusions and the potential for patient harm even when the correct LOINC®
            code is selected. A paper by Stram et al, highlights two laboratories that are both
            performing urinalysis and selected the same LOINC® code for the test, analyte, method,
            and instrument. [2] However, when the data was transferred from the LIS to EHR, the
            quantitative result of count/microliter was being translated to different units in the
            EHR and would have led to erroneous clinical treatment decisions based on the incorrect
            interpretation of the threshold for treatment. The use of accurate codes is not
            sufficient to guarantee that information exchange is accurate across the different
            levels in the laboratory data ecosystem. A research and development program that applies
            a System Safety approach to assess, measure, document, and analyze the data quality,
            integrity, agility, and reliability of the whole lab data ecosystem will be beneficial
            in promoting safe and effective laboratory medicine. Furthermore, a Knowledge Management
            Platform that is based on High Reliability Organization (HRO) principles and that offers
            an integrated and harmonized ecosystem for working across disparate standards will help
            with managing complexity and change management across standards. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>1. Wise, L., Miller, N., Warner, D. (n.d.). The role of CDI in Semantic
            Interoperability. The Role of CDI in Semantic Interoperability / AHIMA, American Health
            Information Management Association. Retrieved December 14, 2022, from
            https://bok.ahima.org/doc?oid=302470#.Y5on41HMKUk </para>
        <para>2. Michelle Stram, Tony Gigliotti, Douglas Hartman, Andrea Pitkus, Stanley M. Huff,
            Michael Riben, Walter H. Henricks, Navid Farahani, Liron Pantanowitz; Logical
            Observation Identifiers Names and Codes for Laboratorians: Potential Solutions and
            Challenges for Interoperability. Arch Pathol Lab Med 1 February 2020; 144 (2): 229–239.
            doi: https://doi.org/10.5858/arpa.2018-0477-RA </para>
        <para>3. Leveson, N. G. (2016). Engineering a safer world: Systems thinking applied to
            safety. The MIT Press. </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
