<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Data Transfer Solutions</title>
    <section>
        <title>Proficiency Testing and Interoperability Overview</title>
        <para>Laboratory proficiency testing (PT) participation is a requirement for performance of
            clinical testing under the Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments of 1988 (CLIA 88)
            to provide an important comparison and objective assessment of lab staff competencies,
            specimen handling, equipment functionality, and results reporting. PT is an external
            quality and accuracy assessment process that tests unknown specimens from a PT provider
            to ensure accurate laboratory results. After submitting test results, the laboratories
            receive data that compares their performance with that of other laboratories in their
            peer group (e.g., other laboratories that performed the same test on the same instrument
            and reagent platforms). The interoperability issues that make direct transmission
            results from the performing laboratory to quality organizations such as PT vendors
            challenging are very similar to the issues that laboratories face when they receive
            results from external laboratories through Health Information Exchanges (HIE) and HL7
            interfaces. Individual laboratories have always utilized their own local test codes,
            tests names, normal range values, and formats of test results and associated units. To
            compensate for this lack of standardization, PT vendors have had to implement a system
            of custom codes to standardize the representation of required data elements across
            result submissions from laboratories to allow them to perform their function of
            assessing the accuracy of results and comparing the performance of the subscriber
            laboratory to their peer groups of other laboratories utilizing the same instrumentation
            and reagents. Like HIE laboratory result transmission, being able to correctly interpret
            PT tests and determine equivalence of test results often requires more information than
            is currently available with most test result transmissions. Method information such as
            instrument and reagent information are not currently able to be captured or transmitted
            through Laboratory Information System (LIS) and Electronic Health Record (EHR) systems.
            The methodology information is not transmitted with the result and must be “married up”
            within the PT vendor information system when the PT result is received. Methodology
            information is stored in the PT vendor system and is often derived from historical
            reporting and must be manually changed by the subscriber laboratory whenever there is a
            change. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Current State Architecture </title>
        <para>When looking at possible future state architectures for the transfer of data between
            quality organizations it is important to examine the current state architecture of the
            solutions in place today. After further exploration, it becomes evident that it is quite
            different from that of a traditional interface utilized in a laboratory. Specifically,
            it is different in the way that the data is transferred, and how the data needs to be
            encoded before it gets to its ultimate destination. Please see below for a graphic of
            what the current architecture looks like for submitting results to a quality
            organization.</para>
        <para>While this narrative is meant to demonstrate a possible future state architecture for
            the transfer of data within quality organizations, part of the intention of this
            analysis is to take a close look at how data is currently transmitted. This document
            will also show how proficiency testing is currently disconnected from the laboratory
            interface ecosystem. It will look at some options that could be used to move the needle
            towards implementing standards, systems processes, and technical frameworks across the
            clinical and quality ecosystems that can better harmonize the approach to data
            transmission. </para>
        <para>The CAP currently employs two methods for direct transmission of PT results from a
            subscriber laboratory. One method utilizes a specially designed PT driver, embedded in a
            widely utilized Instrument Manager Middleware, and the other employs a Cloud-based Hub
            solution. When a PT sample is received by the subscriber laboratory from the PT vendor,
            laboratory personnel must place an order into the LIS system to register the PT
            specimen. This involves utilizing fields in the LIS system such as “Patient Name” to
            provide necessary information for the PT workflow, often using the name or code of the
            PT survey being conducted, as the specimen "Patient Name" entry. The PT specimen must
            then be analyzed in the same manner as any patient sample, for the indicated test. </para>
        <para>In the case of the instrument middleware transmission method, PT results generated by
            the instrument are automatically sent to the Instrument Manager, where the PT results
            are recognized using the PT survey code, translated, and reformatted by the specially
            designed PT driver. This process of translation and reformatting includes applying the
            custom codes developed by the PT vendor to identify the PT test in a standardized format
            regardless of local code and local test name conventions. </para>
        <para>For users of the Cloud-based Hub direct transmission method, laboratory personnel run
            a report in the LIS to extract and send PT results, using the PT survey code, to a
            folder on the laboratory’s network. The PT results are transferred to a Cloud-based Hub
            by agent software monitoring the folder. The PT results are translated and reformatted
            like the Instrument Manager Middleware method, with PT vendor developed custom codes
            applied, to identify data elements in a standardized format. </para>
        <para>The final step is the same for both the Instrument Manager Middleware and Cloud-based
            Hub and the formatted result file is transmitted to the PT vendor system where the PT
            results are automatically populated into the appropriate fields of the result form.
            Laboratory personnel can review results and to make changes such as correcting
            methodology prior to final submission. 
            <figure xml:id="CurrentHubIIE">
                <title>Current State Transmission Architectures</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/Current%20HUB%20DI%20IE.svg" scale="60" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Proficiency Testing Coding </title>
        <para>Although the use of custom codes by PT vendors solves some of the interoperability issues by allowing for aggregation of PT results from multiple laboratories regardless of local name and local code conventions, the PT transmission process is disconnected from the healthcare ecosystem because the custom codes utilized by PT vendors are never incorporated into LIS and EHR systems and are never transmitted outside of the PT direct transmission workflow. In 
            addition, each PT vendor has developed their own set of custom codes which allows for interoperability of results only 
            within their system</para>
        <para>Replacing PT developed vendor custom codes with existing standard ontology codes and incorporating these codes 
            into the LIS and EHR system would theoretically allow for interoperability beyond PT results, including for more 
            efficient downstream use of real patient data for public health and analytics once implemented in the clinical domain. 
            While this may sound like an easy proposition, many barriers stand in the way of widespread implementation. First, 
            there must be an authoritative source for standardized codes that is easily accessible to laboratories. The objective of the Laboratory Interoperability Data Repository (LIDR) is to digitally represent laboratory tests using standard 
            ontologies to fully define the test characteristics to allow for accurate interpretation and equivalence determination and 
            a shared understanding of the data as it moves across the healthcare ecosystem. Incorporation of the standard codes 
            into LIS and EHR systems should be as automated as possible with the codes easily accessible and transparent to 
            laboratory personnel for ease of maintenance. Further development and investment of resources needs to occur with 
            some of the coding systems to allow for new codes to be published at the speed of business to accommodate the 
            need of all data consumers. Lastly, the healthcare ecosystem infrastructure must be updated to support this paradigm 
            shift to ensure that all necessary codes needed to digitally represent laboratory tests are able to be captured and 
            seamlessly transmitted throughout the healthcare ecosystem without loss of information and meaning.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Future State Architecture</title>
        <para>Outlined below are some design ideas for how to transition from the current state
            architecture into a solution that is more closely aligned with how patient data is
            transmitted, which can then be modeled and utilized across various clinical, quality,
            and public health use-cases. The diagram below is meant to be a high-level architecture
            diagram of how technology and interfaces can be utilized, to help quality organizations
            consume data that has been encoded with LIDR. Its purpose is to consume individual
            tests/results coming from laboratories, as well as bulk tests/results to be able to
            provide feedback to the individual submitting laboratory and to the LIDR
            Repository.</para>
        <para>Currently, incorrect mapping of a subscriber laboratory test to custom code used by
            the PT vendor could result in the test being graded against the wrong criteria and the
            laboratory failing the challenge for that test. To avoid that situation, there is
            functionality and systems in place that allow for subscriber laboratories to evaluate
            whether the custom code mapping in the Instrument Manager Middleware and Cloud-based Hub
            solutions are accurate, prior to submitting survey results. Similar tools that could
            evaluate the standard coding provided by LIDR in the LIS and EHR would serve an
            important quality assurance function that would not only ensure that subscriber
            laboratories do not fail PT surveys due to mapping errors but would also improve the
            interoperability of transmitted patient data and the quality of real-work data.</para>
        <para>In addition, quality organizations could provide important feedback to the
            administrators of LIDR on any significant gaps in available coding for specific areas of
            laboratory testing (e.g., microbiology or molecular pathology). Harmonization of coding
            between vendors would be essential as PT vendors need to be able to aggregate similar
            tests across vendor platforms, as well as grading against specific vendor peer groups.
            PT vendors utilizing LIDR codes in place of custom codes could therefore provide
            important feedback on any conflicting coding between vendors for similar tests.</para>
        <para> The intent is that technology and workflows like the one proposed in this diagram
            will eliminate the need for custom mapping. Currently quality organizations and their
            customers often must do some type of mapping to accept incoming tests/results from a
            laboratory into the quality organization. With this process the goal is to have semantic
            interoperability between the laboratory and the quality organization, and hopefully
            expand interoperability to include patient results throughout the healthcare ecosystem.
                <figure xml:id="HighLevelLIDREncodedDataFlow">
                <title>High Level LIDR Encoded Data Flow</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/High%20Level%20LIDR%20Encoded%20Data%20Flow.svg"
                            scale="60" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        <para>In breaking this process down, some key points, assumptions, and areas that need
            further evaluation will be provided. In anticipation of socializing and analyzing this
            diagram, conversation will be initiated that will lead to thoughtful improvements as
            well as a more detailed picture of the specific workflow and technology that would be
            needed to stand up a proof of concept.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Future Considerations</title>
    
        <para>Below are some highlights, narrative, assumptions, and areas that need further
            consideration for this process:</para>
        <section>
            <title>Laboratory Information System (LIS) </title>
            <para>The first critical part of this workflow is when the LIDR is applied to the LIS.
                At this point we have assumed (but will need to clarify through the project) that
                the LIDR would be applied in one of three ways: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A real-time interface. As the LIDR is updated it flows into the LIS
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Third-party load. Either through a connection to a third-party database or
                        an import into the LIS. Similar concept to the way pharmacy loads
                        medications into the EMR</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Update the LIS manually. This would involve LIS staff manually updating
                        the compendium </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>Here are some things requiring evaluation as part of this process: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Do all the data elements that are part of LIDR exist in the LIS? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If not, is there a need to partner with LIS vendors to add fields? </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What are the pros and cons of these options? For example, is a benefit to
                        one of the automated solutions above that there are less errors in the
                        downstream part of this process? </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Interface</title>
            <para>If this data is transported over an interface, the standard used will need to be evaluated. It is known that most 
                laboratories are using HL7v2 for the traditional interfaces to reference labs and public health agencies. In addition, the 
                FHIR standard has gained traction and looks to be increasingly required to implement for specified use-cases under 
                the 21st Century Cures Act. There will be a need to evaluate how these different standards may be able to help the 
                transport of quality data. </para>
               <para>The interface solution that is ultimately utilized will need to have the
                flexibility to send standard data, send data elements that may not exist in the
                standard currently, and potentially string data together depending on what the need
                is from the “Validate and Normalize” process below. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Validate and Normalize </title>
            <para>The quality organization will evaluate the incoming data and consume that structured data. Determination will need to 
                be made if that is one piece of data or a concatenated string of data. In the current state it is a 1:1 mapping based on 
                test code. It will need to be evaluated if a single piece of data, such as the LOINC code would suffice, or if a 
                concatenation of multiple data elements together could be utilized and could be sent as a string of unique data. 
                Evaluation of the concatenated data string would need to occur, to determine where concatenation would happen 
                during the transfer of data from the LIS to the “Validate and Normalize” part of the workflow. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Valid</title>
            <para>Once the above work is completed, the data can then pass through the error management part of the workflow. If the 
                data is “Valid” it would be passed through for final consumption into the quality organizations ecosystem and be used 
                to complete the business process (e.g., PT, reporting, analytics). 
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Error Management </title>
            <para>If it does not pass the “Valid” check then it would need to go through the error
                management process and feedback would need to be provided. Feedback would be
                provided in the following ways: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A single lab has a missing or incorrect piece of information, but the
                        receiving party feels that the LIDR file is  correct. In this case feedback
                        would be given to the individual lab. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The receiving party receive codes and realize that the same instrument
                        from multiple laboratories is feeding data that is not correct. Feedback
                        would be provided to the LIDR repository. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>This process is meant to take bulk tests/results and process them. In this
                        case if any issues are found that feedback would be provided to the LIDR
                        repository</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>