<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Use Cases</title>
    <section>
        <title>Proficiency Testing and Interoperability Overview</title>
        <para>Laboratory proficiency testing (PT) participation is a requirement for performance of
            clinical testing under the Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments of 1988 (CLIA 88)
            to provide an important comparison and objective assessment of lab staff competencies,
            specimen handling, equipment functionality, and results reporting. PT is an external
            quality and accuracy assessment process that tests unknown specimens from a PT provider
            to ensure accurate laboratory results. After submitting test results, the laboratories
            receive data that compares their performance with that of other laboratories in their
            peer group (e.g., other laboratories that performed the same test on the same instrument
            and reagent platforms). The interoperability issues that make direct transmission
            results from the performing laboratory to quality organizations such as PT vendors
            challenging are very similar to the issues that laboratories face when they receive
            results from external laboratories through Health Information Exchanges (HIE) and HL7
            interfaces. Individual laboratories have always utilized their own local test codes,
            tests names, normal range values, and formats of test results and associated units. To
            compensate for this lack of standardization, PT vendors have had to implement a system
            of custom codes to standardize the representation of required data elements across
            result submissions from laboratories to allow them to perform their function of
            assessing the accuracy of results and comparing the performance of the subscriber
            laboratory to their peer groups of other laboratories utilizing the same instrumentation
            and reagents. Like HIE laboratory result transmission, being able to correctly interpret
            PT tests and determine equivalence of test results often requires more information than
            is currently available with most test result transmissions. Method information such as
            instrument and reagent information are not currently able to be captured or transmitted
            through Laboratory Information System (LIS) and Electronic Health Record (EHR) systems.
            The methodology information is not transmitted with the result and must be “married up”
            within the PT vendor information system when the PT result is received. Methodology
            information is stored in the PT vendor system and is often derived from historical
            reporting and must be manually changed by the subscriber laboratory whenever there is a
            change. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Current State Architecture </title>
    </section>
</chapter>