<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Document Describing the Data Transmission and Infrastructure</title>
    <para>The goal of this project is to explore and design ongoing quality control systems that
        would evaluate laboratories’ In Vitro Diagnostic (IVD) test coding.This document is intended
        to provide a detailed overview of the data transport of the required Laboratory
        Interoperability Data Repository (LIDR) Data Elements of clinical test results within these
        quality control systems.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Design Schematic</title>
        <para>The Detailed Design Schematic is a flow diagram, encompassing each area to which the
            data is transported as well as the steps taken within those receiving entities.</para>
        <figure xml:id="DetailedLIDRDataFlowSchematic">
            <title>Detailed LIDR Data Flow Schematic</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/Detailed%20LIDR%20Data%20Flow%20Schematic.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Detailed Narrative</title>
        <para>A detailed narrative has been developed to accompany the above scheme, breaking down the individual components of the flow into five distinctive receiving/sending systems: LIDR, IVD (In Vitro Diagnostic) Vendor, LIS (Laboratory Information System), Quality Organization and External Healthcare Entities (Interoperable patient results).</para>
        <section>
            <title>LIDR</title>
            <figure xml:id="LIDRDataFlowSchematic">
                <title>LIDR Data Flow Schematic</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/LIDR%20Data%20Flow%20Schematic.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The required data elements for the LIDR are the following:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Test Ordered analyte/observable (LOINC ®™)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Test Performed analyte/observable (LOINC ®™)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Specimen type (SNOMED CT ®™) at minimum</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Specimen source site (SNOMED CT ®™)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Specimen source site topography (SNOMED CT ®™)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Specimen collection method (SNOMED CT ®™)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Specimen additives (SNOMED CT ®™)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Additional data elements and standards necessary to enable full laboratory
                        data interoperability</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kit UDI</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Instrument UDI</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Harmonization Indicator</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Units of Measure (UCUM)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Qualitative data result values should be disseminated in SNOMED
                        CT®™</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <section>
                <title>LIDR Data Flow</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The IVD Vendor (manufacturer of the FDA approved test kit or
                            instrument) provides the codes to the LIDR, ensuring each of the
                            required elements are present.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The method of loading the IVD vendor provided codes to LIDR is an
                            upload, via an API (Application Programming Interface) created by the
                            LIDR Developer. There may need to be a separate interface for the IVD
                            vendor to receive feedback on errors and/or check for version
                            updates.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The LIDR developer must address the following potential gap:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Versioning of the LIDR File is required as it will be a
                                    compilation of ALL IVD Vendor’s test system and method data
                                    elements and will require updating when new testing methods are
                                    produced. As an immense entity with many contributors, it is
                                    critical that a method of managing the versions available to end
                                    users are maintained and updated at regular intervals or when
                                    emergent testing needs arise (e.g. pandemic test
                                    development).</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A proposed procedure for how versioning could occur is:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Vendor creates an initial version for all its systems, methods
                                    and tests and sends to LIDR via an interface.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>LIDR stores and adds to the aggregated list of vendor
                                    information and generates a version.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>LIDR sends the new updated version back to the IVD vendors
                                    using a set schedule of release dates at a set frequency (1x per
                                    month, 1 x per 6 months).</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>If the vendor makes an update to its own tests, it updates its
                                    version and sends to LIDR to update the aggregate file.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>An Emergency Release could be produced if there was a critical
                                    need but would require specific criteria to issue it.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>LIDR Loads Data Elements to the Laboratory’s LIS.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The route of data movement to the LIS can be either via a download
                            query from an LIS system or user, utilizing an API which is exposed, and
                            allows for real-time query, or through a file export which could then be
                            entered into the LIS manually or via an import.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The following gap must be addressed:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Both means of transport of the LIDR Elements would need to be
                                    developed by the LIDR developer.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The LIS users must be able to select the LIDR records that match their
                            test compendium and specific methods.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The LIDR also loads to the Quality Organization Intake Interface as
                            well as External Systems receiving patient lab test results, again, via
                            a real-time API or file export. (See Quality Organization Data Flow and
                            External Healthcare Entities Data Flow for gaps related to this).</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>LIDR receives feedback on vendor quality (Vendor Harmonization)
                            through a quality process.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>IVD Vendor</title>
            <figure xml:id="IVDVendorDataFlow">
                <title>IVD Vendor Data Flow</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/IVD%20Vendor%20Data%20Flow%20Schematic.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <section>
                <title>IVD Vendor Data Flow</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The IVD Vendor creates the records for the LIDR based on their
                            analyzer and reagent system testmenus. This forms the backbone of the
                            LIDR. (Please see the Required Elements list found in the LIDR Data flow
                            description).</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Thefollowing gap must be address:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The required elements of Kit UDI, Instrument UDI and
                                    Harmonization Indicator may requireinput/development from the
                                    LIDR, government entities, and standards setting
                                    organizations.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>TheIVD Vendor submits the specifics of the LIDR FILE for each
                            analyzer/test method and test result, including all required elements.
                            The file is uploaded via an API to the LIDR</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Feedback to the IVD vendor could be sent through an interface from the
                            LIDR, to receive version updates and, systemic errors identified through
                            the Quality Management process.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The IVD Vendor provides the LIDR elements to the Lab for the required
                            elements for the specific analyzer or test system. In order to ensure
                            these are maintained and updated accurately with the most recent
                            versions, the proposal is that they be embedded in the Instrument
                            Software.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The following gaps must be addressed:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The LIDR file must be uploaded to the Instrument. This way,
                                    the data could be stored on the Analyzer and is “pre-coded” for
                                    each analyte and included in the LIS (Lab Information System)
                                    interface specifications used for receiving orders and sending
                                    results for that analyzer.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>If the analyzer could store the LIDR, there might not be a
                                    need for labs to load and store it in their LIS, except for
                                    methods that are NOT analyzer specific. The order code mapping
                                    would, however, need to be mapped to the specific order codes in
                                    the LIS.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Software updates to the instrument or test method would need
                                    to be kept current, includingthe LIDR required elements and its
                                    versioning. Most analyzers have software that can be updated
                                    routinely from the vendor, often via a direct internet
                                    connection.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Quality Organization</title>
            <figure xml:id="QualityOrganizationDataFlow">
                <title>Quality Organization</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/Quality%20Organization%20Data%20Flow.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">The following assumptions are being made for data
                    transmission to the Quality Organization:</emphasis></para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Validate based on one piece of data from the LIDR – If a transmission of
                        results from an LIS system is sent, within a format of single required data
                        elements, these data elements can be validated by LIDR.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Expectation that the data structure from LIDR will be valid – LIDR, which
                        will be developedby a third party, must contain the required data elements
                        for every possible vendor/test method and test result.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The data fields that must be available can be found in the LIDR Recommended
                Elements section.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Quality Organization Data Flow</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The route of data movement in this section, begins with the transport
                            of test results from an LIS of a participating laboratory to the quality
                            organization intake interface.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The following gap needs to be addressed:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>In the ideal state the quality organization would intake data
                                    via an HL7 API Interface.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Prior to being sent onto the External Quality Organization’s
                            Ecosystem, the data is validated and normalized, ensuring it will file
                            successfully into the ecosystem.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Structural Validation of the data elements occurs within the quality
                            organization intake interface.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The following gaps need to be addressed:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>If it is validated within the quality organization intake
                                    interface, it requires the quality organizationintake interface
                                    to be able to receive the data elements from the LIDR. The
                                    intake interface must be designed to allow for LIDR Data
                                    Elements in a predefined format.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The LIDR Data elements load to the quality organization must
                                    be via a real-time interface.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the data is validated successfully, it is passed to the quality
                            organization ecosystem for analysis, metrics, and validation of the
                            business process.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The following gaps need to be addressed:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The quality system may need to be updated to allow for the new
                                    codes and formats.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Because there are more data elements than in the current
                                    state, the quality organization likely will need a new schema
                                    and would need to adapt a system to aggregate the data in order
                                    to identify the potential vendor related errors.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the data is not validated successfully, it routes through a Quality
                            Management process described in a later deliverable.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Lab Information System (LIS)</title>
            <figure xml:id="LISDataFlow">
                <title>LIS Data Flow</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/LIS%20Data%20Flow.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">The following assumptions are being made for LIDR load to
                    the LIS:</emphasis></para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LIDR is loaded from a Third Party – LIDR Development and creation is being
                        completed by a third party. Its repository needs to be able to receive
                        requests and return a response message, ideally via an interface to a
                        Laboratory’s LIS (Lab Information System).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LIDR Real-Time Interface – The interface would be real-time, meaning it is
                        accessible by any lab, IVD Vendor or LIS and can transmit data between the
                        recipient and the file.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LIDR as a reference to manually update – If a receiving system doesn’t
                        have the capability to interface, the LIDR file can be accessed to view the
                        required elements and queried for procedure specific definitions which can
                        be exported for the requestor to utilize as needed.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The data elements to load can be found in the LIDR Recommended Elements document.
                However, these are the additional required fields (which will be unique for each
                lab) that must be present in the individual LIS and must be provided as part of each
                patient result transmission.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ability to populate a Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)
                        certificate number and its laboratory name for each test kit/specimen which
                        identifies the actual performing CLIA certified laboratory.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ability to record the disposition and/or quality of the test performed
                        that do not meet the laboratory’s criteria for acceptability.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <section>
                <title>LIS Data Flow</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The route of data movement in this section, begins with the LIDR,
                            which contains the recommended elements.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Via a query from an LIS System or user, the records can be loaded to
                            the LIS, much like existing LIS systems can load and store LOINC codes,
                            CAP Synoptic Reports, and/or manually accessed for specified
                            procedures.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The download query can be via an API (which would need to be developed
                            by the LIDR developer) or through a file export which can then import to
                            the LIS.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The LAB must be able to select the records that match their test
                            compendium and specific methods.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The following gaps must be addressed:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>LIDR must be the source of truth of the most current version
                                    of Data Elements.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Because these files may be extremely large, it is critical
                                    that LIDR is developed with an interface to download the data to
                                    an LIS/EMR.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The lab must be able to load LIDR records specific to their
                                    test compendium and methods/instruments. Preferred method would
                                    be flowing from vendor to analyzer, followed by interface from
                                    LIDR to LIS and then the last method is a query to LIDR.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The LIS must be able to accept the elements even if the LIS or
                                    EMR already has the SNOMED or LOINC mapping present. (In current
                                    state, LOINC updates to an LIS/EMR may or may not be kept up to
                                    date).</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The LIS may not have the capability to use formatted codes
                                    directly from the LIDR files loaded to the LIS and an LIS
                                    Analyst may need to manually build the codes into the LIS,
                                    mapping them to the correct test codes and methods. Ability to
                                    query would be necessary.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>The LIS Vendor may need to create new fields to accommodate
                                    new LIDR elements.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>It is recommended that the IVD Analyzers receive the LIDR
                                    records specific to its test menu, pre-installation or via an
                                    update from an interface directly to the LIDR to the analyzers
                                    Programming Software. This might relieve some work on the part
                                    of the LIS analysts to map or encode the required elements,
                                    however there is a potential that this process would create a
                                    conflict between the version on the instrument and what is
                                    loaded in the LIS.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>It would be beneficial to engage a contact from the pilot
                                    lab’s Instrument and LIS Vendor to help investigate these
                                    ideas.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>If the LIS Vendor could work with the IVD Vendors to preload
                                    the required elements from LIDR (in both the analyzer and the
                                    LIS), it could shift the onus from the individual lab
                                    organization to these vendors, and would assist in ensuring more
                                    accurate and less discrepant versions of the required elements
                                    and thus improving interoperability.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>It is recommended that labs load only what applies to their
                            compendium. Once loaded to the LIS, an order is placed in the LIS for a
                            test procedure. The test order is sent to the analyzer or test method
                            for test performance.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>When the result of the test is completed, the result is transmitted
                            from the analyzer back to the LIS whereit is reviewed by
                            auto-verification rules or manually verified (completed) by a lab
                            tech.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Within the LIS, the LIDR elements are applied to the results prior to
                            being sent from the LIS to the Transmit Interface via an HL7 API.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The following gaps need to be addressed:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Depending on the LIS, there might be a need for a mapping
                                    table in the LIS or Interface Engine for sending lab test
                                    results, mapping the required elements to particular fields
                                    within the HL7 Message.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Discreet HL7 fields will need to be developed for the
                                    following data elements: UDI, harmonization indicator, specimen
                                    disposition by HL7.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The results are transmitted from the transmit Interface to external
                            systems’ intake interface or interface engine via an API. The required
                            elements of the results are validated for semantics against a LIDR file
                            available to the receiving system.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The following gap needs to be addressed:</para>
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Formatting of the interface from the LIS/EHR to the quality
                                    organization, must allow results from non-patient
                                    samples.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the data is deemed structurally valid, it is sent forward to the
                            organization’s ecosystem. If it is not, it would be rejected by the
                            intake interface of the receiving system.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Proposed Technical Elements for the Ideal State</title>
        <figure xml:id="LIDRTechnicalSchematic">
            <title>LIDR Technical Schematic</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/LIDR%20Technical%20Schematic.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Technical Connectivity between LIDR and IVD
                    Vendor:</emphasis></para>
            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                    <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Data Flow Segment</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Transmitted Data</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para><emphasis role="bold">Infrastructure</emphasis><emphasis
                                        role="bold">to</emphasis></para>
                                <para><emphasis role="bold">TransmitData</emphasis></para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">GAPS</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>IVD Vendor to LIDR</entry>
                            <entry>LIDR Elements definedby Vendor</entry>
                            <entry>Application Programming Interface that is real-time (Exposed
                                database).</entry>
                            <entry>Interface is determined by LIDR Developer.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>LIDR to IVD Vendor</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>LIDR Version updates</para>
                                <para>Qualityfeedback</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>Application Programming Interface</entry>
                            <entry>Interface is determined by LIDR Developer.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Technical Connectivity between LIDR and LIS:</emphasis></para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="4">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Data Flow Segment</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Transmitted Data</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Infrastructure to Transmit
                                Data</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">GAPS</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>LIDR to LIS</entry>
                        <entry>LIDR Elements/ LIDR Version updates</entry>
                        <entry>Application Programming Interface that is real-time (exposed
                            database).</entry>
                        <entry>Interfaceis determined by LIDR Developer.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Technical Connectivity between LIDR and Quality
                Organization:</emphasis></para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="4">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Data Flow Segment</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Transmitted Data</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Infrastructure to Transmit
                                Data</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">GAPS</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>LIDR to Quality Org</entry>
                        <entry>LIDR Elements/ LIDR Version Updates</entry>
                        <entry>Application Programming Interface that is real-time (exposed
                            database).</entry>
                        <entry>Interface is determined by LIDR Developer.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Quality Org Analytics Reports to LIDR</entry>
                        <entry>IVD Vendor Quality Feedback</entry>
                        <entry>Application Programming Interface</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Interface is determined by LIDR Developer.</para>
                            <para>May need to be an email process.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Technical Connectivity between IVD Vendor Instrument and
                LIS:</emphasis></para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="4">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Data Flow Segment</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Transmitted</emphasis>
                                <emphasis role="bold">Data</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Infrastructure to Transmit</emphasis>
                                <emphasis role="bold">Data</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">GAPS</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>IVD Vendor Instrument to LIS</entry>
                        <entry>ORDERs and LIDR encoded test results</entry>
                        <entry>Utilize interface engine (Data Innovations) or direct interfaces
                            within the LIS</entry>
                        <entry>Interface is Dependent on the LIS in use at the Individual
                            Lab</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Technical Connectivity between LIS and Quality
                Organization:</emphasis></para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="4">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Data Flow Segment</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Transmitted Data</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Infrastructure to Transmit
                                Data</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">GAPS</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>LISto Quality Org Intake</entry>
                        <entry>LIDR Encoded PT results</entry>
                        <entry>HL7 Format Interface or XML File</entry>
                        <entry>Dependent on the Quality Organization’s capabilities to receive via
                            interface.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Quality Org Intake to</para>
                            <para>Quality Org (Validation System)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>LIDR Encoded PT Results</entry>
                        <entry>Application Programming Interface</entry>
                        <entry>Dependent on the Quality Organization’s capabilities.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Quality Org (Validation System) to Quality Org Ecosystem</entry>
                        <entry>LIDR Encoded PT Results</entry>
                        <entry>Application Programming Interface</entry>
                        <entry>Dependent on the Quality Organization’s capabilities.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Quality Org (Validation</para>
                            <para>System) to LIS Transmit Interface</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Error Messages</entry>
                        <entry>HL7 Format Interface</entry>
                        <entry>Dependent on the Quality Organization’s capabilities.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        </section>
    <section>
        <title>External Healthcare Entitis (Patient Test Results)</title>
        <figure xml:id="PatientResultsDataFlowSchematic">
            <title>Patient Results Data Flow Schematic</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/Patient%20Results%20Data%20Flow%20Schematic.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>The data fields to load can be found in the LIDR Recommended Elements section.
            However, these are the additional required fields (which will be unique for each lab)
            that must be present in the individual LIS and must be provided as part of each result transmission.<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ability to populate a Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)
                        certificate number and its laboratory name for each test kit/specimen which
                        identifies the actual performing CLIA certified laboratory.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ability to record the disposition and/or quality of the test performed
                        that do not meet the laboratory’s criteria for acceptability.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ability to transmit the sample demographics including a specimen
                        identifier, collection date and time and other elements external systems may
                        require. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <section>
            <title>Patient Test Result Data Flow</title>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The route of data movement in this section, begins with the transport of
                        test results from an LIS to the transmit interface of a laboratory to
                        another Healthcare Organization, Physician Practice EMR or Department of
                        Public Health Intake Interface. All transmissions are via HL7 API.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Prior to being sent onto the External Organization’s Ecosystem, the data
                        is validated and normalized, ensuring it will file successfully into the
                        ecosystem.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Validation of the data elements occur within the Intake Interface
                        Engine.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Thef ollowing gap needs to be addressed:</para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If it is validated within the Intake Interface, it requires the
                                Intake Interface or EMR/LIS to be able to receive the data elements
                                from the LIDR as a real-time Interface</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If the data is validated successfully, it is passed to the external
                        organization ecosystem for integration to the business process which would
                        allow for successful interoperability of lab test results.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The following gaps need to be addressed.</para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The receiving EMR/LIS system may need to be updated to allow for
                                the new codes and formats.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Because there are more data elements than in the current state,
                                the LIS/EMR Vendors likely will need to develop a new schema.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If the data is not validated successfully, it is rejected, and
                                error messages are sent back to the sending labs interface for error
                                resolution and resubmission of test results.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    
              
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
