<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Ecosystem</title>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose of a Retrospective and Industry Evaluation</title>
        <para>In today’s healthcare ecosystem, there is a need for high-quality and accurate data as
            healthcare organizations becoming increasingly reliant on EHRs, laboratory information
            systems (LISs), and other electronic information systems. Terminology standards are a
            primary tool that many organizations use to work towards this goal and improve the
            quality and accuracy of their data. Terminology standards aim to ensure information is
            captured and represented in a repeatable and standardized format so that other
            organizations and stakeholders using said terminology standard have a common
            understanding of the data. While terminology standards are a useful tool, extensive
            knowledge management (KM) is needed to identify, manage, and share the standardized data
            that these systems and standards capture. However, as data flows within and between
            healthcare systems, the use of different terminology standards, KM processes, and
            systems themselves can pose a threat to the integrity of data.</para>
        <para>IKM is an approach to data management that aims to maintain the meaning, integrity,
            and quality of data as it travels within and between healthcare systems. IKM is an
            evolving approach to manage disparate terminology standards using a common, centralized,
            and repeatable representation of data. The use of a common model supports the
            interoperability of data between disparate terminology standards, well documented
            version control even when different terminology standards employ their own versioning
            practices, and the incorporation of new or emerging terminology standards. IKM will use
            an iterative approach to build upon previous work on Resource Description Frameworks
            (RDFs) and property graphs with novel ideas and concepts. There is no reference or best
            practice guide for how an IKM solution can or should operate and will therefore require
            extensive research, prototyping, and development. </para>
        <para>While IKM may pose as a daunting task for many organizations due to the large barrier
            to entry and resource commitment, our team is not the only stakeholder working towards
            IKM solutions. SNOMED CT® and LOINC® have announced a collaborative partnership to
            increase the interoperability of their data and standards by facilitating the
            identification of synonymous concepts and reducing duplication in the standards. Our
            work prototyping and trialing an IKM reference implementation has given us insight into
            various challenges, work arounds, and best practices. Our work has identified functional
            and non-functional areas of IKM that require further exploration and refinement to
            support more widespread adoption, which can be shared with other organizations and
            stakeholders to shape their work and support a unified approach.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Summary of Findings – Functional and Non-Functional Issues Related to Knowledge
            Management Proof of Concept</title>
        <para>Over the past year, our team has been working to develop an IKM reference
            implementation, Komet, to demonstrate IKM capabilities. Our work with Komet builds upon
            data property graph and RDF foundations and incorporates new concepts like versioned
            concept-oriented property graph representation. Due to the relatively novel nature of
            Komet and IKM, our team did not have guidelines or best practices to follow. Our initial
            work serves as a prototype that identifies functional and non-functional areas related
            to IKM that should be further explored. Throughout our experience, we have documented
            the following lessons learned, best practices, and challenges to improve the
            adoptability, functionality, and development of IKM as our team and other stakeholders
            work towards future iterations.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Management</title>
            <para>The team rapidly developed an IKM prototype leveraging the latest Tinkar data
                model standard to showcase IKM capabilities at the SNOMED CT® conference in October
                of 2023. Through the effort over the past year and leading up to that event, we’ve
                identified a few findings that have been resolved or will need to be resolved in the
                future.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Requirements</title>
                <para>As each clinical terminology standard has its own proprietary data
                    representation and tooling to both view and author data, the ability to
                    represent multiple standards with a common underlying data model and view or
                    author across standards in a single environment is an unprecedented idea. IKM
                    would influence a large community of users, such as hospitals, laboratories and
                    clinical informaticists so there are many thoughts and opinions about how IKM
                    should work and what features would be important. Though the potential
                    stakeholder base is large, the access to the community to illicit requirements
                    is very limited. While we were able to conduct user interviews during our UI/UX
                    analysis to gain some understanding of necessary system functionalities, we do
                    have not regular access to those participants. </para>
                <para>To solve for this, we’re leveraging experts to identify high priority
                    capabilities that will be prioritized for upcoming milestones. These milestones
                    will take shape in the form of conferences, community events, and other
                    demonstration opportunities. For example, we plan to organize a Health Level
                    Seven (HL7) Connect-a-thon event to conduct real-world testing scenarios with
                    interested stakeholders.</para>
                <para>Leading up to the SNOMED CT® conference, we found that while we wanted to
                    support rapid development, we still needed a clear understanding of what system
                    capabilities were important to showcase for the demonstration and detailed
                    documentation in the form of user stories for the developers to reference. </para>
                <para>As seen in the figure below, we established a new process to describe the
                    system capabilities in the form of Agile epics and plot them against the
                    appropriate milestones to generate our product feature backlog. As per agile
                    development best practices, these epics are revisited weekly to be defined,
                    refined, and prioritized. These epics are then decomposed into user stories with
                    defined acceptance criteria for the development teams to develop against in 3
                    week increments or sprints. [1]</para>
                <figure xml:id="IKMProductBacklogEpicBoard">
                    <title>IKM Product Backlog Epic Board</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/IKM%20Product%20Backlog%20Epic%20Board.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                    <para>As the IKM community grows, we will leverage the open-source nature of the
                        project to track feature requests through submitted GitHub issues. [2] This
                        external issue tracker will be integrated more fully in the future but will
                        allow us to track feature requests against other priorities and communicated
                        releases back to the IKM community. [3]</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>User Experience and User Interface (UI/UX) Design</title>
                <para>In early 2023, a UI/UX assessment for IKM was conducted by Deloitte/Amplified
                    to better understand the needs and pain points of healthcare professionals in
                    their daily operations working with healthcare knowledge. The goal was to use
                    findings from the assessment to determine user profiles, requirements, and
                    priority, which were then used to strategize a human centered UI/UX design for a
                    Next Gen IKM platform that promotes data interoperability. </para>
                <para>The assessment was conducted in five phases:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A landscape analysis to evaluate the competitive landscape of similar
                            products.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A heuristic evaluation of the old Komet version to identify features
                            to keep in the Next Gen version.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>User interviews with multiple professionals in the healthcare
                            space—such as clinicians, health informaticists, public health
                            scientist—to uncover specific needs and pain points of potential
                            users.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A UI/UX workshop to discuss findings from interviews and align on
                            future UI/UX strategy.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Creation and prioritization of user stories for future sprints based
                            on workshop results.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>Some of the challenges faced by the UI/UX team include representing different
                    knowledge standards with different requirements for viewing/editing in a
                    standardized way, abstracting complexities behind-the-scenes for an easier user
                    experience and designing in a way that supports iterative development while
                    still meeting future requirements.</para>
                <para>The team plans to tackle these challenges by identifying commonalities and
                    differences between user interfaces and data schema of existing knowledge
                    standards. The aim of these planned activities is to better understand how to
                    design a standard UI and conduct periodic user evaluation sessions for voluntary
                    user feedback within the healthcare industry. Healthcare stakeholders can help
                    the UI community explore the latest design and share insightful information in
                    the user experience. They can also influence the process of building modular and
                    re-usable UI components that allow flexible and adaptable development in an
                    agile environment with changing requirements.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>DevOps Processes</title>
                <para>In the current state of health IT, healthcare data standard organizations have
                    implemented restrictive licensing around their proprietary data and technology
                    which creates siloes and the inability to collaborate across standards. IKM
                    provides an open-source solution that could be used across the community to
                    collaborate and further reduce these data siloes. Komet is an open-source
                    solution in the form of an installed Java application that provides users the
                    ability to visualize, manage and extend disparate medical terminologies.
                    [4]</para>
                <para>Early in the development phase, we identified that we would need to make an
                    investment in DevOps technologies and tooling to allow our open-source solutions
                    to be rapidly developed and released to reach the largest audiences possible. We
                    began by hosting our DevOps tools, as it was the quickest way to begin rapid
                    prototyping. However, through this process, we’ve found that the hosting of
                    these tools requires more overhead and manhours than we would like. Our larger
                    goals and priorities require developers’ time to contribute to our solutions
                    rather than supporting our DevOps tools. We are currently investigating and
                    analyzing different alternative approaches to move to Software-as-a-Service
                    (SaaS) solutions for DevOps.</para>
                <para>Additionally, due to the licensing issues around proprietary data, as well as
                    other open-source technologies, we leverage both an internal and external code
                    repository. This arrangement allows us to continue development while we work
                    through licensing with the goal of becoming fully open-source. [5] Currently,
                    this complication keeps us from leveraging open-source supported tooling and
                    requires us to support complex DevOps processes to restrict the publishing of
                    code. Once these license issues are resolved, we’ll be able to leverage
                    additional tools to streamline and simplify our processes.</para>
                <para>However, our DevOps processes are largely successful as we’re able to
                    collaboratively develop across a large team and release both code and artifacts
                    to our public repository often and with little manual effort. Additionally,
                    every promotion to GitHub releases Windows, Mac and Linux versions of the Komet
                    installer to be available to the community for use.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Data Layer Development</title>
                <para>As new knowledge standards are transformed and introduced to the Tinkar Core,
                    the more the need for ease of code troubleshooting and management becomes
                    apparent. [6] Reinforcing the code to also handle different types of data and
                    types of programming languages will also keep the data ingestion and export free
                    of conflicts. Additionally, adding in a layer of abstraction is needed to allow
                    all types of users to set up and use Komet. For large scale development and
                    automation to be possible these improvements to code and architecture will be
                    crucial. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Bindings</title>
                <para>Currently, Tinkar Core uses Tinkar Terms to call certain Java variables that
                    represent retrievable concepts from the Tinkar datastore. As the codebase
                    develops and changes, these can be difficult to maintain, especially when more
                    complexity is added. Each Tinkar Term affected must be manually identified and
                    changed if needed. Not only is it time consuming, but it can be susceptible to
                    human error. By creating an automated solution like a bindings library, updates
                    will be made efficiently and can be integrated into a dependency management
                    system. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Protocol Buffers</title>
                <para>With the requirement of being able to support many types of information
                    systems, the ingestion of data requires a programming language neutral format.
                    Protocol buffers solve this issue, by serializing the structure data with a
                    format that supports many programming languages. Additionally, it is open-source
                    code and does not require a licensing to implement. This would allow the data to
                    be exported in easy to share formats that can be simply shared and imported.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Data Retrieval and Curation</title>
                <para>As the Komet users increase, adoption of the tool will need to accommodate a
                    variety of experienced users. Currently, the Tinkar database requires a
                    significant amount of coding and or prior knowledge of lower-level data
                    structures to successfully retrieve and manipulate Tinkar data elements. This
                    inevitably limits the immediate number of users who can implement meaningful
                    solutions using Komet and the Tinkar data. Creating an abstraction layer and or
                    user experience that allows users to have an easier and streamlined approach
                    working with and updating Tinkar data will result in users utilizing the Komet
                    to its full potential. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Solution Adoption</title>
           
            <para>To date, the IKM Solution Adoption team has worked to identify key stakeholders
                and tailor content to their understanding of  the goals of IKM. In this phase of
                increasing awareness, the team has developed and disseminated informational
                presentations and trainings both internally and externally to federal and industry
                partners. Through this and additional presentations and demos of Komet at industry
                conferences (i.e., SNOMED International Expo, American Medical Informatics
                Association), the team has been able to identify champions for the IKM movement
                across the ecosystem. As awareness has increased, the team has been able to maintain
                stakeholder relationships through personalized communications to individual
                stakeholders at organizations of significance (i.e. Food and Drug Administration,
                Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology, Graphite
                Health, Royal College of Pathologists of Australasia).. [8] Through such
                engagements, the team has recognized the following key findings of developing
                successful communications that will propel the efforts up the communications curve
                trajectory. </para>
            <para>Through such engagements, the team has recognized the following key findings of
                developing successful communications that will propel the efforts up the
                communications curve trajectory. </para>
            <section>
                <title>Curating Technical Communications</title>
                <para>There is a need in IKM communications to provide adequate technical guidance
                    for stakeholders interested in collaboration and/or integration. Therefore, the
                    development of proper processes and documentation of work has been critical to
                    the IKM strategic communications efforts and will continue to be strengthened as
                    we move towards driving engagement.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Defining Integrated Knowledge Management</title>
                <para>Integrated Knowledge Management is an evolving and novel movement in the
                    healthcare information technology field. Therefore, communicating to all
                    potential stakeholders effectively on the mission to increase cohesion in health
                    data standards and what problems that it may solve is paramount to advancing the
                    movement.
                    Based on
                    feedback from stakeholder engagement sessions, the team has been iteratively
                    refining strategic communications initiatives to develop concise and aimed
                    messaging to key stakeholders.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Ensuring End User Adoption</title>
                <para>A more nuanced challenge that the IKM movement faces as technologies and
                    integration methods develop into end-user capabilities is the adoption and
                    implementation of these tools by the end-users themselves, whether they are
                    clinicians, healthcare organizations, laboratories, or other healthcare-related
                    entities. Many of these end-users may not have the technical background or
                    insight into the issues that IKM addresses and aims to solve and therefore may
                    not fully be invested in adopting such a solution into their operations. </para>
                <para>As future efforts in the Integrated Knowledge Management space are advanced,
                    there will be an increased need for intentional strategies centered around
                    communications to the various stakeholders that IKM impacts to ensure engagement
                    and ultimate adoption. Technical professionals in the data standards field will
                    need to have transparent and detailed information on the methodologies used in
                    previous efforts in order to continuously improve upon the collaborative
                    process. Further, end-user specific communication plans will be developed that
                    articulate both the problems that IKM attempts to solve along with a clear
                    explanation about the tools’ capabilities. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Representation</title>
            <para>data and the connections between tables [15]. Also, descriptions of data
                structures and constraints are included, allowing storage of a description of its
                own structure within the database. While this self-describing approach is reference
                terminology-agnostic, making it capable of accommodating various data sources,
                challenges for determining the importance of terminology-specific data components
                are introduced [16].</para>
            <para>Representing data properties such as concepts, patterns, or semantics becomes a
                complex task, especially when importing data from multiple terminology standards. As
                clinical reference terminologies, SNOMED CT® and LOINC® employ different data
                structures to represent their respective content. These data structures do not
                translate easily between terminologies. SNOMED CT® utilizes Concepts, Descriptions,
                and Relationships, organized hierarchically to convey clinical meanings to its
                terms. LOINC® codes are represented by five or six main parts. And hierarchical
                relationship between LOINC® terms is manually applied outside of the LOINC® SNOMED®
                Collaboration. The components from each of these terminologies may function as
                crucial data structure components for axioms and related data properties within the
                database. [9]</para>
            <para>Once imported into a self-describing data structure, determining equivalence with
                another terminology standard or which parts of the data components are important may
                create unanticipated challenges [15]. Unlike more specific terminology models,
                Tinkar lacks pre-defined references to identify crucial components or properties
                within incoming data, necessitating a comprehensive understanding of the dataset.
                This challenge extends to determining the importance or equivalence of specific data
                components, prompting the creation of new properties and concepts before the data
                can be seamlessly imported into Tinkar. While the generic nature of Tinkar provides
                valuable flexibility for accommodating diverse data standards, it underscores the
                need for a proactive and nuanced approach to customization. This adaptability allows
                Tinkar to serve as a versatile platform capable of handling a variety of data
                sources, but it also highlights the importance of thoughtful customization to ensure
                effective integration. [6]</para>
            <para> </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Evaluation of Current SNOMED® LOINC® Collaboration</title>
        <para>In October 2022, Regenstrief Institute (RII) and SNOMED International, also known as
            International Health Terminology Standards Development Organization (IHTSDO), signed a
            cooperative agreement to collaborate the work between LOINC® and SNOMED CT®. This will
            eliminate duplicative data, allowing the two terminologies to be used together by
            creating an extension of the SNOMED CT® with the LOINC® knowledge standard included.
            Using the SNOMED CT® formats and concepts, the LOINC® knowledge standard will be more
            defined and accessible. [10]</para>
        <para>The SNOMED LOINC® Collaborative Agreement indicates a pivotal progression towards data
            interoperability as the two organizations are industry leaders in health data standards
            and terminology. [11] We conducted an analysis of the current state of the collaboration
            project to better understand the successes and pain points as well as assess how IKM may
            provide additional solutions.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Management: SNOMED® LOINC® Collaborative Agreement Demonstration
                Project Progress Reports </title>
            <para>The SNOMED LOINC® Collaborative Agreement is a critical first step forward towards
                data interoperability and a testament towards the collective need for collaborative
                solutions. As described on the website, the LOINC® Ontology can be accessed in two
                ways: through a full data download of the LOINC® Ontology file or viewable through
                the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser. The browser provides the same capabilities
                of the SNOMED CT® browser but provides visibility to LOINC® data through the
                appropriate search or query. The website, while brief, provides additional
                information to the community such as release notes, frequently asked questions, and
                the ability to provide feedback and sign up to receive project updates. [11]</para>
            <para>Regarding Knowledge Management, our analysis will be focused on the systems and
                services provided by the LOINC® and SNOMED CT® Interoperability Solution as
                described on their website. [12] The analysis of the user interface / user
                experience will be discussed in section <emphasis role="bold">UI/UX: SNOMED LOINC
                    Collaborative Agreement Demonstration Project Progress Reports</emphasis> and
                analysis of the data representation implications are expanded on in section<emphasis
                    role="bold">Knowledge Representation: SNOMED LOINC Collaborative Agreement
                    Demonstration Project Progress Reports</emphasis>. Further details regarding the
                communications to the community is discussed in section <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Ecosystem Engagement: SNOMED LOINC Collaborative Agreement Demonstration
                    Project Progress Reports </emphasis>.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Hearing from the Community</title>
                <para>The LOINC® and SNOMED CT® Interoperability Solution encourages the community
                    to provide input to help inform how the solution will proceed. [11] Responders
                    can provide their perspective related to content, releases and use case.
                    Additionally, responders can leverage the feedback form to ask questions.</para>
                <figure xml:id="ScreenshotofFeedbackPageonLoincSnomedWebsite">
                    <title>Screenshot of Feedback Page on loincsnomed.org</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Screenshot%20of%20Feedback%20Page%20on%20LoincSnomed%20Website.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>Community involvement is a key to ensure the solutions that are being made available meet the needs of the users. Similarly, IKM provides the ability for users to provide feedback through GitHub issues. GitHub provides custom form layouts to give users the best experience for submitting technical and non-technical issues or questions. [12]</para>
                <figure xml:id="ScreenshotofGitHubNonTechnicalIssueSubmissionPage">
                    <title>Screenshot of GitHub Non-Technical Issue Submission Page</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Screenshot%20of%20GitHub%20Non%20Technical%20Issue%20Submission%20Page.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Complications in Community Visibility</title>
                <para>Though the LOINC® and SNOMED CT® Interoperability Solution collects community
                    feedback and issues, there is no visibility into that information. Community
                    members have no insight into what ideas and questions have already been
                    submitted. Furthermore, there is no visibility into what feedback will be acted
                    upon or what questions have been answered. According to GitHub, a leader in
                    open-source community best practices, keeping communication public is key so
                    that all members have access to the same information. [11]</para>
                <para>IKM provides the ability for all issues submitted to be visible. The team can
                    provide transparent updates, such as commenting to answer questions, assigning
                    the issue for work, or assigning the issue to a milestone for release. This will
                    allow the issue creator and the rest of the community to have full insight into
                    when the issue may be addressed.</para>
                <figure xml:id="ScreenshotofGitHubIssueScreen">
                    <title>Screenshot of GitHub Issue Screen</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Screenshot%20of%20GitHub%20Issue%20Screen.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>UI/UX: SNOMED® LOINC® Collaborative Agreement Demonstration Project Progress
                Reports </title>
            <para>Through their collaborative agreement, LOINC® and SNOMED CT® have developed the
                LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser, which allows users to navigate concepts, view
                concept details, and determine equivalency between LOINC® and SNOMED CT® concepts.
                [10] This is an important development for the medical terminology field because it
                represents a move toward achieving interoperability. The collaboration data set and
                supporting browser tool, while useful, is a work in progress and has some user
                challenges in its current state.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Utilizing Search in the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser</title>
                <para>From a user perspective, navigating through the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT®
                    browser to locate and view concepts is done in two primary ways: searching by
                    typing or navigating the taxonomy. [10] Using the built-in search engine, the
                    user can find results with as few as three letters. The search results
                    automatically update as the user types, so there is no need to hit “Enter”, just
                    edit the input field and wait for the results to refresh.</para>
                <para>In addition to the search bar, the search option also includes a list of
                    filters to narrow search results as shown on the left side of the image below.
                    Prior to entering text in the search bar, only the four green filter options and
                    the “Group by concept” checkbox appear. After entering text, additional filters
                    appear, which are filtering by: language (e.g., English), semantic tag (e.g.,
                    observable event), module (SNOMED CT® core vs. LOINC® Extension module), and
                    refset (e.g., Web Ontology Language
                    [OWL]
                    axiom reference set). [13]</para>
                <figure xml:id="LOINCOntologySNOMEDCTBrowserSearchFilters">
                    <title>LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser Search Filters</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/LOINC%20Ontology%20SNOMED%20CT%20Browser%20Search%20Filters.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>The user can also navigate through concepts using the taxonomy structure in
                    the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser. In the default "Perspective”, the
                    taxonomy structure lists all SNOMED CT® observable entity concepts in
                    alphabetical order. If the user changes the “Perspective” to “Comparing
                    Hierarchy”, the system displays a more robust taxonomy of SNOMED CT® concepts,
                    as shown below. The user can then navigate the hierarchy to find concepts. The
                    user cannot currently view and navigate the equivalent LOINC® hierarchy.</para>
                <figure xml:id="TaxonomyStructureintheLOINCOntologySNOMEDCTBrowser">
                    <title>Taxonomy Structure in the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Taxonomy%20Structure%20in%20the%20LOINC%20Ontology%20SNOMED%20CT%20Browser.svg" align="center" scale="25"></imagedata>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>In the current state, the user experience in searching and navigating the
                    LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser can be improved by improving the default UI
                    settings, allowing the user to edit the views to fit their needs, and adding the
                    ability to search and navigate within LOINC® data specifically. In the default
                    UI, some features are hidden from the user and may require time and effort to
                    uncover them. Surfacing functional user settings will enhance user
                    experience.</para>
                <para>Noted improvements can be made to search to enhance the function and
                    experience. Improving the search user interface, making search and navigation
                    more intuitive (e.g., filters, taxonomy), and optimizing page space use will
                    enhance the tool’s usability. The image below demonstrates what an optimized
                    search function might look like for an Integrated Knowledge Management tool. The
                    view below is simplified and clean but simultaneously more functional and
                    user-friendly. [14]</para>
                <figure xml:id="HypotheticalOptimizedSearchFunction">
                    <title>Hypothetical Optimized Search Function</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Hypothetical%20Optimized%20Search%20Function.svg" align="center"  scale="50"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Viewing a Concept and its details in the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT®
                    Browser</title>
                <para>Upon selecting a concept to view within the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT®
                    browser, the Concept Details tab on the right side of the screen displays
                    information pertaining to that concept. The initial view is the Summary tab that
                    displays parent/child information within the SNOMED CT® hierarchy as well as
                    LOINC® equivalents (if applicable). The other tabs, Details, Diagram,
                    Expression, Refsets, Members, History, and References provide further
                    information on the concept. [15]</para>
                <figure xml:id="ViewoftheSummaryTab">
                    <title>View of the Summary Tab</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/View%20of%20the%20Summary%20Tab.svg" scale="30"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>In addition, there is a settings button in the upper right corner of the
                    Concept Details window that allows the user to change some settings to their
                    preference. This type of customizable functionality is needed for a tool that
                    will be so widely used across fields. [15]</para>
                <figure xml:id="ConceptDetailsWindow">
                    <title>Concept Details Window</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Concept%20Details%20Window.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>These features provide the user a functional view of concepts in a
                    straightforward manner, but there stands room for improvement. For example, most
                    tabs of a given concept do not present useful or novel information, if they have
                    information at all. Notably, after searching through dozens of concepts, this
                    team was unable to locate one that had information in the History tab. Because
                    the team was unable to locate a concept with a populated history, it was not
                    clear whether this functionality was not yet available or simply empty. It would
                    benefit the user to communicate more clearly which concepts are missing
                    information. For future implementations, developers of similar tools can look to
                    prioritize communication with the user, so that it is clear to the user what
                    they are seeing (and not seeing). [13]</para>
                <figure xml:id="HistoryTabofConceptDetails">
                    <title>History Tab of Concept Details</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/History%20Tab%20of%20Concept%20Details.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Utilizing the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser for Purpose and
                    Contributing</title>
                <para>The LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® browser, a collaborative effort between LOINC®
                    and SNOMED CT®, seemingly relies disproportionately on the SNOMED CT® dataset.
                    In fact, finding equivalency between concepts may be best executed if the user
                    already knows the existing LOINC® concept and needs to find the equivalent
                    SNOMED CT® concept. Trials in finding LOINC®-equivalents using SNOMED® concepts
                    often proved fruitless as many SNOMED® concepts did not produce a LOINC®
                    equivalent. Upon finding a concept that has a LOINC® equivalent, the indication
                    is rather small and does not provide a great deal of information, as shown
                    below. [13]</para>
                <figure xml:id="LOINCOntologySNOMEDCTBrowserIndicationofEquivalence">
                    <title>LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® Browser Indication of Equivalence</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/LOINC%20Ontology%20SNOMED%20CT%20Browser%20Indication%20of%20Equivalence.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>To enhance the existing system, there should be a more complete record for concepts, including the ability to view how they have changed over time. An example of how this could be done in an integrated knowledge management system is shown below.</para>
                <figure xml:id="ExampleofHypotheticalConceptsVersioningRecord">
                    <title>Example of Hypothetical Concepts Versioning Record</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Example%20of%20Hypothetical%20Concepts%20Versioning%20Record.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>While the current system relies heavily on the SNOMED CT® hierarchy, the
                    system must look ahead to not favor one terminology over another and allow the
                    user to search all terminologies. LOINC® terminologies should have a larger
                    presence within the tool, so that it is easier to navigate concepts and
                    determine equivalence without needing significant background knowledge. [9] </para>
                <para>Using and navigating the LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® browser requires the
                    creation of an account. This account, however, does not allow the user to make
                    contributions to the platform, only view data. Editing the tool and terminology
                    requires access to a separate system, which is a barrier to potentially valuable
                    contributions. Specialized tools like this one are better off when they capture
                    the expertise of the individual user through open-source collaboration rather
                    than restricting editing rights. </para>
                <para>The image below captures what collaboration within an IKM tool might look
                    like. Allowing users to edit and contribute increases the knowledge base and the
                    momentum at which the tool itself improves. </para>
                <figure xml:id="HypotheticalIKMToolingCollaboration">
                    <title>Hypothetical IKM Tooling Collaboration</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Hypothetical%20IKM%20Tooling%20Collaboration.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>The LOINC® Ontology SNOMED CT® browser is a useful tool that can be improved by focusing on the end user to improve UI/UX. Improvements and enhancements to the tool’s user experience will be a key component to its long-term viability.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED LOINC Collaborative Agreement Demonstration Project Progress Reports </title>
            <para>While the success of the technical integration is critical, of equivalent
                significance is the organization’s ability to communicate about its efforts to
                enable awareness and adoption of the newly integrated model. Evaluating the
                partnership’s solution adoption efforts against the communications strategy of the
                IKM movement can provide indicators of success. </para>
            <section>
                <title>Achievements in Technical Communications</title>
                <para>Similar to the  need for technical communications, the ontology browser
                    homepage links to the documentation release, providing an introductory technical
                    explanation of the processes utilized to link the two data standards. The
                    release includes details on the content inclusions of the browser, modeling
                    guidelines used to integrate standards, concept/attribute representation, and
                    future steps that the technical partnership will embark on to improve the
                    browser. This document is critical for the public to access the information
                    regarding the collaborative processes and technical efforts made on the project
                    and provides a background for non-technical individuals to understand its
                    development and technical individuals to see where their own collaboration or
                    implementation may align. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Challenges of Integrated Knowledge Communications</title>
                <para>Regenstrief LOINC® and SNOMED International collaborated on a singular virtual
                    location for the LOINC®-SNOMED CT® Ontology Browser to be housed and available
                    to the public. This site has the entirety of their current progress integrating
                    the two data standards up to their most recent version release (October 15,
                    2023). While the site provides some introductory background into the objectives
                    of the partnership between the two organizations, there is little communication
                    of what the overarching goal of that partnership is aimed to accomplish.
                    Integrating knowledge requires an active community effort to advance healthcare
                    information technology, and the challenge of engaging champions for this effort
                    can be mitigated by increasing the community’s understanding and support.
                    Garnering the community’s trust is vital in progressing the efforts towards an
                    integrated knowledge management solution. [11]</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Ensuring End User Adoption</title>
                <para>As communication strategies are developed,  crafting specific messaging for
                    end user segmentations is critical to promoting adoption of tools and IKM
                    advancements. The LOINC®-SNOMED CT® collaboration will benefit from a similar
                    approach in identifying end user groups and then building compelling
                    communications to each grouping based on key interests and pain points. The
                    collaborative partnership’s overall end user adoption strategy will be a duality
                    of technical information that supports the operational collaboration and the
                    non-technical communications positioning that engages users to learn and apply
                    tools. The technical guidance will need to provide detailed support for
                    technical experts to involve themselves effectively within their efforts and may
                    include user guides, collaboration forums, and proper feedback channels. The
                    non-technical communications will need to cater towards conveying benefits of
                    the browser and what problems this collaboration addresses for a given end user
                    segmentation.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Representation: SNOMED LOINC Collaborative Agreement Demonstration
                Project Progress Reports </title>
            <para>Mapping LOINC® terms to SNOMED CT®, specifically for the laboratory component of
                LOINC® required extensive discussion among stakeholders and an extension of the
                SNOMED CT® concept model to accommodate LOINC® Axis properties. The table below
                shows the SNOMED CT® attribute crosswalk to the LOINC® Axis. </para>
            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="left"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="left"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="left"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">LOINC axis </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">SNOMED CT attribute</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry morerows="1">Component</entry>
                            <entry>246093002 | Component (attribute) OR 704319004 | Inheres in
                                (attribute)</entry>
                            <entry morerows="1">The Property of the LOINC® Term determines if the
                                LOINC® Component is modeled with 246093002 | Component (attribute)
                                or 704319004 | Inheres in (attribute), e.g., a term with property of
                                mass concentration is modeled using 246093002 | Component
                                (attribute) whereas a term representing an inherent part of
                                component such as type is modeled using 704319004 | Inheres in
                                (attribute). -When the LOINC® Component includes an adjustment
                                and/or a count, this additional information is included in the
                                terming of the LOINC® concept but not by an attribute in the
                                model.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>704326004 | Precondition (attribute) (included when the LOINC®
                                Component includes a challenge)</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Property</entry>
                            <entry>370130000 | Property (attribute)</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Scale </entry>
                            <entry>370132008 | Scale type (attribute)</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>System</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>704327008 |Direct site (attribute) OR </para>
                                <para>704319004 |Inheres in (attribute)</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>704319004|In heres in (attribute)</para>
                                <para>Is used when the LOINC® Term has a property type of Prid,
                                    Type, Number of cells, ID</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Time</entry>
                            <entry>370134009 | Time aspect (attribute)</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Method </entry>
                            <entry>246501002 | Technique (attribute)</entry>
                            <entry> </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
            <para>Release notes acknowledge some terms defined by LOINC® Parts require additional
                discussion before finalizing the modeling and terming. An example of this issue is
                LOINC terms defined by LOINC® Part Antibiotic XXX” (‘other antibiotic’). In
                addition, inclusion of the Great Britain (GB) English refset for LOINC terms is
                still pending. [11]</para>
            <para>LOINC® contains properties that define a Category Status of “Order Only,”
                “Observation Only”, or “Both Order and Observation”. SNOMED CT® hierarchies define
                whether such concepts are an order (Procedure hierarchy) or an observation
                (Observable Entity hierarchy). The SNOMED CT® equivalent of the LOINC® “Both Order
                and Observation” Category Status was not found. [11] </para>
            <para>A goal is for the majority of the concepts created in the LOINC® Extension of
                SNOMED CT® is to be designated as sufficiently defined. Where this is not possible,
                the concept is designated as primitive. Primitive concepts within the SNOMED CT®
                terminology and its extensions interfere with use of a classification process where
                the formally stated definitions of each concept compute the subsumption hierarchies
                and defining properties of each concept. Some of the concepts will remain as
                primitive in future releases and some will change to fully defined as the work
                progresses. Some concepts are currently designated as primitive as a map from the
                needed LOINC® Part to SNOMED CT® concept does not yet exist. However, this is
                expected to be resolved in future releases. [11]</para>
            <para>Across many domains, the meaning of a particular observation can be best
                understood in the context of the set of possible answers (result values). For
                example, qualitative laboratory tests often have fixed answer lists for expected lab
                values, as seen in the screenshot below. Answers are not linked to Observable Entity
                concepts in SNOMED CT®. [14]</para>
            <figure xml:id="ExampleofQualitativeLaboratoryTestswithFixedAnswerLists">
                <title>Example of Qualitative Laboratory Tests with Fixed Answer Lists</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/Example%20of%20Qualitative%20Laboratory%20Tests%20with%20Fixed%20Answer%20Lists.svg" align="center" scale="40"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>A Clinical LOINC crosswalk for standardized assessment instruments and document ontology has not been addressed yet in the LOINC® SNOMED CT® Collaboration.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>This deliverable serves as an initial report to document the challenges our team faced
            during the research and initial development of an IKM solution and environment. Our
            summary of findings for various components of the SNOMED CT® LOINC® collaborative
            agreement that aims to develop an IKM environment and the identification of functional
            and non-functional issues our team experienced with IKM have identified critical areas
            that will require additional and continued efforts to improve the implementation,
            functionality, and adoption of IKM solutions.</para>
        <para>While this deliverable will inform the direction and focus areas for our future work,
            this report can also function as a resource and reference implementation for SNOMED CT®,
            LOINC®, and other stakeholders working to develop IKM solutions. As our team works to
            develop an open-source environment for IKM, we look forward to and encourage
            collaboration with other stakeholders to gain a deeper understanding of the challenges
            they faced, best practices, and IKM as a whole. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>IKM Epic Board - Agile board - Jira [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 8]. Available
                    from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://ikmdev.atlassian.net/jira/software/c/projects/IPB/boards/40"
                        >https://ikmdev.atlassian.net/jira/software/c/projects/IPB/boards/40</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>A library for manipulating with proofs that use inference rules. [Internet].
                    GitHub. [cited 2023 September 15]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://github.com/liveontologies/puliz"
                        >https://github.com/liveontologies/puliz</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Bug and Issue Reporting Process Framework. [Deloitte Deliverable]. December
                    20, 2023 [Cited 2024 Jan 9] Available Internally at Deloitte Consulting LLP.
                    DeloitteBAA_Task_2.3.4_Bugs and Issue Reporting Process Framework.pdf</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The Integrated Knowledge Management Application | Komet [Internet]. [cited
                    2024 Jan 19]. Available from: <link xlink:href="https://www.ikm.dev/application"
                        >https://www.ikm.dev/application</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Reynolds CJ, Wyatt JC. Open source, open standards, and health care
                    information systems. J Med Internet Res. 2011 Feb 17; 13(1):e24. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>HL7 International [Internet]. 2021. HL7 Logical Model: Standardized
                    Terminology Knowledgebase, Release 1. Available from:<link
                        xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/private/standards/HL7_LM_TERM_KB_R1_INFORM_2021AUG_FINAL.pdf"
                        >https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/private/standards/HL7_LM_TERM_KB_R1_INFORM_2021AUG_FINAL.pdf</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Systemic Harmonization and Interoperability Enhancement for Laboratory Data
                    (SHIELD) | FDA [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 9]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/diagnostic-data-program/systemic-harmonization-and-interoperability-enhancement-laboratory-data-shield"
                    /></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>SHIELD - Standardization of Lab Data to Enhance Patient-Centered Outcomes
                    Research and Value-Based Care | ASPE [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 9]. Available
                    from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://aspe.hhs.gov/shield-standardization-lab-data-enhance-patient-centered-outcomes-research-value-based-care"
                    /></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>LOINC — The freely available standard for identifying health measurements,
                    observations, and documents. [Internet]. Loinc.org. 2019. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://loinc.org/">https://loinc.org/</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>LOINC and SNOMED CT: LOINC SNOMED CT Extension - Why, What and How | LinkedIn
                    [Internet]. [cited 2023 Jan 8]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/loinc-snomed-ct-extension-why-what-how-termlex/?trk=pulse-article"
                    /></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Regenstrief and SNOMED International broaden collaboration to facilitate
                    interoperability nationally and globally by linking LOINC and SNOMED CT
                    [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 9]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.snomed.org/news/regenstrief-and-snomed-international-broaden-collaboration-to-facilitate-interoperability-nationally-and-globally-by-linking-loinc-and-snomed-ct"
                    /></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Changing the layout of a view - GitHub Docs [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 9].
                    Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://docs.github.com/en/issues/planning-and-tracking-with-projects/customizing-views-in-your-project/changing-the-layout-of-a-view"
                        >https://docs.github.com/en/issues/planning-and-tracking-with-projects/customizing-views-in-your-project/changing-the-layout-of-a-view</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>SNOMED CT - Observable entity (observable entity) [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan
                    10]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://browser.loincsnomed.org/?perspective=full&amp;conceptId1=363787002&amp;edition=MAIN/LOINC/2023-10-15&amp;release=&amp;languages=en"
                    /></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Answer File – LOINC [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 10]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://loinc.org/answer-file/"
                        >https://loinc.org/answer-file/</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>1.3: Chapter 3 Characteristics and Benefits of a Database - Engineering
                    LibreTexts [Internet]. [cited 2024 Jan 9]. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://eng.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/Computer_Science/Databases_and_Data_Structures/Database_Design_(Watt)/01%3A_Chapters/1.03%3A_Chapter_3_Characteristics_and_Benefits_of_a_Database"
                    /></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Abad-Navarro F, Martínez-Costa C. A knowledge graph-based data harmonization
                    framework for secondary data reuse. Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine
                    [Internet]. 2024 Jan 1 [cited 2024 Jan 9];243:107918. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0169260723005849"
                        >https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0169260723005849</link></para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
