<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Emergency Preparedness</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>For the purpose of this volume, we define emergency disaster response in regards to
            four different categories of disaster: natural disasters, public health crises, acts of
            terrorism and radiation and chemical emergencies. [1] Natural disasters include
            earthquakes, hurricanes, floods, tornadoes, tsunamis, wildfires, volcanic eruptions and
            extreme temperatures, and these events can cause great damage to the environment,
            property, wildlife and human health. [2] Public health crises include epidemics,
            pandemics, and other disease outbreaks ranging from new influenza strains to potentially
            deadly diseases, as seen during the recent COVID-19 pandemic. Acts of terrorism can
            range from bomb threats to the threat or usage of biohazardous materials. [3] Lastly,
            radiation and chemical emergencies include the accidental or intentional release of
            radioactive materials or other toxic substances that can cause widespread damage in a
            specified area, as seen in the Chernobyl Accident in 1986 or the Tokyo subway nerve gas
            attack in 1995. [4] [5]</para>
        <para>The year 2024 marks 45 years of emergency management for the U.S. Federal Emergency
            Management Agency (FEMA) and celebrates the presence and dedication of public services
            before, during and after an emergency disaster. [6] The rapid development of technology,
            such as individuals’ access to smartphones during 9/11, has greatly motivated the need
            for applying innovative technology solutions during emergency situations. Up to this
            point we have understood the failures and successes of knowledge management in
            healthcare settings, but it’s important to understand them as part of an emergency
            response as well. For instance, communications and knowledge sharing was critically
            lacking during the September 11<superscript>th</superscript> attacks, ultimately
            hampering the emergency response. The 9/11 Commission Report describes the issues with
            interoperability and included recommendations for better communication systems between
            emergency authorities. [7]</para>
        <para>As we have previously discussed, the primary challange with the adoption of new
            technology and standards revolves around adapting technology to the local context and
            need. Addressing user understanding of technology, ensuring interoperability, and
            implementing data standardization - all while respecting current knowlede - are critical
            aspects of this overarching challenge. Integrating communication systems in all public
            and private spheres, and integrating social media and social services requires a strong
            strategy for designing and testing interfaces and interactions for usability. Promoting
            open data and using open-source technology to accommodate as many technical solutions is
            part of emloying IKM. This volume explores the level of current adoption of IKM in the
            existing emergency natural response system and further discusses challenges and
            recommendations for better practice in the near future. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Landscape of Emergency Management in the United States</title>
        <para>FEMA was founded in 1979 by President Jimmy Carter, however federal emergency
            management reaches back as far as 1802 when the government needed to respond to the
            natural destruction of a seaport in New Hampshire. Since then, FEMA has undergone
            several organizational transformations and expansion of services to arrive where it is
            today as an agency that helps people pre, during, and post emergency. [8]</para>
        <para>Emergency management and disaster response consists of five mission areas as defined
            by FEMA. These five areas include prevention, protection, mitigation, response, and
            recovery. These areas are part of the National Preparedness Goal which is to “...secure
            and resilient nation with the capabilities required across the whole community to
            prevent, protect against, mitigate, respond to, and recover from the threats and hazards
            that pose the greatest risk” [9], and includes risks such as natural disasters, disease
            pandemics, chemical spills, man-made disasters, and terrorist and cyber-attacks. The
            five mission areas are defined as follows:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>Prevention<emphasis role="bold">: </emphasis>Prevent, avoid or stop an
                imminent, threatened or actual act of terrorism<para> [10]</para></listitem>
            <listitem>Protection<emphasis role="bold">: </emphasis>Protect our citizens, residents,
                visitors, and assets against the greatest threats and hazards in a manner that
                allows our interests, aspirations and way of life to
                thrive<para>[10]</para></listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Mitigation: Reduce the loss of life and property by lessening the impact of
                    future disasters</para>
                <para> [10]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>Response<emphasis role="bold">: </emphasis>Respond quickly to save lives,
                protect property and the environment, and meet basic human needs in the aftermath of
                a catastrophic incident<para> [10]</para></listitem>
            <listitem>Recovery<emphasis role="bold">: </emphasis>Recover through a focus on the
                timely restoration, strengthening and revitalization of infrastructure, housing and
                a sustainable economy, as well as the health, social, cultural, historic and
                environmental fabric of communities affected by a catastrophic
                    incident<para>[10]</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A simple way to think about emergency management is by breaking down a response into
            before, during, and after the response. In this paper we explore how IKM can play into
            each of these response areas.</para>
            
    </section>
    <section>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Examples of Knowledge Management in Emergency
                Response</emphasis></title>
        <section>
            <para>Emergency preparedness can broadly be split in pre-emergency, emergency response,
                and post emergency. Knowledge management and communications is critical during all
                stages of preparedness. In the pre-emergency timeframe, during the mitigation and
                preparedness stages of emergency management, knowledge management can be used to
                bolster training and education. For example, FEMA’s Emergency Management Institute
                (EMI) offers online training courses for emergency preparedness through its
                partnership with affiliated centers. [11] Training and education of first responders
                can help orient and prepare those involved once and emergency occurs, and is a core
                tenant of knowledge management best practices. </para>
            <para>Another example of a national approach to emergency knowledge management is FEMA’s
                National Incident Management System (NIMS). NIMS is an example of a system that uses
                knowledge management to integrate resources across organizations by sharing and
                communicating compiled information. NIMS provides standardized vocabulary, systems
                and processes, and are large players when it comes to training and education.
                [12]</para>
            <para>The National Emergency Response Information System (NERIS) is another example of
                system that employs interoperable data and information into an analytics platform
                used by the U.S. Fire Administration to support decision making. [13] Information
                and data from fire departments across the country in integrated into the system, and
                these departments can then access timely and accurate data to provide actionable
                intelligence. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>IKM In Emergency Response</title>
        <para>As discussed, the interoperability of data and communications is already a large part
            of emergency preparedness and response. IKM has a place in emergency preparedness by
            enhancing the ability of organizations to share and integrate critical data.
            Standardizing data can help improve emergency preparedness outcomes and enable the
            government to respond more efficiently, ultimately lessening the damage caused by an
            emergency. However, current standards organizations such as LOINC® and SNOMED CT® do not
            mention emergency preparedness, suggesting the emergency response system as a potential
            area for application of IKM. Furthermore, the lack of organizations that standardize
            emergency response terminology generates an opportunity to build a knowledge management
            and crowdsourcing framework for emergency preparedness. </para>
        <section>
            <title>The COVID-19 Pandemic and IKM</title>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <para>During the COVID-19 pandemic the absence of interoperable laboratory data was a
            challenge to response efforts. The lack of interoperable data during the pandemic
            showcased the inability of the government to properly estimate disease incidence and
            other metrics, ultimately cascading into inadequate communications and erosion in the
            public’s trust. The Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act (P.L.
            116-136) was established to require laboratories to report COVID-19 test results to the
            United States (U.S.) Health and Human Services (HHS) Secretary. [14] SHIELD developed
            the LOINC® to IVD (LIVD) mapping specifications for IVDs for SARS-CoV-2 diagnostic use,
            and in 2020 HHS ordered the use of LIVD test results provided to SHIELD. A study of five
            medical centers that used LIVD concluded there is potential for LIVD to improve semantic
            interoperability and data quality of LIS data. Although the benefit of LIVD is well
            documented, further efforts to promote its widespread use to achieve true laboratory
            interoperability are desirable. [15]</para>
        <para>The pandemic also pushed forward other new technologies to help facilitate the
            response through the introduction and expansion of Artificial intelligence (AI). One of
            the main issues facing emergency responders and the public during the pandemic was the
            inability of policy and communications to efficiently update when new data and
            information was made available. Dealing with inaccurate, unreliable, and incomplete data
            all contributed to a flat emergency response effort. [16,17] Interoperability challenges
            were part of lessons learned from the COVID-19 pandemic, and fostered advacnements in AI
            and advanced analytics.</para>
        <para>AI trains machines to learn from experience, taking new inputs and performing
            human-like tasks in logically programmed sequence with advanced analytics. As a result
            of rapidly developing AI, generative AI, a category of AI system that is able to produce
            meaningful content of its own, is known to be far superior to the traditional role of AI
            that primarily deals with numeric data with a limited amount of text. This generative AI
            has become a powerful tool to leverage existing data for enhancing data analysis and
            decision-making steps. Generative AI can touch on many parts of emergency response and
            preparedness, including optimizing resource allocation, creating alerts based on
            environmental scans, enhancing trainings and educational initiatives. [18]</para>
        <para>Although AI is a powerful tool in the field of Emergency Response &amp; Preparedness,
            the output of AI is solely dependent on the quality of numerical data with limited
            texts. Even with the existence of generative AI and its advanced outputs, public health
            institutions in the U.S. must navigate through a complex web of data paths with limited
            interoperability and data access. For example, more than a third of public health
            agencies were unable to access surveillance data during the COVID-19 pandemic, hampering
            their response. [19] </para>
        <para>IKM can help unlock the full power of AI by ensuring data is of high quality,
            complete, reliable, and interoperable. [20] </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>Different institutions at the local, state, federal, national and international levels
            navigate through the challenge of adopting the latest technology in all shapes and
            forms. Simultaneously, they not only need to keep up with interoperability of their
            legacy systems with new systems, but also need to maintain an interoperable system with
            other institutions’ Incident Command System (ICS). </para>
        <para>Adopting IKM becomes an additional layer for response organizations to incorporate.
            Having experienced the global pandemic in recent years, the role of compliance is
            imperative for public safety. Enforcement in the areas of public safety and emergency
            planning remain crucial and requires government support to upgrade existing digital
            technologies. Achieving this upgrade at the local and state levels will empower and
            facilitate the federal level of maintaining interoperable ICS system with the latest
            available technology for many years to come. </para>
        <para>The field of emergency response and preparedness is well established with many
            agencies and organizations serving in this space. Emergency preparedness is an important
            part of public health and requires a thorough management plan. In an ideal setting,
            emergency response systems work as well-oiled machines with complex processes and actors
            spanning across every field. The use of IKM in emergency preparedness and response can
            sharpen these processes and facilitate timely decision making and a more successful
            response. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            <example>
                <caption>
                    <para>1. Occupational Safety and Health Administration. Emergency Preparedness
                        and Response [Internet]. U.S. Department of Labor; 2024 [cited 2024 April
                        9]. Available from <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.osha.gov/emergency-preparedness"
                            >https://www.osha.gov/emergency-preparedness</link></para>
                    <para>2. The National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH).
                        Natural Disasters and Extreme Weather Topics [Internet]. Centers for Disease
                        Control and Prevention. Available from <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/emres/natural.html#:~:text=Natural%20disasters%20can%20cause%20great,volcanic%20eruptions%2C%20and%20extreme%20temperatures"
                            >https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/emres/natural.html#:~:text=Natural%20disasters%20can%20cause%20great,volcanic%20eruptions%2C%20and%20extreme%20temperatures</link>.</para>
                    <para>3. JCAT. Counter Terrorism Guide for Public Safety Personnel [Internet].
                        U.S. Office of the Director of National Intelligence; 2-24 [cited 2024 April
                        10]. Available from <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.dni.gov/nctc/jcat/index.html"
                            >https://www.dni.gov/nctc/jcat/index.html</link></para>
                    <para>4. International Atomic Energy Agency. Frequently Asked Chernobyl
                        Questions [Internet]. IAEA; 2023 [cited 2024 April 11]. Available from <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.iaea.org/newscenter/focus/chernobyl/faqs"
                            >https://www.iaea.org/newscenter/focus/chernobyl/faqs</link></para>
                    <para>5. Okumura T. Takasu N. Ishimatsu S. Miyanoki S. Mitsuhashi A, Kumada K.
                        Tanaka K. Hinohara S. Report on 640 victims of the Tokyo subway sarin
                        attack. Annals of Emergency Medicine 1996; Aug; 28(2):129-35. Available
                        from: <link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/8759575/"
                            >https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/8759575/</link></para>
                    <para>6. Federal Emergency Management Agency. FEMA Commemorates 45 Years of
                        Emergency Management [Internet]. U.S. Department of Homeland Security; 2024
                        [cited 2024 April 10]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fema.gov/press-release/20240401/fema-commemorates-45-years-emergency-management"
                            >https://www.fema.gov/press-release/20240401/fema-commemorates-45-years-emergency-management</link></para>
                    <para>7. The 9/11 Commission Report: Final Report of the National Commission on
                        Terrorist Attacks Upon the United States. Washington DC: W. W. Norton &amp;
                        Company. 2004. p. 397. <link
                            xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ISBN_(identifier)">ISBN</link>
                        <link
                            xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0393326713"
                            >0393326713</link>. </para>
                    <para>8. FEMA. History of FEMA [Internet]. www.fema.gov. 2021. Available from:
                        https://www.fema.gov/about/history</para>
                    <para>9. FEMA. National Preparedness Goal | FEMA.gov [Internet]. www.fema.gov.
                        2020. Available from:
                        https://www.fema.gov/emergency-managers/national-preparedness/goal</para>
                    <para>10. FEMA. Mission Areas and Core Capabilities [Internet]. www.fema.gov.
                        2020. Available from:
                        https://www.fema.gov/emergency-managers/national-preparedness/mission-core-capabilities</para>
                    <para>11. FEMA - Emergency Management Institute (EMI) Home Page [Internet].
                        Fema.gov. 2019. Available from: https://training.fema.gov/emi.aspx</para>
                    <para>12. Federal Emergency Management Agency. National Incident Management
                        Systems (NIMS) [Internet]. U.S. Department of Homeland Security; 2023 [cited
                        2024 April 17]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fema.gov/emergency-managers/nims"
                            >https://www.fema.gov/emergency-managers/nims</link></para>
                    <para>13. Federal Emergency Management Agency. Six Fire Departments Onboarded
                        onto the New National Emergency Response Information System [Internet]. U.S.
                        Department of Homeland Security; 2023 [cited 2024 April 17]. Available from:
                            <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fema.gov/press-release/20240312/six-fire-departments-onboarded-new-national-emergency-response-information"
                            >https://www.fema.gov/press-release/20240312/six-fire-departments-onboarded-new-national-emergency-response-information</link></para>
                    <para>14. KFF. The Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security Act: Summary
                        of Key Health Provisions [Internet]. United States; 2024 [cited 2024 April
                        18]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/issue-brief/the-coronavirus-aid-relief-and-economic-security-act-summary-of-key-health-provisions/"
                            >https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/issue-brief/the-coronavirus-aid-relief-and-economic-security-act-summary-of-key-health-provisions/</link></para>
                    <para>15. Cholan RA, Pappas G, Rehwoldt G, Sills AK, Korte ED, Appleton K, Scott
                        NM, Rubinstein WS,</para>
                    <para>Brenner SA, Merrick R, Hadden WC, Campbell KE, Waters MS. Encoding
                        laboratory testing data:</para>
                    <para>case studies of the national implementation of HHS requirements and
                        related standards in five laboratories [internet]. USA; 2022 [cited 2024
                        March 20]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article/29/8/1372/6592172"
                            >https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article/29/8/1372/6592172</link></para>
                    <para>16. Wallace M, Sharfstein JM. The Patchwork U.S. Public Health System
                        [Internet]. NEJM 2022; 386:1-4. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMp2104881"
                            >https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMp2104881</link></para>
                    <para>17. Galaitsi SE, Cegan JC, Volk K, Joyner M, Trump BD, Linkov I. The
                        challenges of data usage for the United States’ COVID-19 response
                        [Internet]. Int J Inf Manage 2021 August; 59: 102352. Available from:
                        https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8017563/ </para>
                    <para>18. Hasley A. Kamoie B. Mariani J. Karnik C. Sinha I. Egizi AM. Leveraging
                        for AI for effective emergency management and crisis response [Internet].
                        Government &amp; Public Services by Deloitte; 2024 [cited 2024 April 8].
                        Available from:
                        https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/industry/public-sector/automation-and-generative-ai-in-government/leveraging-ai-in-emergency-management-and-crisis-response.html </para>
                    <para>19. Austin T, Mariani J, Dickau D, Kishnani PK, Kannan T. How teaming
                        artificial intelligence with humans can help de-bias decision-making
                        [Internet]. Perspectives by Deloitte; 2024 [cited 2024 April 9] Available
                        from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/pages/public-sector/articles/artificial-intelligence-bias.html"
                            >https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/pages/public-sector/articles/artificial-intelligence-bias.html</link></para>
                    <para>20. Hasley A. Kamoie B. Mariani J. Karnik C. Sinha I. Egizi AM. Leveraging
                        for AI for effective emergency management and crisis response [Internet].
                        Government &amp; Public Services by Deloitte; 2024 [cited 2024 April 8].
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/industry/public-sector/automation-and-generative-ai-in-government/leveraging-ai-in-emergency-management-and-crisis-response.html"
                            >https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/industry/public-sector/automation-and-generative-ai-in-government/leveraging-ai-in-emergency-management-and-crisis-response.html</link></para>
                </caption>
            </example>
        </para>
    </section>
    
</chapter>
        