<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Ethical Consideration</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction to Ethical Imperatives</title>
        <para>Ethics are individual or shared moral principles that govern our behavior and set standards for what is considered right or wrong. These moral principles can be applied to any component of human behavior, including personal, social, and economic or business decisions. Many organizations and businesses have internal ethical codes and guidelines for employees to follow when working , including medical and Standards Development Organizations (SDOs). [1]
            As our team continues efforts towards Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) and a contributed IKM application, it is critical that our work improves the interoperability and quality of healthcare data to support medical professionals and patients with ethical considerations.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Medical Ethics</title>
        <para>The medical field is driven by a strong code of Medical Ethics, or bioethics, that
            guide providers through their daily practice, decision making, and issues related to
            patient care. There are four pillars of medical ethics that guide providers as they
            determine the best course of action for patient care:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Beneficence (doing good)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Non-maleficence (to do no harm)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Autonomy (giving the patient the freedom to choose freely, where they are
                    able)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Justice (ensuring fairness) [2]</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Unlike other fields, medical providers and other professionals involved in patient
            care are often faced with moral decisions that have unique consequences for not only
            patients, but also for the patient’s family, communities, and even themselves. The
            Hippocratic Oath may come to mind when thinking about ethics in patient care. This
                5<superscript>th</superscript> century Code of Ethics advanced the idea of relieving
            patient suffering and promoting well-being through patient-physician relationship and
            still guides providers today. The American Medical Association’s Code of Medical Ethics
            is another ethical guide for providers that was adopted in 1847; this code explains the
            standards of ethical conduct for physicians, patients, and the entire medical
            profession/society. The current Code has greatly expanded since 1847 and offers general
            rules of practice as well as providing tools for physicians facing novel ethical
            questions. [3]</para>
        <para>Patient care providers are not the only medical professionals that encounter scenarios
            that raise ethical questions surrounding the care they provide, professionals involved
            in medical research also face ethical dilemmas, like which patients qualify for
            experimental treatments. The medical community created institutional review boards to
            address ethics in research and develop guidelines and solutions for these
            questions.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Impact of Healthcare Terminologies on Ethics</title>
        <para>An ongoing and developing conversation in medical ethics is the proper use of health
            data. Genomics is an example of a data source that produces large volumes of health
            data. The field of Genomics uses whole genome or whole exome sequencing extracted from
            biological specimens to study genetically linked diseases, population wide health, and
            rare or neglected diseases. However, while this data offers researchers quality insight,
            the use of this data opens the door to questions about patient consent, data storage and
            future use, and breaches in patient privacy. To manage, codify, and communicate the
            large amounts of health data they collect, healthcare organizations use healthcare
            terminology standards like Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms© (SNOMED
            CT©), Logical Observations Identifiers Names and Codes© (LOINC©), and National Library
            of Medicine’s codification of the U.S. pharmacopeia (RxNorm) developed by SDOs. Although
            SDOs continuously improve their codes, many terminology standards lack interoperability
            between the standards themselves and the organizations that use them, which can impact
            patient safety and the quality of care. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Ethical Implications for Providers</title>
        <para>Beyond facilitating communication, healthcare terminology standards play a crucial
            role in medical ethics. In an environment where every decision holds weight, these
            terminologies work to ensure that healthcare professionals share a common understanding
            of patient data so that providers can translate information into actionable insights and
            improved patient outcomes. Making informed decisions is a critical component of a
            medical professional’s ethical responsibility. Electing for a given treatment option
            without understanding critical factors like existing health conditions, medical history,
            or other pertinent information can have both ethical and qualitative impacts on patient
            care. As efforts continue towards successful IKM, data must be seamlessly exchanged
            within and between systems, while maintaining meaning and accuracy, to prevent
            misunderstandings and errors and fulfill a provider’s ethical duty to “do good” and “do
            no harm”.</para>
        <para>Furthermore, these terminologies play a role in addressing challenges related to
            health equity, including fairness and accessibility in healthcare. Terminology standards
            provide a normalized and repeatable way to classify conditions, treatments, and various
            other aspects of patient care. As we work to improve the interoperability and accuracy
            of transmitted data through IKM, researchers and providers will more easily be able to
            identify and address discrepancies in healthcare. Standardized terminologies are
            instrumental in dismantling barriers that stem from linguistic, cultural, or systemic
            differences by providing a universal language for health conditions and treatments to
            support consistent care, irrespective of a patient or provider's background or
            geographic location. Healthcare terminologies promote a shared understanding of
            conditions and treatments across groups of people, reducing disparities in healthcare
            delivery. Standardized terminologies benefit clinicians in the same way by providing
            them with an unbiased language to navigate the world of clinical decision making and
            potential ethical dilemmas. [4]</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Ethical Implications for Patients</title>
        <para>The ethical implications of patient comprehension are profound. In scenarios where
            treatment options are complex or risky, the ability of patients to understand and weigh
            these options is critical. Healthcare terminologies work to convey information in a
            consistent and clear manner, reducing the likelihood of misunderstandings that could
            impact patient decisions [4 - 6]. These terminologies serve as key facilitators in
            enhancing patient communication and autonomy. By providing a clear and consistent
            language for health information, they empower patients to understand their health
            better, participate actively in their care, and make informed choices – all fundamental
            to ethical and patient-centered healthcare.</para>
        <para>Ethical patient care, including informed patient decision making, must remain a
            driving force behind IKM. Ensuring that data, clinical concepts, and terminologies are
            standardized and interoperable between and within systems like EHRs, patient portals and
            educational materials can lead to improved patient comprehension, better self-management
            of conditions, reduced hospital readmissions, and the ability for patients to ultimately
            choose their care. [5]</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Ethical and Practical Considerations in Localized Artificial Intelligence (AI) and
            Machine Learning (ML) Development </title>
        <section>
            <title>Concerns About Localized AI/ML Models</title>
            <para>While localized development of AI and ML offers customization and optimization
                benefits, the associated risks and challenges necessitate careful consideration.
                Without adequate safeguards and oversight, localized development can lead to biased,
                unreliable, and inequitable AI/ML algorithms, compromising patient care and
                outcomes. The concerns associated with localized development highlighted below
                document the need for a more standardized, equitable, and generalizable approach to
                developing AI/ML algorithms in healthcare.</para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Bias Risk </emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Concern; There is a risk of introducing or worsening biases
                                    when developing algorithms locally especially if the dataset
                                    used is not diverse enough.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Impact; This could result in predictions and unreliable
                                    outcomes, for groups potentially leading to suboptimal care for
                                    these patients.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Limited Applicability</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Concern; Algorithms developed and validated on localized data
                                    may not perform well when applied in healthcare settings or
                                    patient populations. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Impact; The lack of applicability can limit the usefulness and
                                    effectiveness of the algorithm in healthcare contexts.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Inconsistency in Healthcare</emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Concern; Different healthcare facilities may develop their
                                    localized algorithms resulting in inconsistent sepsis detection
                                    and care approaches. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Impact; This inconsistency can cause confusion among
                                    healthcare providers. Compromise the quality and standardization
                                    of care across settings. </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Regulatory Hurdles</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Concern; Regulatory bodies may face challenges when evaluating
                                    and approving versions of localized algorithms. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Impact; The variability introduced by localized development
                                    adds complexity to the approval process and oversight.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Challenges with Maintenance and
                                Updates</emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Concern; Managing, maintaining and updating localized
                                    algorithms can be resource intensive and complex. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Impact; This complexity can lead to difficulties, with version
                                    control (as in fact mentioned by Shawn in the document he shared
                                    on the teams thread), updates and continuous improvement of the
                                    algorithms.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Ethical and Equity Concerns</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Issue; The development and implementation of localized
                                    algorithms raise concerns regarding fairness, equity and ethical
                                    considerations. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Effect; If not properly regulated localized algorithms could
                                    worsen healthcare disparities and give rise to concerns.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Lack of Standardization</emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Issue; The presence of localized algorithms may lead to a lack
                                    of standardization, in the detection and treatment practices for
                                    sepsis. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Effect; This absence of standardization can impede the
                                    integration and compatibility of AI/ML tools, across healthcare
                                    systems.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
</section>
        <section>
            <title>Ethical Considerations and Concerns with Localized AI/ML Models</title>
            <para>Allowing smaller sepsis AI device manufacturers to pursue localized development
                raises several ethical considerations and requires careful oversight. Ethical
                considerations include;</para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Equity and Fairness</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Concern: Smaller manufacturers might have access to limited
                                    datasets, which may not be representative of diverse patient
                                    populations. This limitation can lead to the development of
                                    biased algorithms that do not perform equitably across different
                                    groups.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Ethical Question: Is it ethical to deploy algorithms that
                                    might not provide equitable benefits to all patient groups due
                                    to limitations in data diversity and representativeness?</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                
            
            
                
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Quality and Safety</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Concern: Smaller manufacturers might lack the resources to
                                    conduct extensive validation and testing of their algorithms,
                                    potentially compromising the quality and safety of their
                                    devices.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Ethical Question: Can we ensure that devices developed by
                                    smaller manufacturers meet the necessary quality and safety
                                    standards to protect patient health and well-being?</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>

                
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Transparency and
                            Accountability</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Concern: There might be variations in the level of
                                    transparency and accountability among smaller manufacturers,
                                    raising concerns about the ethical deployment and use of their
                                    devices.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Ethical Question: How can we ensure that smaller manufacturers
                                    adhere to ethical standards of transparency and accountability
                                    in the development and deployment of their devices? </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                
                
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Regulatory Compliance</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Concern: Smaller manufacturers might face challenges in
                                    navigating and complying with regulatory requirements,
                                    potentially leading to non-compliance and associated
                                    risks.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Ethical Question: Is it ethical to allow the deployment of
                                    devices that might not fully comply with regulatory standards
                                    and requirements due to limitations in resources and
                                    expertise?</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                

            
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Access and Affordability</emphasis></para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Concern: Devices developed by smaller manufacturers might have
                                limited availability and accessibility, potentially exacerbating
                                healthcare disparities.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Ethical Question: How can we ensure that devices developed by
                                smaller manufacturers are accessible and affordable to all patients
                                who might benefit from them?</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Recommendations for Ethical Practices</title>
            <para>While smaller sepsis AI device manufacturers pursuing localized development raises
                several ethical consideration, with the appropriate support, resources, and
                guidelines, it is possible to address the ethical concerns associated with localized
                development by smaller manufacturers that support innovation and diversity in the
                field. </para>
            <orderedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Ethical Oversight</emphasis>; It is important to establish mechanisms
                        for oversight in order to thoroughly review and monitor the development and
                        deployment of devices by manufacturers (if not already there).</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Support and Resources</emphasis>; Smaller manufacturers should be
                        provided with support and resources to ensure their adherence to standards
                        and regulatory requirements.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Partnership</emphasis>; Encouraging smaller manufacturers to collaborate
                        with institutions, academia and research organizations will grant them
                        access, to datasets and expertise fostering better development
                        practices.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Tailored Ethical Guidelines</emphasis>; Developing and implementing
                        guidelines that are specifically tailored for manufacturers will serve as a
                        comprehensive framework guiding their responsible development and deployment
                        processes.</para></listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Recommendations and Guidelines for Small Vendors Developing Localized AI/ML
                Models</title>
            <para>Support resources and guidelines are crucial for addressing ethical concerns
                related to localized development by smaller manufacturers while fostering innovation
                and diversity in the field. Below are examples of such resources and
                guidelines:</para>
            <section>
                <title>Support Resources</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Sharing Platforms</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Description: Establish platforms where healthcare
                                    institutions, researchers, and manufacturers can share and
                                    access diverse and representative datasets.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Purpose: To check that smaller manufacturers have access to
                                    the data needed for developing unbiased and generalizable
                                    algorithms.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Funding and Grants (not just Broad Agency
                                Announcements)</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Description: Provide financial support through grants,
                                    subsidies, or low-interest loans specifically aimed at
                                    supporting ethical AI/ML development in healthcare.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Purpose: To alleviate financial constraints that might hinder
                                    the ethical development and validation of AI/ML algorithms by
                                    smaller manufacturers.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
          
           <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Technical Assistance</emphasis></para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Description: Offer technical support and assistance to
                                        smaller manufacturers in the development, validation, and
                                        deployment of AI/ML algorithms.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Purpose: To help smaller manufacturers navigate technical
                                        challenges and implement best practices in algorithm
                                        development and validation.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    
                
     
            
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Educational Resources</emphasis></para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Description: Develop and disseminate educational
                                        materials, workshops, and training programs on ethical AI/ML
                                        development in healthcare.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Purpose: To educate and inform smaller manufacturers about
                                        the ethical considerations and best practices in AI/ML
                                        development.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Ethical Guidelines</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Ethical Principles for AI/ML
                                Development</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Description: Establish a set of ethical principles that guide
                                    the development and deployment of AI/ML algorithms in
                                    healthcare, focusing on fairness, transparency, accountability,
                                    and non-discrimination.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Purpose: To provide a foundational ethical framework for
                                    smaller manufacturers to adhere to during the development
                                    process.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                
                
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Best Practices for Data
                                    Management</emphasis></para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Description: Outline best practices for data collection,
                                        management, and usage, emphasizing the importance of data
                                        diversity, representativeness, privacy, and security.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Purpose: To guide smaller manufacturers in managing data
                                        ethically and responsibly.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Algorithm Validation and Testing
                                    Guidelines</emphasis></para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Description: Develop guidelines for the validation and
                                        testing of AI/ML algorithms, including recommendations for
                                        external validation and performance assessment.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Purpose: To check that algorithms developed by smaller
                                    manufacturers are rigorously tested and validated for safety and
                                    efficacy.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Transparency and Accountability
                                    Standards</emphasis></para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Description: Set standards for transparency and
                                        accountability in AI/ML development, including requirements
                                        for documentation, explanation, and justification of
                                        algorithmic decisions.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Purpose: To promote transparency and accountability among
                                        smaller manufacturers in the development and deployment of
                                        AI/ML algorithms.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Community Engagement
                                    Recommendations</emphasis></para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Description: Provide recommendations for engaging with
                                        patient communities, healthcare providers, and other
                                        stakeholders during the development process.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Purpose: To foster collaboration and input from the
                                        broader community to ensure that AI/ML algorithms address
                                        the needs and concerns of all stakeholders.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>

            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>Ethical considerations must remain a driving force behind the development,
            implementation, and adoption of IKM. IKM must support providers and patients as they
            navigate existing ethical dilemmas, while balancing the ethical concerns surrounding
            patient data, personally identifiable information, and personal health information use
            and storage. IKM will also need to rapidly integrate with new technologies to address
            ethical considerations, particularly around privacy and consent, as artificial
            intelligence, machine learning, and other technologies become more prominent in the
            healthcare ecosystem.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Smith IH, Kouchaki M. Building an Ethical Company [Internet]. Harvard
                        Business Review. 2021. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://hbr.org/2021/11/building-an-ethical-company"
                            >https://hbr.org/2021/11/building-an-ethical-company</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Varkey B. Principles of Clinical Ethics and Their Application to Practice.
                        Medical Principles and Practice [Internet]. 2021 Feb;30(1):17–28. Available
                        from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7923912/"
                            >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7923912/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Harvey JC. The Cambridge World History of Medical Ethics. JAMA. 2009 Dec
                        2;302(21):2371.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Blue Cross Blue Shield Association. Setting the standard: addressing
                        health disparities with better data; 2-22 April [cited 2024 January 29].
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.bcbs.com/the-health-of-america/healthequity/setting-the-standard-addressing-health-disparities-better-data/"
                            >Setting the standard: addressing health disparities with better data |
                            Blue Health Equity (bcbs.com)</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>AHRQ Health Literacy Universal Precautions Toolkit: Health Literacy and
                        Patient Safety Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality; 2015 February
                        [cited 2023 November 28]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.ahrq.gov/health-literacy/improve/precautions/tool2.html"
                            >https://www.ahrq.gov/health-literacy/improve/precautions/tool2.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
