<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>FDA System Safety within Laboratory Data Exchanges End of Base Year Report </title>
    <sect1>
        <title>A System-Theoretic Process Analysis (STPA) of the U.S. Diagnostic Laboratory Data Ecosystem </title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Summary</title>
            <para>Many studies have found large numbers of preventable medical errors in the U.S., despite significant efforts to
                reduce them. This project, a collaboration between Synensys and MIT, studied how the laboratory data ecosystem works today, identified weaknesses and sources of adverse events, and recommends changes to eliminate or reduce such events. We used System-Theoretic Process Analysis (STPA), a technique based on system theory that allows analysis and understanding of very complex, adaptive systems.</para>
                
                <para>Using STPA we created a model of the healthcare laboratory data ecosystem by interviewing fifty stakeholder who represent components of the U.S. healthcare system. These components included departments across the U.S. Health and Human Services (FDA, CDC, National Library of Medicine, ONC, and CMS), standards development organizations, Health IT (HIT) vendors, regulators, public health agencies, clinical practitioners, device manufacturers, administrators, payors, accreditors, policymakers, patients, informaticists, and laboratorians.</para>
                
                <para>The goal for the system model was to try to assist in understanding how the system works as a whole, that is, how the components work together to provide—or to not provide—needed diagnostic laboratory data. While we found that nobody seems to understand the entire U.S. laboratory data ecosystem in detail, we were able to combine the information elicited in the interviews to create a useful model to satisfy our analysis goals. We then used this model to identify the causal factors in common types of adverse events related to healthcare laboratory data. In this study, we concentrated on two hazards: (1) patients receiving less than acceptable care and (2) loss of reputation or trust in the laboratory data ecosystem.</para>
                
                <para>Using the model, we identified unsafe actions and decision making in the system such as the healthcare provider ordering the wrong test, receiving incorrect test results, not receiving the test results at all, receiving test results after delays, or receiving test results for a different patient. Causal scenarios were then created for the identified unsafe events. We identified several hundred potential unsafe actions across the system and multiple causal scenarios/factors for each of those. The identified unsafe actions and scenarios were reviewed by participants in the system for their reasonableness and importance in the real-world operation of the system.</para>
                
                <para>Based on our analysis of the system and the potential unsafe actions, we identified the following systemic flaws and propose recommendations to address them:</para>
            <sect3>
                <title>Systemic Factors and Recommendations Addressable by the SHIELD Initiative</title>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="underline">Decentralized and missing
                                    oversight.</emphasis> The system is characterized by strong
                                regulation in some parts of the system while the system as a whole
                                is weakly regulated. There are very few regulations that address
                                interactions between system components in a meaningful way. Gaps may
                                arise partly because decentralization makes it unclear who has the
                                ultimate jurisdiction over interactions. Each agency may have
                                different goals and directives based on the responsibilities they
                                were assigned by Congress or HHS leadership that limit what they can
                                or cannot add to regulations. </para>
                            <para>Another consequence of decentralized oversight is that regulatory
                                agencies may not have access to the information they need to perform
                                their regulatory duties. For example, an agency may need particular
                                data elements to be shared in a certain format that is unobtainable
                                if data requirements are not under their regulatory scope. </para>
                            <para>In addition, financial incentives for adopting safer practices may
                                differ among various groups. For example, there are no requirements
                                for laboratory HIT to use more advanced standards like FHIR for
                                communication with EHRs. The lack of requirements hinders adoption
                                of new standards that might address problems arising from new and
                                complex diagnostic tests being shared in unstructured formats. </para>
                            <para>Furthermore, in some cases, information is not being collected
                                about potential regulatory gaps, or no controller has any authority
                                to ensure that a problem gets addressed. For example, there are
                                insufficient mechanisms to ensure that providers adequately receive
                                laboratory data, or to ensure that specimens collected outside of a
                                laboratory are collected and transported appropriately. Insufficient
                                studies are being conducted on identification of regulatory gaps in
                                the ecosystem. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 1:</emphasis> Assign
                                responsibility for addressing gaps in the regulatory oversight of
                                laboratory data exchanges between system components that are
                                regulated by different agencies. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 2:</emphasis> Identify the
                                data and standards needs of regulatory agencies and ensure they have
                                the ability to use them appropriately. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 3:</emphasis> Encourage the
                                identification of regulatory gaps in other areas of the laboratory
                                ecosystem through additional systems-theory-based analyses. </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="underline">Inadequacies and gaps in laboratory
                                    data standards, including standards that are loosely
                                    constrained, ambiguous, and outdated.</emphasis> Laboratory data
                                standards may not be tightly constrained because each implementer
                                may possess their own set of requirements for each use of the
                                standards and may thus want it to be implementable in different
                                ways. Even if stakeholders’ implementation goals are aligned,
                                ambiguity in laboratory data standards may make different
                                implementations still appear reasonable and fully compliant with
                                regulation. The use of outdated or obsolete laboratory data
                                standards may similarly raise challenges for patient safety and data
                                interoperability. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 4:</emphasis> Reference
                                libraries must develop a knowledge base that establishes a ground
                                truth for naming, coding, and mapping of reference terminologies to
                                particular laboratory tests, and stakeholders must be incentivized
                                to use it. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 5:</emphasis> Appropriate
                                groups must be assigned responsibility for identifying gaps and
                                weaknesses in laboratory data standards and for establishing a
                                reporting channel for problems related to them. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 6:</emphasis> SDOs must
                                continuously support users by identifying and eliminating
                                ambiguities in implementation guides for HIT standards. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Systemic factors and recommendations addressable by the other components of the laboratory data ecosystem</title>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="underline">Inaccurate perceptions of risks with
                                    respect to both laboratory data and the use of health
                                    information technology (HIT).</emphasis> A common theme observed
                                in multiple scenarios is a flawed perception of risk in diagnostic
                                healthcare. Many stakeholders in the ecosystem hold assumptions
                                about the low safety-criticality of laboratory data and HIT that
                                lead to flawed decision making across the system. An example is the
                                effect on clinical decision making when there are data presentation
                                problems or missing data: Errors are often blamed on the medical
                                practitioners using HIT even if the software is counterintuitive or
                                misleading. </para>
                            <para>Causes of misperceived risk include beliefs that HIT is low risk
                                in comparison with its potential benefits leading to less than
                                rigorous oversight; limited proactive and reactive laboratory safety
                                efforts, including investigating sources of diagnostic error; and a
                                limited reporting system with no regulatory body keeping records on
                                IVD (in vitro device) and lab errors. There also exist false
                                assumptions about the ease of installing and maintaining HIT. </para>
                            <para>One result of misperceived risk is that laboratory data and HIT
                                problems are not prioritized when designing and implementing
                                responses to adverse events. In general, misperceived risk is a
                                common cause of accidents in all industries. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 7:</emphasis> Proactively and
                                retroactively investigate systemic sources of diagnostic error. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 8: </emphasis>Create a
                                consolidated national database for HIT safety reporting that can be
                                used to identify trends and opportunities for improving patient
                                safety outcomes. It should include information about HIT not
                                behaving as users intended and allow understanding how features of
                                HIT design may have contributed to “user errors.” </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="underline">Lack of a systems view by participants
                                    in the system.</emphasis> Nearly all stakeholders in the U.S.
                                healthcare system are trying to make locally optimal changes to
                                reduce adverse events. However, without taking a systems’ view, many
                                changes made at the local level do not make the system significantly
                                safer. Local or limited “fixes” may just shift the problem to a
                                different part of the system or even make it worse. It may also
                                cancel an improvement or change made by others. </para>
                            <para>After dozens of interviews, it became clear that no stakeholder
                                holds a complete view of the entire ecosystem. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 9: </emphasis>Educate the
                                healthcare community on systems engineering and systemic approaches
                                for solving problems, including tools to accomplish this goal. </para>
                            <para>One particular area in which customized “local solutions” were
                                prevalent was in the design and maintenance of HIT systems and
                                standards. Designing a new HIT or updating it without sufficient
                                consideration of the system’s connections to other systems can lead
                                to broken connections. The difficulty of installing or maintaining
                                HIT is often underestimated. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 10:</emphasis> Establish
                                appropriate control loops for updates to standards and HIT. </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="underline">Inadequate regulatory emphasis on the
                                    safety involved in health system information
                                    technology.</emphasis> Regulatory directives to the ONC have
                                historically been driven by increasing the usage and capabilities of
                                HIT without emphasizing safety. Designs that meet ONC certification
                                requirements frequently have significant safety risks. Furthermore,
                                no one is currently required to use certified HIT, as incentives for
                                using certified IT are only available to facilities that are
                                eligible for certain government programs.</para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 11:</emphasis> Assign
                                regulatory oversight of HIT safety to ONC or another appropriate
                                group. Include the explicit directive to develop and include
                                safety-related certification criteria for HIT and the ability to
                                limit the inclusion of “hold harmless” clauses in HIT contracts. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 12:</emphasis> Establish
                                incentives for using certified HIT throughout the entire healthcare
                                ecosystem. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="underline">Flawed communication and
                                    coordination.</emphasis> A common causal factor identified is
                                the lack of formal communication and coordination channels between
                                those attempting to control diagnostic data safety. Many regulators
                                do not have the information they need to change or update regulatory
                                standards. Medical practitioners may also not be incentivized to
                                report problems if previous reports have not been appropriately
                                addressed. Following standards is often voluntary. While some
                                requirements do exist to follow standards, they often refer to
                                outdated standards without a strong process to change the standards
                                to recognize best practices.</para>
                            <para>Additionally, inadequate communication and coordination channels
                                between data users may also contribute to patient harm. For example,
                                medical practitioners are responsible for ordering tests to monitor
                                and diagnose patients, but at the same time have a huge range of
                                responsibilities and could benefit from better communication with
                                laboratories. Laboratorians have up-to-date information on changes
                                to the diagnostic testing environment, including new test options or
                                how tests results should be interpreted. However, due to the way
                                many interfaces are set up, laboratorians may not receive sufficient
                                data to fully support practitioners. For example, a laboratory may
                                not be able identify if a test result is critical and time-
                                sensitive if they don’t appropriately receive the patient’s relevant
                                clinical context. </para>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Recommendation 13:</emphasis> Develop formal
                                processes for inclusion of laboratorians in the multidisciplinary
                                teams responsible for decisions about laboratory data needs,
                                representations, and interfaces at care facilities. </para>
                            <para>See recommendations 5 and 8 as well. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </sect3>
                
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Conclusion</title>
            <para>Our goal in this study was not to focus on what individuals or even individual components of the system are doing wrong, but instead on why their actions make sense within the system as it exists today. Our recommendations are about how to change the overall system design to allow and encourage safe behavior by everyone. The causal scenarios for adverse events identified by STPA point clearly to actionable recommendations that can be linked to the related flaws in the system. A rationale for all the recommended changes to the system is provided by the links to the identified adverse event scenarios.</para>
                <para>The problems we identified are not unknown within the healthcare community. What is not understood widely is how to get past the problems and effect changes to greatly increase healthcare safety. By formally analyzing the system and identifying why the problems are occurring, we were able to generate recommendations that have the potential to greatly decrease adverse events.</para>
                
                <para>Perhaps the biggest takeaway from our effort and from the application of system theory is that the difficult problems in U.S. healthcare safety cannot be solved without applying a systems-theoretic approach: major improvements will require redesign of the system as a whole, not just small tweaks to parts of it. The problems are not so much in the individual system components, where everyone is trying to provide safe and effective care. The most serious and persistent problems are instead occurring in the interactions and interdependences between the system components. Only by redesigning the system to control these interactions will significant progress be made.</para>
                <para>While the recommendations in this report represent large changes for the healthcare community, they are standard features in other industries that have highly successful safety records. For example, the U.S. has an incredibly safe aviation system, which is unparalleled compared to other types of transportation systems. One of the reasons is that aviation in the U.S. long ago instituted the systems approach to safety recommended for healthcare in this report.</para>
                <para>Finally, changing the current system, as difficult as it will be, is not enough. There also needs to be action to control the foreseeable changes in the healthcare industry. One of these is the rapidly growing use of software and information technology. We can wait until the inevitable adverse events start to occur widely, or we can take action to ensure that new software and advanced automation is introduced from the beginning with acceptable controls over patient safety.</para>
                <para>The types of structural changes recommended in this report may take some time to introduce into the U.S. healthcare system. In the meantime, near-term solutions will be required to provide adequate control over hazards. All the changes will require the participation of everyone in the healthcare community to ensure that the most effective controls are successfully created and used. Local optimization may in some cases have to be sacrificed for increases in overall healthcare safety, quality, and efficiency.</para>
          
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
