<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Framework Considerations for Safety Systems Thinking on Knowledge Management
        Constructs</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <para>Today’s current state for knowledge management constructs lack a standardized approach
            to ensure the quality of data as it is entered or transferred into the health care and
            laboratory systems. Without a clear and repeatable way to verify the accuracy of
            information within an electronic health record (EHR) or laboratory system, there are
            opportunities for hazards and patient safety issues to emerge. Our team will design a
            system based on a Safety Systems Thinking approach and High Reliability Organization
            (HRO) principles that can improve the quality, reliability, and interoperability of data
            and address the concerns with current knowledge management constructs. We will use prior
            work and research from industry leaders and subject matter experts (SMEs) as
            foundational building blocks as we continue to research laboratory and health care
            systems, medical terminology standards, and best practices and lessons learned to
            support our development and design process.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <para>The health care system in the United States has undergone a digital transformation
            over the past few decades as digital health information systems and electronic health
            records have been widely adopted and implemented. Despite this expansive transformation,
            elements of interoperability, data quality management, and the associated patient safety
            risks are underrepresented as key subject matter experts and informatics stakeholders
            have not been optimally involved in the design and implementation process of health
            information systems.</para>
        <para>The current state for health care knowledge management to ensure data quality and
            interoperability is to encode health data using medical terminology standards such as,
            Logical Observation Identifiers Names and Codes (LOINC), Systematized Nomenclature of
            Medicine – Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT), and RxNorm. These terminologies provide a
            standardized method to create and enter data elements into health care systems and, in
            an ideal world, support seamless interoperability between health care systems or health
            record systems. However, the application and use of these standards is typically not
            consistent during implementations between facilities within a health care system or
            between different systems. This non-standardized implementation leads to localized
            variants of terminologies and knowledge representations that limit interoperability and
            impacts opportunities to comprehensively understand data within a system.</para>
        <para>Not only is current knowledge management unstandardized, but there is also relative
            uncertainty regarding the quality and accuracy of the data representing knowledge. A
            standardized process to validate the vast amount health care data does not exist, nor is
            there a standardized understanding of what data should be validated, which further
            impacts the quality and accuracy of data, the ability to support research and clinical
            decisions, and patient safety. Existing data validation techniques need to be
            standardized and refined to support comprehensive and reproducible validation of data
            within systems and data that is transferred between systems.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Background</title>
        <para>Improving existing knowledge management constructs requires an understanding of
            industry leading frameworks and principles. Safety Systems Thinking and HRO principles
            are two frameworks that will support the development of a standardized and repeatable
            knowledge management and data validation process with continual improvement.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Saftey Systems Thinking</title>
            <para>A systems thinking approach to safety is a thorough and disciplined approach to
                identifying, analyzing, eliminating, and controlling hazards by analysis, design,
                and management procedures that operate throughout a system’s life cycle. Hazards are
                created by unsafe conditions and processes that may lead to negative outcomes for
                stakeholders in the system, such as patients, providers, and researchers.</para>
            <para>Traditional approaches to safety view hazards as a linear chain of events and
                focus on eliminating component failures. However, a system thinking approach to
                safety attempts to eliminate hazards by examining the various hierarchical control
                structures and feedback loops that impact the conditions of a system.</para>
            <para>In systems thinking, analysis of the system begins in the early concept design
                stage and continually evaluates changes in the system or the environment that could
                indicate a shift to unsafe conditions. Reporting and information sharing channels
                are established, including hazard documentation, tracking, and resolution. These
                documentation channels are critical to support continual process improvement and are
                maintained throughout the lifespan of the system.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>High Reliability Organization Principles</title>
            <para>A High Reliability Organization is an organization that avoids accidents and
                hazards, even in complex environments where accidents are common. HROs are based on
                five key principles:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Preoccupation with Failure</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The organization works to ensure stakeholders are aware of errors
                                and understands how errors occur, the processes that allow errors to
                                occur, and how to reduce the causes of errors.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Reluctance to Simplify</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Stakeholders do not oversimplify the system and aim to fully
                                understand all the processes and control structures that may impact
                                that system.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Sensitivity to Operations</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Organizations and stakeholders identify, and continually measure,
                                key indicators of quality and safety that could alert to changes,
                                even small ones, or indications of a shift towards unsafe conditions
                                or hazardous environments.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Deference to Expertise</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Organizations utilize the experience and knowledge of pertinent
                                SMEs at every opportunity.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Commitment to Resilience</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Organizations learn from errors through feedback loops and
                                continuous monitoring, as they aim to continually improve.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Framework Considerations</title>
        <para>Following the rapid transition to EHRs, there is a desperate need to overhaul the
            current knowledge management constructs within the health care system to improve data
            quality and patient safety. While there will never be a perfectly safe system, an
            approach embedded in both Safety Systems Thinking and HRO principles can support major
            strides towards that goal. A combined approach will guide organizations through the
            successful implementation or redesign of systems to implement clear, concise, and
            standardized data validation techniques and support continuous process improvement
            through SME-led risk analysis and statistical, evidence-based review. </para>
        <para>It is not uncommon for other high-risk industries to adopt HRO principles. Commercial
            aviation and nuclear submarines are industries that adopted HRO based principles to
            enable substantial improvements to quality and safety. Pairing these principles with a
            systems-based approach to safety and proven tools like Statistical Process Control
            (SPC), Systems Theoretic Process Analysis (STPA), and Causal Analysis based on System
            Theory (CAST) will further improve the safety, standardization, and quality of systems
            and knowledge management constructs.</para>
        <para>As we use systems thinking and HRO principles to develop and design a system that
            addresses the existing flaws in the current knowledge management constructs, it is
            critical that we perform a comprehensive and proactive assessment of the pertinent
            laboratory and health care systems, their controls, best practices, and weaknesses.
            Figure 1 below outlines some common knowledge management construct issues that we will
            work to address as we design a system with proactive data assurance methods.</para>
        <para>Figure 1: Common Knowledge Management Construct Challenges</para>
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata
                        fileref="images/Common%20Knowledge%20Management%20Construct%20Challenges.png"
                    />
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Related Work</title>
        <para>Subject matter experts and other industry leaders have demonstrated use cases for the
            feasibility and applicability of a Systems Safety and HRO-based approach to improving
            data interoperability, reliability, and quality in the health care system. Our work will
            build upon the findings of these subject matter experts and will incorporate lessons
            learned to address known issues with current state knowledge management
            constructs.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Increasing the Value of Health Data by Engineering Safety, Quality, and High
                Reliability into the Data Lifecycle</title>
            <para>In this 2022 paper by Dr. Keith E. Campbell et al., the team outlines an
                Independent Validation and Verification (IV&amp;V) approach that was designed with
                system safety, HRO principles, and statistical process control techniques. The
                generalized and iterative IV&amp;V sought to improve the quality and
                interoperability of data through a three-phased approach, error discovery and
                assessment, statistical process control, and continuous process improvement.</para>
            <para>By identifying and establishing feedforward pathways and baseline metrics for data
                and knowledge quality, the team provided a use-case for an IV&amp;V approach’s
                ability to statistically improve the quality and interoperability of prescription
                data. Dr. Campbell and team highlighted a variety of lessons learned that will need
                to be addressed to continue improvements to health care data, including the need to
                embed data and informatics SMEs into EHR modernization (EHRM) efforts and to expand
                HRO principles to Standards organizations and health care system data processes.
                [1]</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>A Risk-Based Methodology for the Quality Assurance of Healthcare Knowledge
                Artifacts</title>
            <para>Greg Rehwoldt outlines a real-world use case of developing and applying a
                risk-based methodology to improve the quality of current state knowledge artifacts
                in this 2018 dissertation. This paper highlights a variety of issues with current
                state knowledge management, particularly the lack of effective quality assurance for
                existing knowledge artifacts. Current approaches to quality tend to focus on system
                specific events or stakeholder mistakes, but as the health care environment has
                evolved, quality assurance must validate data during creation and as it transitions
                between systems.</para>
            <para>While improving patient safety and data quality are key focuses of this paper,
                financial theory is also applied to demonstrate how cost and time variables will
                impact quality assurance. It is critical that data validation and assurance methods
                are implemented optimally to reduce the risk of hazards or patient safety issues
                while accounting for organizational constraints and pressures. [2]</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Background to Capability Maturity Model Integration (CMMI)</title>
            <para>The Capability Maturity Model Integration for Development (CMMI-DEV) is a risk
                management model developed at the Carnegie-Mellon University as a maturity
                assessment for an organization’s processes and to support the identification of
                opportunities to improve management of risk and performance under stress. The model
                was designed as a process improvement initiative to support gap assessments and
                identify goals to support measured improvements to high value areas.</para>
            <para>The CMMI-DEV examines 22 process areas and ranks an organization’s maturity for
                each area and that area’s process capabilities. By examining each area, this model
                identifies areas where improvements would provide the highest value and allows
                organizations to tailor their focus and efforts. [3]</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Our National Rush to the EHR - An Analysis of Current Clinical Information
                Quality and Data Governance Practices</title>
            <para>The Enterprise Clinical Information Maturity (ECIM) framework outlined in this
                paper builds upon the previously mentioned CMMI-DEV model and supports the
                development of goals and baseline measurements to improve data quality and
                standardization. The ECIM framework also considers organization goals and the use of
                clinical data when evaluating current state processes. This comprehensive approach
                supports the identification of specific issues or opportunities for data quality and
                knowledge management improvements.</para>
            <para>This paper highlights how current state electronic health information practices
                are not mature and identifies a variety of recurring issues related to knowledge
                management and data quality.</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Electronic Medical Record (EMR) clinical documentation guidelines are
                        poorly standardized and communicated to end-users.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The lack of internal data audits across the health care industry results
                        in unknown patient record quality, accuracy, and completeness.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Key informatics stakeholders and SMEs are not adequately included in EHRM
                        efforts.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Providers do not use current state knowledge management tools, like
                        standardized terminology or classification systems, optimally.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Providers must learn to structure and enter clinical information with a
                        standardized process to support data interoperability as natural language
                        processing (NLP) abilities remain limited.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Systems lack a standardized approach to terminology and data that leads to
                        many redundant, ambiguous, or improperly mapped terms in EHR data
                        dictionaries. This can often lead to improperly labeled data as information
                        is shared between systems.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Data issues that affect multiple records can occur as automated data flows
                        apply terminology maps based on the received map, rather than the original
                        source data. [4]</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>While this Framework Consideration paper has outlined key principles, frameworks, and
            research that will be used as we design an improved knowledge management system, there
            is still important research and work that needs to be done. Our team will need to
            continue researching existing laboratory and health care systems and terminology
            standards to build upon the years of research and SME experience.</para>
        <para>Our system will be designed with Safety Systems Thinking and HRO principles and will
            support the application of a rigorous and improved data review process that verifies and
            validates data at each step of information exchange for accuracy, completeness, and
            reliability. We must determine how to optimally design a system that ensures data from
            multiple medical terminology standards and EHRs maintains all relevant information and
            meaning as it seamlessly moves within and between systems. The goal of our work is to
            optimally improve data accuracy and patient safety, while understanding the real-world
            pressures of the health care and laboratory systems</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Campbell KE, Montella D, Brown SH, Powell SM, Campbell SW, Cholan RA, et
                        al. Increasing the Value of Health Data by Engineering Safety, Quality, and
                        High Reliability into the Data Lifecycle 2022. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Rehwoldt G. A Risk-Based Methodology for the Quality Assurance of
                        Healthcare Knowledge Artifacts (dissertation). 2018.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You C, Sherer T, Mabee D, Jacobs M, Koke J, Boer G, et al. Capability
                        Maturity Model Integration (CMMI), background notes - azure boards
                        [Internet]. Capability Maturity Model Integration (CMMI), background notes -
                        Azure Boards | Microsoft Learn. [cited 2022Dec15]. Available from:
                        https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/devops/boards/work-items/guidance/cmmi/guidance-background-to-cmmi?view=azure-devops#related-articles</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hawry PL, Clouse T, Spisla C, Konieck D. Our National Rush to the EHR - An
                        Analysis of Current Clinical Information Quality and Data Governance
                        Practices 2013.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

