<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Healthcare Quality Improvement with IKM Terminology Knowledge Architecture
        (Tinkar)</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>While Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) and other content is explored in more
            detail in other volumes, the following areas are key components to healthcare quality
            improvement (QI).</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Healthcare QI</emphasis> is a systematic and continuous action
            aimed at measurable improvements in healthcare services and the health status of
            targeted patient groups. [1] The National Academy of Medicine defines healthcare quality
            as the degree to which health services for individuals and populations increase the
            likelihood of desired health outcomes consistent with current professional knowledge.
            [2] QI seeks to standardize processes and structure to reduce variation, achieve
            predictable results, and improve outcomes for patients, healthcare systems, and
            organizations. It involves a combination of efforts from healthcare professionals,
            patients, researchers, and educators to make changes leading to better patient outcomes,
            system performance, and professional development. [3]</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">IKM</emphasis> in healthcare refers to the systematic management
            of knowledge resources, aimed at increasing access to available, accurate, and timely
            information. It involves a quality improvement approach comprising a multipart sequence
            and cycle, including data collection, storage, dissemination, review, analysis, and
            recommendations for improvement. [4] An IKM approach is intended to achieve
            institutional goals through continuous quality improvement, a focus on efficiency,
            collaboration, and transparency.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Tinkar</emphasis> is an IKM framework designed to manage and
            standardize healthcare terminology. It ensures the consistency and accuracy of medical
            records, which is crucial for effective communication and treatment planning. Tinkar
            plays a vital role in data interoperability and accuracy, supporting healthcare
            organizations as they manage standard terminology modules, value sets, coding systems,
            and local terms and equivalence mappings.</para>
        <para>Training healthcare staff is a critical component of healthcare QI and in the
            healthcare delivery process. Training is a core tenant of maintaining a safe and high
            quality healthcare system and ensures an environment that encourages staff retention.
            Healthcare professionals must meet and maintain professional standards set by their
            respective professional organizations, as well as legislative and regulatory
            requirements. These standards are often updated, and training can ensure staff are aware
            of updated knowledge, best practices, and policies. </para>
        <para>There are a wide range of stakeholders involved in the delivery of care and in the
            healthcare ecosystem, from physicians, laboratorians, nurses, support staff, and more,
            who generate and share curated knowledge with each other. Organizing and relaying this
            information in an efficient and effective way is not a simple task. Often times,
            critical information and context is lost or distorted during data exchange within and
            between systems, resulting in incomplete or inaccurate knowledge. IKM aims to ensure
            systems maintain and communicate information without data loss as it flows between
            systems. Healthcare employees rely on IKM to receive timely and correct information for
            their training.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Objectives of this Volume:</emphasis></para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Explore the role of IKM and Tinkar in enhancing healthcare quality.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Discuss how these systems can be integrated into healthcare settings to
                    improve patient care and operational efficiency.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Provide insights into the implementation strategies and challenges of adopting
                    IKM and Tinkar.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Highlight the impact of these systems on healthcare quality
                    improvement.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <section>
            <title>Importance of IKM and Tinkar in Healthcare Quality Improvement</title>
            <para>All healthcare organizations are continuously striving towards healthcare QI, a
                process used to identify and address healthcare disparities, to reduce harm and
                issues that may arise from administrative or technical mistakes. Inaccuracies or
                omissions in health records may lead to unintended and harmful effects to the
                patient. Improving upon certain processes can help mitigate these errors and have a
                positive impact on patients and healthcare providers.</para>
            <para>IKM can help play a pivotal role in Healthcare QI through the following:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Enhanced Decision-Making: </emphasis>IKM plays a
                        pivotal role in healthcare by facilitating the flow and management of
                        knowledge throughout its lifecycle. This process is crucial for informed
                        clinical decision-making, which directly impacts patient care quality.
                        [5]</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Standardized Healthcare Terminology:
                        </emphasis>Tinkar addresses the need for standardized terminology in
                        healthcare. It ensures consistency and accuracy in medical records, which is
                        fundamental for effective communication and treatment planning. [6]</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Evidence-Based Medical Practices (EBMP):
                        </emphasis>The integration of research evidence, clinical expertise, and
                        patient preferences in clinical decision-making is a cornerstone of EBMP.
                        IKM and Tinkar support this integration by managing both tacit and explicit
                        knowledge, crucial for successful EBMP. [5]</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Operational Efficiency: </emphasis>IKM and Tinkar
                        support efficient knowledge management in healthcare and add significant
                        value to diagnostic, decision-making, and treatment processes. Efficient
                        knowledge management helps reduce medical errors caused by misdiagnosis or
                        incorrect information. [6]</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Knowledge Sharing and Organizational Learning:
                        </emphasis>These systems foster a culture of knowledge sharing, leading to
                        organizational learning. This aspect is vital for continuous improvement in
                        healthcare practices and patient safety. [7]</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Healthcare Education: </emphasis>The role of IKM in
                        healthcare education is another critical component that can be used to
                        improve patient outcomes, provider experience, and the efficacy and
                        efficiency of IKM itself.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>To undergo optimal healthcare QI, patients and healthcare professionals will need
                a thorough understanding of IKM and how IKM contributes to patient care. Education
                and training are important processes in the healthcare system that will help align
                the knowledge base of patients and healthcare professionals, and is needed to
                maintain quality patient care and to meet high quality healthcare standards.
                Training involves both the management and sharing of important and relevant
                information amassed from best practices, experience, and research. Proper training
                can ensure all individuals involved in delivery of care are up to date on the most
                relevant technology, skills, and processes. IKM is the systematic organization of
                knowledge and will play an important part in any well-developed training
                curriculum.</para>
            <para>The implementation of IKM and Tinkar in healthcare settings is not just a
                technological upgrade but a strategic move towards a more efficient, accurate, and
                patient-centered healthcare system. IKM and Tinkar's role in standardizing
                healthcare terminology and enhancing knowledge management paves the way for improved
                healthcare quality, education, and patient
                outcomes.<?oxy_comment_start author="rgeorgacopoulos" timestamp="20240506T154103-0500" comment="add sentence about health policy"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        
        <title>The Current State of Healthcare Quality</title>
        <section><title>Challenges in Healthcare Quality Management</title>
        
        <para>Despite the association between low-quality healthcare and significant mortality and
            economic impacts, especially in low- and medium-income countries, healthcare systems
            globally struggle to provide a consistent, standardized, and high-quality standard of
            care. Issues surrounding clinical workflows, the workforce, stagnant healthcare systems,
            and health equity all pose challenges that need to be addressed to improve the quality
            of care provided.</para>
        <para>Issues optimizing clinical workflows lead to inefficient practices, incomplete
                information, alert fatigue, and delays in care, which further compound and
                contribute to clinician dissatisfaction and turnover. Beyond suboptimal workflows,
                the healthcare workforce is an aging workforce that faces significant personnel
                shortages and burnout that were exacerbated by the COVID-19 pandemic, particularly
                in nursing, posing a primary concern to the delivery of care. Further impacting
                healthcare providers, rapid advancements in medical science and information outpace
                the ability of the actual healthcare systems to adapt. This poses a perpetual
                challenge to healthcare systems to stay up-to-date with emerging therapies,
                concepts, practices, and technologies. </para>
            <para>Additionally, challenges with technology adoption are a major issue facing an
                already overburdened health system. While the use of advanced technology in
                healthcare workflows is meant to save time and improve efficiencies, it often leads
                to added stress and burnout. Healthcare systems will need to find a way to upskill
                the workforce to lessen the technological burden and alleviate the stress of a
                diminished talent pipeline. </para>
        <para>Another key component of healthcare delivery is health equity. Advancing health equity
                by addressing healthcare disparities, including socioeconomic, racial, and
                gender-based inequities, is a complex and critical challenge in healthcare. All of
                these challenges are bookended by patient safety, with issues like medication
                errors, diagnostic inaccuracies, and hospital-acquired infections (HAIs) continuing
                to pose significant challenges to healthcare quality. [8]</para>
        </section>
        <section><title>The Role of Data and Information Management in Healthcare
                Quality</title>
        
        <para>Data and information management play a vital role in improving the quality of
                healthcare by ensuring the data used during  decision making processes is of the
                highest quality and accurate. High quality data can enhance the decision making
                process by allowing providers to see a clear picture of the patient's health and is
                critical for patient health management, research, and any other area that data is
                used. Proper data management entails accurately entering information into EHRs,
                which in turn helps improve clinical validity and can enable more accurate
                diagnosis, ultimately improving the quality of patient care. [9] Poor data
                management practices can lead to recurrent errors, associated injuries or deaths
                caused by issues like illegible paper-based records, a lack of trust in providers
                and the healthcare system as a whole, decreased visits, and other negative health
                impacts. Addressing poor data management practices is a vital aspect of a
                well-functioning healthcare ecosystem and can help support patient engagement and
                improve safety.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Role of Healthcare Education in Healthcare Quality</title>
            <para>Healthcare education can be broken down into two key components:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Training and education for providers, researchers, public health experts,
                        and other professionals involved in the delivery, research, or study of
                        patient care. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Education for patients to understand their conditions, treatments,
                        preventative measures, and other aspects of their healthcare journey to
                        promote healthy, voluntary behaviors that improve health outcomes.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>Knowledge management structures and applications that support provider training
                and learning or the delivery of care include clinical decision support, patient care
                coordination, the use of new technologies like telehealth/telemedicine, and the
                sharing of state-of-the-art research on emerging conditions. IKM supports this
                version of healthcare education throughout the various stages of a healthcare
                professional’s journey by conglomerating disparate knowledge into a singular source
                that is then accessible to the provider, reducing cognitive burden, fostering
                collaboration between organizations, lowering wait times by removing the need for
                providers to extensively search for information, and improving provider knowledge
                and patient care. Healthcare students (MD, RN, NP, PhD, Masters, etc.), providers,
                researchers, public health experts, and more can all benefit from more efficient and
                optimized information management, organization, and sharing. This type of healthcare
                learning not only facilitates improved diagnoses, treatment, communication, and
                patient outcomes, but also supports workflow and operation optimization, process
                improvement, and business outcomes for other professionals and organizations
                involved in patient care. [10, 11] For instance, Certified Nursing Assistants and
                other nursing home healthcare personnel were provided an interactive educational
                program regarding infection prevention and control (IPC). Following each module, IPC
                knowledge scores were recorded and showed significant improvement. Not only did this
                education improve healthcare knowledge for healthcare workers, but it also supported
                improvements to workflows, processes, and patient care by reducing
                multidrug-resistant organisms and infections in a high-risk community like nursing
                homes. [12]</para>
            <para>Beyond training for providers, healthcare education for patients is critical and
                its impact is well documented, resulting in significant health outcomes for
                prevention and control of obesity, reduction of tobacco use in adolescents, and
                more. [13, 14] Low healthcare literacy can lead to lower overall health outcomes,
                misuse of medication, overall misunderstanding of health information, and longer
                wait times to seek treatment, which itself can compound health problems. By
                improving health literacy through expanded healthcare education, patients will have
                a better understanding of their diagnoses and will be able to make more informed
                decisions regarding their treatment. [15]</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Opportunities to Improve Healthcare Quality</title>
            <para>The Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality has highlighted three case studies
                that showcase efforts to improve a patient's healthcare experience and health
                outcomes by addressing performance issues and updating and implementing strategy and
                action plans. [16]</para>
            <para>1. <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/wysiwyg/cahps/quality-improvement/reports-and-case-studies/Case_Study_Specialty_Practice_Updated.pdf"
                    >Improving Customer Service and Access in a Surgical Practice:</link> A surgical
                practice implemented a six-step plan to enhance customer service and access, leading
                to improved patient experiences. </para>
            <para>2. <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/wysiwyg/cahps/quality-improvement/reports-and-case-studies/WR_751_AHRQ_Quigley_08_26_10.pdf"
                    >Improving Hospital Inpatient Nursing Care</link>: A large acute care hospital
                successfully implemented a plan to improve the emotional support provided to
                inpatients by nursing staff, enhancing patient care quality. </para>
            <para>3. <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/wysiwyg/cahps/quality-improvement/reports-and-case-studies/ExecSummcaseplancustsvce-RAND7607.pdf"
                    >Improving Performance for Health Plan Customer Service:</link> A health plan
                employed quality improvement methods to enhance customer service for its members,
                demonstrating the impact of targeted initiatives on
                serv<?oxy_comment_start author="rgeorgacopoulos" timestamp="20240506T154252-0500" comment="add case study for health policy"?>ice
                quality. <?oxy_comment_end?></para>
            <para>Similarly to these case studies, IKM can have a positive effect on clinical
                decision making, patient care and coordination, and research and development by
                allowing the harmonization of information between systems. However, IKM also plays
                an important role in healthcare education and training. The benefits of a well
                curated IKM training program can benefit both patient care and employee happiness
                and retention, which effectively leads to better patient care. Comprehensive
                training programs are more critical than ever as advanced technology is introduced
                into the workflow. Many healthcare organizations are facing critical staffing
                shortages and are expanding their pool of candidates via telehealth. However, this
                strategy alone cannot alleviate the need for a technologically prepared workforce.
                Instead of looking to hire new talent with relevant skills, organizations can train
                their current staff in the necessary skills. IKM can support the transfer,
                management, and retrieval of information from different parts of the healthcare
                system to create a robust training program to upskill staff. [17]</para>
            <para>Training requires active participation and buy in from both the healthcare
                administration and employees. It is important that both understand the benefit of
                training and upskilling: a well-run organization that is successful, satisfied
                employees, lessened burnout, greater retention, and better patient care and patient
                experience. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Future Implementation Strategies</title>
        <para>Implementing IKM and Tinkar in healthcare organizations will involve several key
            steps. The first step is an assessment of current systems to evaluate existing knowledge
            management and data systems to identify gaps and areas for improvement. It is important
            to involve key stakeholders, including healthcare providers, Information Technology (IT)
            professionals, and administrators, to ensure alignment and support. Our team can also
            prepare healthcare systems for the implementation of IKM and Tinkar by developing a
            strategic plan that outlines the goals, timelines, resources, and responsibilities for
            implementing IKM and Tinkar. Training and education should be provided for healthcare
            professionals and IT staff on the new systems and processes to ensure the success of the
            implementation. Throughout the implementation, thorough and continual testing of the new
            systems will need to take place to ensure they meet the required standards and are
            user-friendly. As the process evolves, continuous monitoring of the systems is necessary
            to measure effectiveness and make necessary adjustments.</para>
        <para><?oxy_comment_start author="rgeorgacopoulos" timestamp="20240506T154329-0500" comment="add a few sentences here about policy"?>Implementing<?oxy_comment_end?>
            IKM and Tinkar in healthcare can face several challenges. Many organizations face
            difficulties implementing new processes simply due to resistance to change. Addressing
            resistance by involving staff in the planning process and clearly communicating the
            benefits can help reduce the amount of resistance. Another reason workers may be
            hesitant to change is their perception of the difficulties in adapting to new
            technology. Ensuring robust IT support to manage technical issues related to system
            integration and data standardization can help mitigate this reluctance. As well as IT
            support, ongoing training will help workers adapt to the new environment. Providing
            comprehensive training to help staff adapt to new systems and processes, as well as
            upskilling can ensure adherence. Beyond preparing the workforce for any changes in their
            workflow, it is vital to implement strong data security measures to protect patient
            information and comply with regulations.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Implementing IKM into Healthcare Education</title>
        
            <para>As IKM efforts continue, its use and integration into education for providers,
                other healthcare professionals, and patients is paramount. Using the following best
                practices, IKM can enhance patient outcomes, professional knowledge, adoption of new
                solutions, and overall workflows and processes.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Participant Involvement</emphasis>: Ensure critical
                        stakeholders are involved throughout the design, testing, iterative
                        improvement, and implementation of IKM-led education.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Comprehensive Planning</emphasis><emphasis
                            role="bold">and Program Development</emphasis>: Healthcare education
                        should be designed with a holistic plan that includes needs and resource
                        assessments, thorough research and evaluation, identification of target
                        audiences and timelines, and comprehensive information sharing through IKM
                        solutions.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Integration with Target Community</emphasis>: IKM
                        solutions, and the healthcare education they support, should be integrated
                        with the target audiences. Healthcare education for patients should be
                        designed and shared with patients at appointments or telehealth
                        appointments, at school, at laboratories, and other settings where
                        healthcare is delivered. Provider and healthcare professional learning
                        should be provided at the point of care through clinical decision support
                        tools, at professional schooling and hands-on training, and more.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Creation of Lasting Impacts</emphasis>: IKM should
                        aim to making lasting and impactful changes to healthcare education that
                        lead to meaningful changes in health-related behavior. Education should be
                        designed to alter healthcare workflows, processes, or treatment based on the
                        latest research and information sharing and patients should change their
                        behavior, thinking, and interactions with their healthcare journey.
                        [15]</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Studies show that multidisciplinary and interdisciplinary knowledge is lacking in
                higher-education. [18] IKM offers a unique opportunity to support education
                development in the interdisciplinary field of healthcare by sharing knowledge from a
                wide range of resources and disciplines. Proper integration of IKM can improve
                healthcare education for both healthcare professionals and patients by addressing
                emerging trends and topics in real-time like COVID-19, universal health coverage,
                public health education, and an adequate health workforce. IKM fosters the
                integration of knowledge from a wide array of sources, and trainings will be
                continuously updated to reflect evolving knowledge. A benefit of implementing IKM
                into trainings is the ability to simplify the coordination of different sources of
                knowledge. [19]</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Measuring the Impact on Healthcare Quality</title>
        <para>Several key performance indicators (KPIs) and metrics can be utilized to measure the
            impact of IKM and Tinkar, and healthcare training and education on healthcare
            quality:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="italic">Patient Outcomes: </emphasis>Metrics such as
                readmission rates, patient recovery times, and complication rates.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="italic">Operational Efficiency: </emphasis>Indicators like
                average length of hospital stay, time to treatment, and resource utilization
                rates.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="italic">Data Accuracy and Consistency: </emphasis>Performance
                measures like the reduction in data discrepancies and errors in patient
                records.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="italic">Staff</emphasis><emphasis role="italic"
                    >Satisfaction</emphasis><emphasis role="italic">and</emphasis><emphasis
                    role="italic">Engagement: </emphasis>Surveys and feedback mechanisms to gauge
                the impact on healthcare providers' workflow and job satisfaction. [20]</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="italic">Health </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">Equity:
                </emphasis>Collection of patient data including Race, Ethnicity, and Language, and
                percentage of workforce trained in collecting this data. Other domains include data
                collection and use, cultural competency trainings, DEI in leadership, and strength
                of community partnerships. [21]</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Evaluating the effectiveness of IKM and Tinkar requires a robust data analysis to
            assess the changes in healthcare delivery and outcomes before and after implementation.
            Gathering user feedback from healthcare providers and IT staff on the usability and
            impact of  solutions is  a helpful tool when evaluating effectiveness, as well as
            regular quality audits to ensure that the solutions are being used effectively and are
            contributing to continuous healthcare improvement. Lastly, comparative studies comparing
            performance with similar healthcare organizations that have not implemented IKM and
            Tinkar can be used to identify the success of the implementation.</para>
        <para>Looking ahead, continuous improvement in healthcare quality will likely focus on
            several emerging trends in healthcare. Advanced data analytics will leverage big data
            and predictive analytics for proactive healthcare management; Personalized Medicine will
            utilize patient-specific data to tailor treatments and interventions; Integration of
            Emerging Technologies (IoET) will incorporate tools like Artificial Intelligence (AI),
            machine learning, and IoET devices into healthcare systems to enhance decision-making
            and patient monitoring. Shifting the focus to patient engagement, the healthcare process
            experience, and regular training and education will ensure that both patients and
            providers are centered in the process and healthcare professionals are up-to-date with
            the latest technologies and practices in healthcare quality improvement. [22]</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>This volume has explored the integration and potential impact of IKM and Tinkar in
            healthcare quality and education improvement. Both IKM and Tinkar play a crucial role in
            enhancing healthcare quality by improving decision-making, standardizing care processes,
            ensuring data accuracy, and optimizing both healthcare professional and patient
            education. Successful implementation requires a strategic approach, including
            stakeholder engagement, training, continuous monitoring, and the development of well
            refined key performance indicators that are collaboratively developed with various
            stakeholder groups.</para>
        <para>Overcoming challenges such as resistance to change, technical barriers, and data
            security concerns is essential for effective implementation but can be proactively
            mitigated with industry best practices. It is recommended that healthcare organizations
            embrace technological advancements, foster a culture of continuous learning, prioritize
            data security and privacy, and engage in collaborative efforts to maximize the benefits
            of IKM and Tinkar in healthcare. Patients and providers can achieve a higher quality of
            healthcare through curated trainings and educational programs enhanced by the benefits
            of IKM. In conclusion, the integration of IKM and Tinkar holds significant potential for
            advancing healthcare quality. By embracing these technologies and addressing associated
            challenges, healthcare organizations can improve patient outcomes, enhance operational
            efficiency, and pave the way for a more dynamic and patient-centered healthcare
            system.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>John Hopkins Medicine. Quality Improvement [Internet]. <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/"
                    >www.hopkinsmedicine.org.</link>2022. Avail- able from;
                    https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/nursing/center-nursing-inquiry/nursing-inquiry/quality-improvement</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services. Quality measure and quality
                    improvement [Internet]. CMS.gov. 2023. Available from:
                    https://www.cms.gov/Medicare/Quality-Initiatives-Patient-Assessment-Instruments/MMS/Quality-Measure-and-Quality-Improvement</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Batalden PB, Davidoff F. What is “quality improvement” and how can it
                    transform healthcare?. Quality and Safety in Health Care [Internet]. 2007 Feb
                    1;16(1):2–3. Available from:
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2464920/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Communications FIUD. Office of Institutional Knowledge Management [Internet].
                    medicine.fiu.edu. [cited 2024 Feb 28]. Available from:
                    https://medicine.fiu.edu/about/administrative-offices/office-of-
                    institutional-knowledge-management/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Shahmoradi L, Safadari R, Jimma W. Knowledge Management Implementation and the
                    Tools Uti- lizedin Healthcare for Evidence-Based Decision Making: A Systematic
                    Review. Ethiopian journal of health sciences [Internet]. 2017;27(5):541–58.
                    Available from:https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5615016/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Benefitsof knowledge management in healthcare | CKEditor [Internet].
                    ckeditor.com. 2023. Available from:
                    https://ckeditor.com/blog/benefits-of-knowledge-management-in-healthcare/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Why is Knowledge Management in Healthcare so Important? [Internet].
                    KnowledgeBase Blog. Available
                    from:https://www.knowledgebase.com/blog/knowledge-management-in-healthcare-so-important/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Kluwer W. Six challenges to delivering quality healthcare [Internet].<link
                        xlink:href="http://www.wolterskluwer.com/"
                    >www.wolterskluwer.com.</link>2022.
                    Availablefrom:https://www.wolterskluwer.com/en/expert-insights/six-challenges-to-delivering-quality-healthcare</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Adane K, Gizachew M, Kendie S. The role of medical data in efficient patient
                    care delivery: A re- view. Risk Management and Healthcare Policy [Internet].
                    2019;12(1):67–73. Available from:
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6486797/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Brown J. Knowledge management in the healthcare industry [Internet]. 2023
                    [cited 2024 Mar 25]. Available from:
                    https://helpjuice.com/blog/healthcare-knowledge-management#:~:text=The%20Role%20of%20Knowledge%20Management%20in%20a%20Healthcare,Operations%20and%20Process%20Improvement%20...%207%20Compliance%20</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Mujumdar V, Jeffcoat H. Leveraging Knowledge Management for Better Quality
                    Surgical Care: An Introduction [Internet]. [cited 2024 Mar 26]. Available
                        from:<link
                        xlink:href="https://www.facs.org/for-medical-professionals/news-publications/news-and-articles/bulletin/2021/03/leveraging-knowledge-management-for-better-quality-surgical-care-an-introduction/"
                        >https://www.facs.org/for-medical-professionals/news-publications/news-and-articles/bulletin/2021/03/leveraging-knowledge-management-for-better-quality-surgical-care-an-introduction/</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Koo E, McNamara S, Lansing B, Olmsted RN, Rye RA, Fitzgerald T, et al. Making
                    Infection Prevention Education Interactive can enhance knowledge and improve
                    outcomes: Results from the targeted infection prevention (TIP) study. American
                    Journal of Infection Control. 2016 Nov;44(11):1241–6.
                    doi:10.1016/j.ajic.2016.03.016 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wilson L-AM, Giles-Corti B, Burton NW, Giskes K, Haynes M, Turrell G. The
                    association between objectively measured neighborhood features and walking in
                    middle-aged adults. American Journal of Health Promotion [Internet]. 2011 Mar 1
                    [cited 2024 Mar 26];25(4). Available from:
                    https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.4278/ajhp.090421-QUAN-144
                    doi:10.4278/ajhp.090421-quan-144 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Reducing Tobacco Use Initiation: Mass Media Campaigns When Combined with Other
                    Interventions (1999 Archived Review) [Internet]. 2014 [cited 2024 Mar 28].
                    Available from:
                    https://www.thecommunityguide.org/sites/default/files/Tobacco-Mass-Media-Combined-Cessation-Archive.pdf
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Health education: Theoretical concepts, effective strategies, and core
                    competencies: A foundation document to guide capacity development of Health
                    Educators [Internet]. Cairo, Egypt: World Health Organization, Regional Office
                    for the Eastern Mediterranean; 2012 [cited 2024 Mar 26]. Available from:
                    https://iris.who.int/bitstream/handle/10665/119953/EMRPUB_2012_EN_1362.pdf?sequence=1
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Case Studies of Quality Improvement Initiatives | Agency for Healthcare
                    Research &amp; Quality [Internet]. Ahrq.gov.2011. Available
                    from:https://www.ahrq.gov/cahps/quality-improvement/reports-and-case-studies/Case-Study_QI-Initiatives.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Upskilling in healthcare to retain talent and reduce burnout | Pathstream
                    [Internet]. pathstream.com. [cited 2024 Mar 28]. Available from:
                    https://pathstream.com/upskilling-in-healthcare/#:~:text=To%20realistically%20embed%20learning%20into%20healthcare%20contexts%2C%20organizations</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Galgotia D, Lakshmi N. Implementation of Knowledge Management in higher
                    education: A comparative study of private and Government Universities in India
                    and abroad. Frontiers in Psychology [Internet]. 2022 Jun 16 [cited 2024 Mar
                    27];13. Available from:
                    https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2022.944153/full
                    doi:10.3389/fpsyg.2022.944153 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Chen B, Shin S, Wu M, Liu Z. Visualizing the knowledge domain in health
                    education: A Scientometric analysis based on CiteSpace. International Journal of
                    Environmental Research and Public Health [Internet]. 2022 Jun 19 [cited 2024 Mar
                    27];19(11):6440. Available from:
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9180308/ doi:10.3390/ijerph19116440
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Orand J. Most important metrics for a healthcare quality management dashboard
                    | symplr [In-ternet]. www.symplr.com. 2021. Available from:
                    https://www.symplr.com/blog/most-important-metrics-healthcare-quality-dashboard</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Health Equity, Diversity &amp; Inclusion Measures for Hospitals and Health
                    System Dashboards [Internet]. Available from:
                    https://ifdhe.aha.org/system/files/media/file/2020/12/ifdhe_inclusion_dashboard.pdf</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health. 8 Healthcare Quality Improvement
                    Tips [Internet]. Ex- ecutiveand Continuing Professional Education. 2017.
                    Available from:
                    https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/ecpe/8-healthcare-quality-improvement-tips/</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
