<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) Overview</title>
    <section>
        <title>Motivation for IKM</title>
        <para>Knowledge management is an important process organizations use to identify, organize,
            and disseminate information and is providing greater value and insights through data
            with the emergence of technologies and advanced analytics such as AI and machine
            learning. Individuals and organizations alike are continuously generating data which may
            sit in siloed databases, but, with the appropriate tools, can be aggregated across
            platforms, analyzed, and utilized. However, the flow of data through systems can lead to
            a myriad of issues including loss of meaning, inability to aggregate data,
            misinterpretation, and more. Achieving coordinated and standardized ways to integrate
            data across systems is an important tenant of integrated knowledge management (IKM). </para>
        <para>These issues are no different for healthcare and laboratory data. The introduction of
            the clinical information systems, including electronic health record (EHR) systems and
            laboratory information systems, in the 1960’s revolutionized the way an individual’s
            health data was stored. Health data went from static data recorded in paper records to
            dynamic, encoded knowledge stored in informational systems and introduced the ability to
            aggregate and examine these data points to generate new ideas and solve problems.
            Removing ourselves from the idealized state of full knowledge integration, the current
            landscape is composed of a range of EHR platforms, laboratory information systems (LIS),
            users, standards organizations, and agencies, all of which employ their own methods for
            collecting, recording, and using healthcare data. The healthcare system’s transformation
            into a digitalized health information system was quickly adopted but several core high
            reliability organization (HRO) principles were excluded, including ensuring the system
            was interoperable, data was of the highest quality, and patient safety was prioritized. </para>
        <para>Several organizations have emerged to address these issues through industry coding
            standards and implementation guidance. However, these have fallen short of ensuring high
            quality data with a common representation or standardization across the healthcare
            ecosystem. Standards including Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine – Clinical Terms
            (SNOMED CT), Logical Observations Identifiers Names and Codes (LOINC), RxNorm (National
            Library of Medicine’s codification of the U.S. pharmacopeia) and others exist to address
            the variation in healthcare data and resulting inefficiencies by working with
            terminology, standards, and meaning. Each organization follows a set of rules that
            govern the standards and add structure, however, even the best-meaning user may
            interpret the use of standards differently, highlighting the need to move beyond the
            reliance on standards alone. The integration of the above-mentioned organizations,
            users, and standards are important to create an interoperable and high-quality
            healthcare system. </para>
        <para>Currently, implementers must know how to work with all the existing standards and be
            familiar with their respective rules and formats. Through this body of work, we are
            advancing a reference demonstration of an IKM environment that can be used by various
            stakeholders in the laboratory ecosystem to easily view, manage, and integrate existing
            knowledge standards (e.g., SNOMED, LOINC) in a singular location, ultimately allowing
            users to identify relationships between disparate knowledge sets. This work will help
            set the foundation for a common model that would eventually help promote collaboration
            across standards-development organizations, vendors, and provider-organizations,
            improving interoperability of laboratory data across the entire ecosystem. Through IKM,
            all standards work together under one data model with tooling to work across standards
            and through redundancies. IKM can benefit healthcare and society by improving patient
            outcomes, allowing meaningful data analyses, and increasing interoperability. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Problem IKM Addresses </title>
        <para>In healthcare, organizations that help achieve standardized health data are referred
            to as Standards Development Organizations (SDOs). SDOs exist in every industry, but in
            health Information Technology (IT) the following are key examples: <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>SNOMED CT<superscript>®</superscript></entry>
                            <entry>A national standard, comprehensive and precise multilingual
                                health terminology globally [2]</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>LOINC</entry>
                            <entry>Logical Observation Identifiers Names and Codes terminology:
                                facilitate the exchange and pooling of clinical or laboratory
                                results for clinical care, outcomes management, claims attachment,
                                and research by providing a set of universal codes and names. LOINC
                                codes allow users to merge clinical results from many sources into
                                one database for patient care, clinical research, or management
                                [3]</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>RxNorm</entry>
                            <entry>Provides normalized names for clinical drugs and links its names
                                to many of the drug vocabularies commonly used in pharmacy
                                management and drug interaction software [4] </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (HL7 FHIR)</entry>
                            <entry>API focused standard that enables electronic health data to be
                                quickly and efficiently exchanged [5]</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable></para>
        <para>The Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology (ONC)
            currently oversees and promotes SDOs and supports the adoption and application of health
            data standards in the U.S. healthcare space. The structure and meaning of data must be
            maintained to achieve full data integrity and a truly interoperable system. FHIR is an
            example of a standard that works to maintain the structure of data as it flows through
            systems, while terminology organizations including SNOMED CT, RxNorm, and LOINC work to
            maintain the meaning of data. With the many existing SDOs and agencies pushing their
            adoption, issues such as overlapping standards coding standards, loss of meaning, and
            partial representation continue to exist. </para>
        <para>While medical terminology standards exist, the way they record, manage, and represent
            terminologies differs, leading to redundant and duplicative ways to reference the same
            concept. This leads to variations in clinical data exchange across the ecosystem as
            organizations use inconsistent and varied concept representation. Interoperability
            specifications aim to force these terminologies to adhere to predefined concepts, code
            systems, and reusable value sets. Although there are standardized codes and formats,
            there are many ways to use these standards. </para>
        <para>To address the current issues with disparate standards, a common model and integrated
            knowledge management capabilities are needed to support the integration and management
            of clinical terminology and local concepts to support increased data quality and
            interoperable clinical information. [1] IKM and implementation of a common model can
            support the integration of disparate standards, provide version control, and support
            extensions that otherwise do not exist. A common model for knowledge standards addresses
            the differences in management and structure across disparate terminology standards, and
            local concepts and code lists/value sets. Built off an architectural design principle,
            Separation of Concerns (SoC), where a system can be divided into sections, and each
            section can be addressed irrespective of other sections and allowed to evolve as needed.
            In this knowledge architecture, the foundational layer provides the common elements of
            interoperability including object identity, versioning, modularity, and knowledge
            representation. In this foundational architecture layer, we find the shared module
            system where version and configuration management provide the foundation for
            interoperability and the common model. </para>
        <para>A common model will unify disparate standards and address the following points when
            designing an interoperable healthcare system:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Version Control</emphasis>: changes to published
                    terminology artifacts will be documented and historic versions maintained if the
                    need for rollback arises. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Extensions</emphasis>: Improved processes around
                    extensions to terminology that conform to the requirements of the standards the
                    extension is based on. The ability to implement terminology extensions and
                    support additional content</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Goals of IKM</title>
        <para>One of the goals of this body of work is to develop both a common model and the
            necessary tooling to support the implementation of the common model and IKM
            capabilities. Our work aims to improve patient care and safety through interoperable,
            high-quality data, and accurate transmission within and between healthcare systems.
            Improved data quality will cascade to other improvements within the healthcare
            ecosystem, such as improved research capabilities, identification of real-world data
            trends, and real-time public health information. A standardized way to represent medical
            terminology must be developed to ensure new concepts are represented in a uniform and
            repeatable way and support the conversion of existing terminology standards into a
            common model while maintaining meaning, associated concepts, semantics, hierarchies, and
            other critical information and relationships. </para>
        <para>To support IKM, an implementation of a common model for knowledge standards must
            support a variety of functionalities across all knowledge standards and frameworks,
            including:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Import</emphasis> – The data model must be able to pull
                    and visualize data from LOINC, SNOMED CT, and other terminology standards into
                    the model’s data elements. Displaying the disparate terminology standards in a
                    single place will allow users and authors to compare commonalities and
                    differences between standards, identify equivalent concepts, and identify how
                    concepts relate to one another.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis> – The model must be able to convert pulled
                    data into the standardized format while maintaining meaning and any associated
                    concepts. Editing will support the identification of unnecessary or redundant
                    concepts caused by unstandardized formatting of concepts across terminology
                    standards. Editing within the model will also support a uniform way to safely
                    and reliably update, evolve, and version content over time as new concepts,
                    relationships, and information are uncovered.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Authoring</emphasis> – The model must support the
                    development of new concepts using a standardized and repeatable format to
                    maintain lossless capture and transmission of data (including identification and
                    inclusion of related concepts), incorporate new concepts such as Long COVID, and
                    meet standardized terminology formatting.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Tooling is needed to support IKM and the common model. The tooling will serve as an
            environment to view all existing standards and how they are related. Examples of
            functionality include: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Concept, semantic, hierarchy, and pattern display and navigation</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Options to view additional details of various concepts</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Clear and concise versioning information</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Equivalent concept lists</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Tinkar Overview</title>
        <para>Today’s healthcare system uses certain information systems to capture and manage
            clinical statements and terminologies. While multiple information systems and
            terminology standards exist, these standards represent and format equivalent concepts,
            semantics, and models in different ways and manage new concept release cycles and
            versioning updates asynchronously. Due to this disparate terminology representation,
            identifying equivalent concepts, transmitting data without losing key details or
            meaning, and ensuring the quality of data is a challenge. Through this body of work, we
            are aiming to improve IKM capabilities and advancing an existing HL7 project within the
            Vocabulary Working Group known as the ‘Guidelines for a Standardized Terminology
            Knowledge base”, also known as Terminology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar). Tinkar is
            intended to provide an architecture that delivers integrated terminology to the
            healthcare enterprise and its information systems. Tinkar addresses the differences in
            management and structure across reference terminology, and with local concepts and code
            lists/value sets. [1]</para>
        <para>Tinkar is a self-describing and machine processed knowledge architecture that allows
            for effective and scalable querying of data, concepts, and information. Using locally
            defined concepts, Tinkar can integrate various terminology standards into the common
            model by accommodating, managing, and defining granular components and their respective
            data sources to support interoperability of semantics. Having the ability to manage
            complex and individual elements of each standard then allows continual process
            improvement, including rapid extension development. Edits to concepts or newly authored
            concepts in Tinkar can be tested and previewed before deployment to a live environment
            and historic versioning of meta data is perpetually maintained to support iterative
            authoring, development, and versioning. [1]</para>
        <para>Tinkar aims to improve the quality of patient care across the healthcare enterprise by
            creating a cross-cutting and common model that can integrate other terminology standards
            and use a repeatable and standardized process to convert disparate clinical statements
            and terminologies into high-quality, interoperable, and exportable clinical data. The
            four main problems that Tinkar and a common model can address are:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Suboptimal ability to identify equivalent concepts within and between
                    terminology standards</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Concepts like “Feels Feverish” and “Feels Hot/Feverish” are both
                            concepts in SNOMED CT but are not recognized as equivalent within SNOMED
                            CT. Tinkar’s standardized process would support the identification of
                            these findings as equivalent and create a relationship between the
                            concepts.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>No standardized way to represent newly identified concepts in real-time</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Terminology standards currently lack the ability to rapidly adapt and
                            deploy pertinent concepts in response to emerging phenomenon, such as
                            COVID-19. Tinkar would allow for a standardized and repeatable process
                            to rapidly develop and version concepts in response to real-time
                            healthcare developments.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Accidental use of incorrect or less accurate concepts due to a lack of
                    harmonization between terminology standards</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The lack of standardized representation of concepts between standards
                            leads to unnecessary confusion, redundant and overlapping concepts, and
                            challenges identifying the most accurate concept when transmitting data
                            between systems and terminology standards. Tinkar works to reduce this
                            unnecessary complication with clear versioning hierarchies that allow
                            for precise identification and representations of appropriate
                            terminologies between standards.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Asynchronous versioning that does not clearly convey detailed descriptions of
                    changes</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Versioning within terminology standards is not currently well documented or clearly
            conveyed to users and versioning between terminology standards is done asynchronously.
            Tinkar will support transparent, detailed, standardized and rapid versioning that
            focuses on improvements for users.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>FDA, SHIELD, and IKM Capabilities</title>
        <para>Our team, in collaboration with the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and the
            Systemic Harmonization and Interoperability Enhancement for Laboratory Data (SHIELD)
            program, are working to demonstrate how Tinkar architecture can optimize and implement
            IKM capabilities and IKM principles through the development of a reference
            implementation. One of FDA’s primary missions is “protecting the public health by
            ensuring the safety, efficacy, and security of human and veterinary drugs, biological
            products, and medical devices”. By improving the quality and interoperability of
            healthcare data our work supports the proper a plethora of medical devices. SHIELD aims
            to support increased patient safety through improved interoperability, transmission, and
            quality of laboratory data between and within healthcare systems. [6]</para>
        <para>The team is supporting FDA and SHIELD goals by demonstrating the reference
            implementation in September 2023 to showcase a common model and standardized framework
            for medical terminology representation and authoring. The September demo will showcase a
            proof-of-concept model that will be further matured and built upon in subsequent
            contract years. The team has and will continue to use an Agile methodology to
            systematically iterate on Tinkar, and overall model development using sprint frameworks
            across a variety of work streams. At the end of the contract’s base year, the team will
            have developed a comprehensive use case that will be used as a reference implementation
            to investigate capabilities to improve clinical analytics and address current state gaps
            to reach an idealized future state.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>IKM Challenges</title>
        <para>While IKM promises a revolutionary way to improve the quality and interoperability of
            healthcare data in the name of improved patient safety and patient outcomes, achieving a
            truly integrated ecosystem will pose a variety of challenges. Creating an IKM
            architecture is itself a major undertaking, but will require a deep, fundamental
            understanding and a detailed approach to address the following challenges. These
            challenges are not exhaustive and will evolve as our team continues our work and
            findings.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Federal Regulation</title>
            <para>As with any new or emerging technology, a variety of Federal agencies will need to
                play a major part in the implementation of an IKM system. Not only is their review
                and approval of the proposed system a necessity before we can implement this tool
                with patient facing healthcare systems, like labs and hospitals, but the federal
                government will also need to develop mandates and incentives to encourage the
                private sector to participate and meet the minimum requirements needed to support
                IKM. Due to the inherent complexity and holistic approach to data, IKM will require
                multiple federal agencies to support and drive participation, like:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) and Office of the
                        National Coordinator for Health IT (ONC) will need to outline minimum data
                        requirements for orders to ensure the participating entities are capturing
                        standardized data elements for standardized questions that come from a
                        well-known and widely available source of truth </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) will need to develop an
                        authorization process that requires new and existing terminology standard
                        organizations, healthcare systems, product developers, and more to comply
                        with pertinent standards prior to incorporation into the IKM platform</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) must provide basic
                        standards and easily accessible guidance to enforce standardized data
                        collection, aggregation, and transmission for the various healthcare systems
                        within the IKM platform</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>It is critical for our team to coordinate with federal agencies as early as
                possible to gather and incorporate their feedback, provide extensive information
                detailing our work, the intended goals, and benefits, and collaborate on
                requirements to support improved data quality and patient safety. A detailed
                stakeholder engagement plan that details timelines, stakeholder dependencies, and
                required actions is required to efficiently develop these mandates and
                requirements.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Stakeholder Incentives</title>
            <para>While SHIELD and the FDA do not want to mandate the use of the IKM environment,
                federal agencies will need to develop minimum requirements and incentives to
                encourage higher education, private sector, and other stakeholders to participate.
                Meeting the minimum requirements for data collection and data transmission will
                require changes to the user interface (UI) and user experience (UX) that standardize
                data entry requirements, representation of data elements, and transmission of data
                on the front and back end of healthcare and laboratory systems. These could be
                extensive changes depending on the age and current data collection of the systems.
                Before hospitals and laboratories commit both financial and personnel resources to
                perform gap assessments, identify areas of improvement, implement changes, train
                staff and users, and sustain updates, regulators and implementers will need to use
                statistical analysis and evidence-based discussions to highlight the current
                problems with data and how these problems directly impact or relate to each
                stakeholder on an individualized level. Demonstrations showing how improvements to
                patient safety, optimization of data collection, transmission, and querying, and the
                IKM environment with statistics analysis will address these current state issues and
                use financial incentives to encourage stakeholders to achieve the optimized future
                state we are working towards.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Coordination Across Standards</title>
            <para>A defining feature of IKM is working to harmonize various terminology standards
                using a common language to standardize data capture while maintain meaning and
                associated concepts throughout transmission and storage. This requires working with
                a variety of terminology standards that asynchronously represent, update, manage,
                and version concepts. The IKM architecture will require a robust and standardized
                process to track changes across terminology standards and version Tinkar concepts
                appropriately in a repeatable way. Changes will need to be made in real time and
                will need to communicate the intricacies of updates, test the validity and
                functionality of changes, and maintain STAMP principles. Changes to concepts may
                occur concurrently as terminology standards release updates and will need to be
                tested and validated using the Tinkar authoring environment.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
    </section>
    <section>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>HL7 Logical Model: Standardized Terminology Knowledgebase, Release 1.
                        Terminology Knowledge Architecture Informative Ballot. HL7 Vocabulary Work
                        Group. August 2021. <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/private/standards/HL7_LM_TERM_KB_R1_INFORM_2021AUG_FINAL.pdf"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>National Library of Medicine. Overview of SNOMED CT [Internet]. Nih.gov.
                        U.S. National Library of Medicine; 2016. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/healthit/snomedct/snomed_overview.html"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LOINC — The freely available standard for identifying health measurements,
                        observations, and documents. [Internet]. Loinc.org. 2019. Available from:
                            <link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>National Library of Medicine. RxNorm [Internet]. www.nlm.nih.gov. 2020.
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/research/umls/rxnorm/index.html"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>FHIR Fact Sheets | HealthIT.gov [Internet]. www.healthit.gov. Available
                        from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.healthit.gov/topic/standards-technology/standards/fhir-fact-sheets"
                        />
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Health C for D and R. Systemic Harmonization and Interoperability
                        Enhancement for Laboratory Data (SHIELD). FDA [Internet]. 2023 Mar 24 [cited
                        2023 May 31]; Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/diagnostic-data-program/systemic-harmonization-and-interoperability-enhancement-laboratory-data-shield"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>

