<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section>
        <title>Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) Book Motivation</title>
        <para>In today’s healthcare ecosystem, providers continually rely on data from an increasing
            number of sources to make informed clinical decisions. While this data is a critical
            component of providing patients with the best care possible, there are major challenges
            with the accuracy, interoperability, and quality of data that is transmitted within and
            between healthcare systems. Clinical terminology standards are one strategy to
            standardize data collection and improve the quality of patient care with standardized
            and repeatable guidelines for encoding health data, however these standards often lose
            critical aspects of the original data capture when they are shared with other providers
            and healthcare systems. To enhance the quality, interoperability and usability of
            patient data, the health care industry requires a solution that harmonizes the different
            clinical terminology standards and generates a common model that supports patient care,
            data querying and analysis, public health, and policy making. In an ideal world with
            interoperable data, data misrepresentations and errors that result in patient harm and
            other inefficiencies in the health care ecosystem would be eliminated entirely. The
            motivation for this work is to explore the pathway to unifying a patient’s care
            experience through reliable and interoperable data that supports accurate and timely
            clinical decision support that is solely prompted and driven by real-world data and
            provides real-time assistance to clinicians.</para>
        <para>The essential challenge of informatics practice within the healthcare enterprise is to
            quickly deliver a high fidelity reasoned interpretation of principles and facts to the
            point of care—and then to quickly aggregate these point of care experiences for analytic
            analysis so that new principles and facts can be formulated and validated as part of a
            continuous optimization of healthcare knowledge and delivery. To effectively answer this
            challenge, we must focus on simplification and integration of knowledge assets, and on
            build, test, deploy, and release processes for delivering these assets to the points of
            care and analysis. This focus on perhaps mundane topics is not because we think that
            novelty has no place in our work; rather, that without a focus on aspects of our
            delivery challenge that are often treated as peripheral to the overall problem, we
            cannot achieve reliable, rapid, low-risk knowledge-asset development and delivery in an
            efficient manner.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Overview of IKM Book</title>
        <para>This Inteagrated Knowledge Management (IKM) Book servers as an educational resource to
            allow stakeholders to perform a deep dive into the IKM Architecture this team has worked
            to develop. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Purpose of This Document</title>
            <para>This book will act as 1) a reference for understanding the complex, multi-layered,
                and highly inter-dependent Health IT landscape, and 2) a framework for the
                implementation of a layered, architecture-based approach to integrating and managing
                knowledge in the healthcare ecosystem that will seek to solve the previously
                identified issues.</para>
            <para>This framework, referred to throughout this book as the Knowledge Architecture, is
                a methodology seeking to enable the concept of Integrated Knowledge Management
                throughout the healthcare ecosystem.</para>
            <para>Through examples and illustrations, this book seeks to demonstrate that such an
                approach for managing knowledge will allow for:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">The ability to recognize equivalence between
                            different standards that are representing the same clinical data,
                        </emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">The ability to represent clinically significant
                            concepts that are needed in a system of record, such as an EHR or LIS,
                            unambiguously, </emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">The ability to prevent the inclusion and/or
                            perpetuation of errors in clinical data represented within healthcare
                            systems of record, and </emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">The ability to ensure the safe and reliable
                            evolution of terminology standards, solutions, and processes as new
                            technologies and policies are implemented.</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The intent of the IKM Book is to have a direct connection to real world events and
                circumstances. For a granular and detailed breakdown of real world examples, please
                refer to Appendix A.
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>(CREATE LINK TO
                APPENDIX HERE)<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>IKM Guiding Principles</title>
            <para>The following key principles are critical in our summarization and discussion of
                Integrated Knowledge Management. </para>
            <para>Functional decomposition—often referred to as a Separation of Concerns
                (SoC)—across components or sections with a specific purpose is a foundational design
                principle for complex system architecture. SoC allows a complete system to be
                subdivided into distinct sections or components with well-defined functionality and
                dependencies. If successful, this approach allows individual sections to be reused,
                as well as designed, implemented, and updated independently to address emerging
                requirements. This is especially useful and important in a medical context given how
                many different health information and clinical terminology projects are ongoing at
                any given time. Efforts are often uncoordinated and led by disparate and unrelated
                standards development organizations. In these cases, SoC allows teams to
                simultaneously work independently and in coordination with each other and reuse the
                resulting artifacts.</para>
            <para>The architecture presented in this book is inspired by core evolutionary design
                principles called “Understandable, Reproducible, and Useful,” upon which SNOMED CT
                development is still based. [1, 2] These criteria describe an approach for improving
                data quality and increasing data integrity and agility: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Understandable: </emphasis>The content can be
                        processed by health IT systems and understood by most healthcare providers
                        without reference to private or inaccessible information. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reproducible: </emphasis>Multiple users or systems
                        apply the data to the same situations and source data with an equivalent
                        result. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Useful: </emphasis>Data is fit-for-purpose – it has
                        practical value for data analysis in support of health information exchange,
                        research, and public health that requires information aggregation across
                        health IT systems. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>In order to produce highly reliable software, the following tenets must be applied
                within a tooling’s software development methodology: Use-case driven,
                architecture-centric, iterative and incremental.<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Use-case Driven</emphasis>: Defining,
                            developing, and refining software design(s) to meet known and emerging
                            use cases enable software solutions to meet critical real-world
                            needs.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Architecture-centric</emphasis>: Formally
                            documenting the “layers” of capabilities that a software system may have
                            enables developers to identify dependencies between layers, allowing for
                            shared responsibility of reducing functional complexity across the
                            entire software solution.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Iterative and Incremental</emphasis>: Similar to
                            the Agile mindset, developing software solutions should in small,
                            iterative, and incremental ways thus affording time to perform adequate
                            Independent Validation and Verification (IV&amp;V) methodologies.
                            IV&amp;V methodologies include general-purpose validation approaches
                            conducted by an organization that is not involved in development to
                            generate metrics for data and software quality. From a health
                            information exchange perspective, IV&amp;V can help compare and test
                            source data against requirements of a destination system through manual,
                            semi-automated, and automated inspection of source-to-destination data
                            reviews, thereby helping ensure a sound data strategy intended to reduce
                            patient safety risk and improve data quality for analysis and tracking.
                            [3]</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Knowledge Architecture</title>
            <para>Increased reliance on computerized health records, including EHRs Systems,
                requires standardized medical terminology to encode health information consistently
                across systems and enterprises. Clinicians require not only objective quantitative
                measurements (e.g., 90 beats per minute for a patient’s pulse), but also procedural
                context (e.g., pulse oximetry, manual) about past observations or requests for
                future interventions. While two quantitative measurements may be the same, the
                procedural information could indicate meaningful semantic differences and lead to
                different clinical interpretation and treatment. As information is exchanged across
                systems, the solution requires a common understanding of data, a method to support
                knowledge representation, and clinical decision rules based on common terminology
                and statements. Each component must address an aspect and together need to address
                the requirements of clinicians. Current HL7 standard implementations rely on
                profiles and templates to disambiguate statement and terminology and provide
                sufficient precision for transactions, documents, and standards-based APIs.
                Therefore, the architectural approach described here is applicable to standards
                organizations developing interoperability for enterprise and project-specific
                implementations in equal measure.</para>
            <para>The Knowledge Architecture, by definition, is a framework for clinical information
                that is organized into distinct layers such that each higher layer relies upon
                artifacts from the lower layer. The purpose of the Knowledge Architecture is to
                standardize clinical statements and terminologies by providing abstraction &amp;
                eliminating unnecessary complexity. It helps to do this by:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Integrating essential clinical terminologies into a coherent
                    integrated system: </emphasis><itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Localized terminology specific to one organization or system </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>EHR Vendor Terminologies (such as Cerner's Code Sets, Event Codes,
                            Event Set Hierarchy)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Interoperability standards: SNOMED, LOINC, RxNorm, and similar</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist><emphasis role="bold">Defining a Standardized Form for clinical
                    statements:</emphasis><itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Reduce unnecessary complexity and improve logical structure</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a coherent integrated healthcare data system</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create an analysis normal form for clinical statements</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>The proposed architecture, shown visually below, serves as an
                implementation of SoC, and helps to break out and organize inter-dependent types of
                knowledge in a way that allows for reuse, ongoing development, and independent
                updates. If employed, this model can help the healthcare ecosystem to individually
                resolve issues in their data within their layers, rather than the entire system,
                leading to much more agile improvement</para>
            <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
            <para>Figure 1: PASTF Model <?oxy_custom_end?></para>
            <para>Detailed descriptions of each layer will be spelled out in the chapters that
                follow, but brief descriptions of each can be found below:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Foundational Architecture</emphasis> – The foundational
                layer of the Knowledge Architecture provides the common elements of
                interoperability, such as: object identity, versioning, modularity, and knowledge
                representation. It includes (a) the foundation and building blocks of the common
                model; (b) how the repeatable transformation process of disparate standards into the
                common model promotes interoperability with other environments; and (c) how the
                modules of the architecture are tightly version controlled over time. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Terminology Knowledge</emphasis> – The terminology knowledge
                layer is responsible for structured sets of medical terms and codes that define
                concepts of interest, including descriptions, dialects, language, and semantic
                hierarchy. SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, and RxNorm are part of this layer. It defines what
                valid codes or expressions may be used by higher level layers.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Statement Model</emphasis> – The statement model layer is
                responsible for defining how data elements are combined to create a statement. This
                layer reuses the artifacts defined in the terminology knowledge layer.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Assertional Knowledge</emphasis> – The assertional knowledge
                layer makes use of the Terminology Knowledge layer concepts to specify non-defining
                facts that may be used by procedural knowledge algorithms. An example fact might be
                that “thiazide diuretics treat hypertension.” Assertional knowledge may also
                indicate what symptoms may be associated with a disorder.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Procedural Knowledge</emphasis> – The procedural knowledge
                layer, also known as imperative knowledge, is the knowledge exercised in the
                performance of some task. An example would be determining a hypertension treatment
                plan by analyzing a combination of a patient’s clinical statements and the available
                assertional knowledge. The procedural knowledge is responsible for information about
                standard ways to carry out specific procedures, as well as other procedural
                guidelines, (e.g., treatment protocols for diseases and order sets focused on
                certain patient situations). Procedural knowledge, together with assertional
                knowledge, enables clinical decision support, quality measurement, and patient
                safety. This layer relies on the architectural foundation and terminology layers,
                incorporates the statement model for information retrieval, and uses assertional
                knowledge. Procedural knowledge artifacts may include clinical alert rules,
                reminders, etc., that trigger actions or recommend interventions.</para>
            <para>Examining a clinical procedure for controlling hypertension illustrates each of
                the layers of the informatics architectural separation of concerns.<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>At the terminology knowledge layer, there may be various codes and
                            terms from disparate source terminologies to define a concept (e.g.,
                            hypertension). Ideally, these overlapping codes and terms would be
                            oriented to the same parent concept during the transformation and
                            integration process at the foundational architecture layer.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The statement model layer enables representation of blood pressure
                            measurement values (e.g., systolic BP = 140 mmHg), or the categorical
                            data (e.g., pregnancy induced hypertension vs. renal hypertension)
                            within a standard data structure to facilitate information exchange or
                            retrieval, such as within a standards-based clinical statement (i.e.,
                            FHIR).</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The assertional knowledge layer represents non-procedural statements,
                            or facts, such as “Stage 2 high blood pressure is over 140 systolic or
                            90 diastolic,” or “beta-blockers and ACE inhibitors may be used to treat
                            hypertension”, or “beta-blockers are contraindicated in patients with a
                            diagnosis of reactive airway disease.”</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Finally, the procedural knowledge layer provides algorithms to analyze
                            clinical statements about a patient, in combination with the assertional
                            knowledge, to recommend a treatment protocol for different kinds of
                            hypertension, including the considerations of, (e.g., patient age,
                            co-morbidities etc., which can be generated by an electronic clinical
                            decision support system [statement + assertional layers]). This layer
                            adds support for workflow and conditional logic (i.e.,
                            if-then-else).</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>IKM Value Proposition</title>
            <para>Implementing Integrated Knowledge Management will reduce the challenges associated
                with unpredictable, poorly controlled, and reactive health IT data. The Knowledge
                Architecture described above will provide the foundation for robust configuration
                management and quality assurance of health IT data while allowing for a standardized
                update and extension process. This approach will support increased clinical and
                laboratory data quality and enable healthcare systems across the industry to conduct
                robust and meaningful data analysis and increase overall interoperability, which
                ultimately enhances the quality of care across all medical facilities.</para>
            <para>The purpose of employing the Knowledge Architecture and enabling Integrated
                Knowledge Management can be succinctly described through its benefits: improved
                patient outcomes, meaningful data analysis, and increased interoperability. </para>
            <section>
                <title>Improved Patient Outcomes</title>
                <para>Patient care will be optimized and efficient, enabling clinicians to provide
                    high-quality care to all patients across all medical facilities.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Meaningful Data Analysis</title>
                <para>Medical facilities will be able to easily query specific health factors to
                    gain necessary insights, draw conclusions, and make recommendations based on
                    accurate patient data.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Increased Interoperability</title>
                <para>Medical facilities will have more interoperable capabilities, opening the door
                    for future opportunities to integrate patient data with other agencies,
                    community partners, and the private sector.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title> Preface from Keith Campbell</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title> IKM Book Introduction</title>
        <section>
            <title>The Promise of Health Information Technology</title>
            <para>Health Information Technology (IT), or the use of computer hardware, software, or
                infrastructure to record, store, protect, and retrieve clinical, administrative, or
                financial information, has become a critically important form of organizing,
                managing, analyzing, and exchanging patient health information. [4] Though first
                employed in the 1960s, Health IT entered the scene and obtained widespread adoption
                in the early-1990s promising:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The enhancement of quality and safety of healthcare,</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The ability to more easily measure and reduce the cost of care,</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The ability to share information with multiple providers across
                        organizations in a continuum of care,</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The ability to implement and automate high-quality decision support into
                        clinical workflows, and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The ability to improve clinician/provider satisfaction and reduce burden
                        and burnout. [5]</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The most commonly known forms of Health IT systems, Electronic Health Records
                (EHRs), or a systematized collection of electronically stored patient and population
                health information, have undoubtably enabled dramatic advancements in patient care,
                allowing for breakthrough technologies with advanced analytical capabilities (e.g.,
                Machine Learning [ML], Artificial Intelligence [AI]) to more easily identify new
                diseases and develop treatments and reduce the need for patients to maintain and
                carry paper records from provider to provider.  </para>
            <para>Despite advancement in technologies like these, a Johns Hopkins study conducted in
                2016 suggested that preventable medical errors, including those due to EHR errors,
                accounted for approximately 250,000 patient deaths every year – making it the
                third-leading cause of death in the United States. [6] When Crico, a medical
                professional liability organization, identified 147 cases of patient harm over five
                years in which an EHR was identified as a contributing factor, a staggering 80
                percent of these cases involved moderate or severe harm to the patient. [7] In
                total, an estimated $61 million in direct payments and legal expenses resulted from
                these cases, at an average cost of $415,000 per case.</para>
            <para>On the surface, exciting new technology has continued to advance in the healthcare
                ecosystem, but cases of patient harm, redundant testing, and over-expenditure
                persists. This begs the question: <emphasis role="bold">is Health IT truly
                    fulfilling its promises?</emphasis></para>
            <para>Technology has the potential to revolutionize patient care – concepts like AI and
                ML promise better patient outcomes and reduced clinician burden. However, these
                systems are only as good as the data from which they operate. EHRs, for example,
                were created to provide healthcare automation, patient care and patient access, and
                reduce clinician workload. The advancements in EHRs have had a great impact for
                patients, but users continue to face complications due to the lack of standardized
                data exchange. Unstandardized data stacking has made it difficult to interpret a
                patient’s chart with accurate data reporting. [8] As far as healthcare technology
                has come, the quality of existing technology platforms is limited through the
                quality of encoded data – which is where the problem begins.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Problems with Electronic Health Data</title>
            <para>While healthcare information originates across a variety of disparate systems and
                organizations, the United States healthcare environment requires interoperable,
                coordinated, and accurate information to support high quality patient care, clinical
                and laboratory research, public health monitoring, and regulatory decision making.
                Many needs must be met in the existing, fragmented healthcare setting which includes
                a network of interconnected information systems.</para>
            <para>Historically, the United States healthcare system has been composed of relatively
                autonomous organizations that maintain loose relationships in support of patient
                care. Patients typically visit one or more primary care clinicians and are
                frequently sent, along with orders and patient data, to specialists, laboratories,
                and other care teams. The observation and interpretation of patients’ healthcare
                data across these settings is crucial to the processes of making safe clinical
                decisions, tracking patient outcomes, anticipating future health problems,
                identifying deviations from expected trends, informing preventive and public health
                measures, supporting clinical research, and providing a legal and historical record.
                [9] </para>
            <para>To provide context with an example, when a primary care provider records a
                diabetes diagnosis in their local system, it is critical for that system to share
                the data accurately and seamlessly to the pertinent pharmacy and laboratory systems.
                These systems must then in turn communicate with one another and with the primary
                care system to alert the provider that the patient has previously been prescribed
                gentamicin and has recently been given an order for a radiologic examination that
                requires intravenous iodine dye – both of which are known to affect kidney function.
                If this information is not accurately communicated across healthcare settings in a
                way that can be readily accessed, the patient may face unnecessary harm or risks
                that could have been avoided.</para>
            <para>The following sections aim to spell out some of the current problems with
                electronic health data more clearly:</para>
            <section>
                <title>The Need for Unmatched Precision</title>
                <para>The degree to which data must maintain precision in healthcare is unmatched in
                    other industries. Health data is unique in its direct association with a
                    person’s health outcomes. Nuanced concepts exist in patient care settings
                    creating challenges for the representation thereof in data capture and
                    transmission. Laboratory testing on a specimen involves a plethora of biological
                    concepts which must be represented by data in a meaningful way while maintaining
                    precision as well as consumption for other entities or systems in the ecosystem.
                    When an association to a patient’s health outcomes is combined with such nuanced
                    concepts, exceptional rigor must be taken in the maintenance of data precision
                    and representation.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>The Size, Scale, and Complexity of the System</title>
                <para>The ecosystem of healthcare entities, which share responsibility in the
                    delivery of care, is vast. Various stakeholders include government health
                    authorities, EHR companies, medical device manufacturers, health insurance
                    companies, medical laboratories, hospitals and healthcare systems, and clinical
                    providers among various site types. A healthcare entity’s data requirements
                    differ in context from other industries regarding the facilitation of patient
                    care and handling of health data in methods that are specific to their context.
                    Industries such as transportation and logistics are more confined to a common
                    context for the data required to successfully facilitate operations. The array
                    of contexts for healthcare entities creates an unsolved challenge for
                    interpreting and exchanging data without compromising its intended meaning.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>The Lack of Adherence and Enforcement of Standards </title>
                <para>Standards in healthcare exist to promote successful interpretation and
                    exchange of data; however, they are not enforced and can experience poor
                    adherence in practice, undercutting their effectiveness and purpose. Despite a
                    significant history of emphasis on healthcare data standards, entities continue
                    to leverage proprietary, or localized, methods for data representation creating
                    inherent and avoidable challenges in care delivery, reporting, and the
                    meaningful application of available technology. Motivations for proprietary or
                    localized data methods cannot be confirmed, however, considerations include
                    protection of market share from competitors and avoidance of public scrutiny for
                    misalignment to standard processes. Maintaining alignment with standards
                    development organizations (SDOs) is resource intensive and invites SDOs to
                    measure and scrutinize an organization against the standard processes to which
                    an entity claims conformity. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>The Inability to Share Between Systems</title>
                <para>Numerous distinct systems and organizations across the healthcare ecosystem
                    lead to a large variation in how data are handled, e.g., data collection, data
                    manipulation, data transmission, data storage, and real-world application. Each
                    system has a proprietary, standard, or ad-hoc information model and is typically
                    configured to satisfy organization-specific needs, resulting in differences in
                    data handling within systems. While this variation is not an innate issue, the
                    difficulty exchanging data between systems and the lack of interoperability
                    compromises data quality and ultimately patient safety. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>The Significant Variation in Types of Data Needed</title>
                <para>Medical data range in format from narrative and textual data to numerical
                    measurements, images, drawings, and more. It is common practice for several
                    different observations of a singular patient to be made concurrently, the
                    observation of the same patient parameter to be made over the course of several
                    points in time, or both. [9] It is also important to keep a record of the
                    circumstances under which data are obtained, further adding to the complexity
                    and volume of data. For example, a simple blood pressure reading may factor if a
                    blood pressure reading is taken on the arm or the leg, whether the patient
                    recently exercised, and what kind of device was used.</para>
                <para>Current approaches for representing data from various, disparate health
                    information systems introduce additional opportunities for inefficiencies,
                    redundancies, and inconsistencies. Unpredictable and denormalized data formats
                    reduce the quality of data processing and the ability to conduct safe and
                    reliable analytics. When incongruent data is repeatedly collated, it requires
                    extensive expertise and resources to synthesize basic trends, information, and
                    insights that should be readily available. A history of numerous scholarly and
                    practical efforts illustrates the challenges of using observational data for
                    safe patient care, comparative effectiveness research, and analyses for biases,
                    workflow differences, and issues with variations in data collection, such as
                    invalid, inconsistent, and missing data. [10 – 25]</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>A Brief Overview of Health Data Standards</title>
            <para>Standards are generally required when excessive variation creates inefficiencies
                or impedes effectiveness. [9] There have been many valuable standards applied
                throughout history such as railroad tracks, telephones, WiFi, and financial
                transactions. The broad goal of the application of standards to electronic health
                data is unambiguous data exchange, or “interoperability” – the ability of two
                parties, either human or machine, to exchange data or information so that it is
                transportable, organizable, and interpretable in an expected format. </para>
            <para>Standards for electronic health data have existed since the creation of the EHR in
                the 1960s. Computer engineers responsible for EHR development were tasked with
                representing health concepts in a digital format that could be shared with users and
                connected systems for common interpretation. In 1965, the Systematized Nomenclature
                of Pathology (SNOP) was developed to provide a common way to describe morphology and
                anatomy. A decade later, SNOP expanded into its known name today, Systematized
                Nomenclature of Medicine (SNOMED). As the adoption of EHRs increased during the
                1980s, Health Level Seven International (HL7) was formed in 1987 as a non-profit,
                American National Standards Institute (ANSI)-accredited standards development
                organization to develop standards that provide global health data interoperability.
                Since then, several SDOs in the healthcare space have appeared and, along with HL7
                and SNOMED, continued to commit resources to the development and adoption of
                standardized health data processes. In 2004, under the United States Department of
                Health and Human Services (HHS), the Office of the National Coordinator for Health
                Information Technology (ONC) was born to promote a national health information
                technology infrastructure and oversee its development. While ONC is not an SDO, it
                works in close coordination with SDOs to support the adoption and application of
                health data standards in the U.S. </para>
            <para> While interoperable health data is a complex and nuanced topic, a primary
                component is maintaining the meaning and intent of clinical data from the point of
                consumption throughout the transmission and use of that data across various systems.
                As data is exchanged within and between multiple healthcare systems, the original
                provider’s meaning and intent must be electronically communicated in a way that,
                upon receipt, receiving systems and providers can understand in an identical manner.
                Data exchange standards provide a formal process for defining specific constructs to
                be exchanged between machines and must be used to support this seamless transfer of
                data.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Structure and Meaning</title>
                <para>In simple terms, <emphasis role="italic">Structure </emphasis>and<emphasis
                        role="italic"> Meaning </emphasis>are two considerations to ensure data
                    maintains its full integrity and can be communicated in a way that supports
                    interoperability.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Structure</emphasis> is the ability of systems to
                    agree on how to format the data. Structural interoperability ensures the
                    seamless communication of the data’s structure between systems but does not
                    guarantee that the receiving system will interpret the data with the original
                    intent. Web pages, for instance, are developed using HTML or XML to ensure
                    structural interoperability. While this guarantees a web page can be read by any
                    machine with a web browser, it does not ensure the meaning of that page is
                    identical across machines. There are a variety of healthcare structural
                    standards, including Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR), Health
                    Level Seven (HL7) Version 2 Messaging (HL7 v2), and Consolidated Clinical
                    Document Architecture (C-CDA). </para>
                <para>To understand structural interoperability, consider the two sentences below.
                    While both sentences have the same sentence <emphasis role="italic"
                        >structure</emphasis>, their <emphasis role="italic">meanings</emphasis> are
                    completely different and only one makes logical sense.</para>
                <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?><emphasis
                        role="bold">Figure 2: Structural
                    Interoperability</emphasis><?oxy_custom_end?></para>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Meaning</emphasis> is the ability of systems to share
                    the same interpretation of the data. Meaning interoperability ensures the
                    original meaning and intent of data is interpreted identically across all
                    parties but allows for structural variance. When people and systems use
                    different words and codes to describe synonymous or related things, healthcare
                    meaning standards translate the data to a common meaning. Healthcare terminology
                    and meaning standards include Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical
                    Terms (SNOMED CT®), the Logical Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes
                    (LOINC®) and RxNorm (a terminology defining medications and ingredients from the
                    National Library of Medicine).</para>
                <para>In the below example, the two sentences share a common <emphasis role="italic"
                        >meaning</emphasis>, however the sentence <emphasis role="italic"
                        >structure</emphasis> varies drastically. </para>
                <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?><emphasis
                        role="bold">Figure 3: Meaning
                    Interoperability</emphasis><?oxy_custom_end?></para>
                <para>While Figure 1 and 2 intend to illustrate <emphasis role="italic"
                        >structure</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">meaning</emphasis> simply,
                    a more real-world example like, “the patient was given pain medication” and “the
                    patient was given medication for pain,” highlights potential issues when
                    determining equivalence. Objectively, the two sentences do not follow the same
                        <emphasis role="italic">structure;</emphasis> however, they may or may not
                    have the same <emphasis role="italic">meaning</emphasis> depending on your
                    perspective or interpretation. The first sentence could be read to mean “the
                    provider prescribed the patient pain medication to address pain” or that “the
                    patient acquired pain medication from another source other than the provider.”
                    The complex relationship between these two concepts can lead to confusion and
                    will need to be addressed to accurately characterize equivalence.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example of Overlapping and Intersecting Nature of Standards</title>
                <para>Hospitals and independent reference labs are two primary entities in the
                    health data ecosystem which share direct relationships and interfaces in the
                    exchange of clinical data. Healthcare interfaces must leverage various existing
                    standards for <emphasis role="italic">structure </emphasis>and<emphasis
                        role="italic"> meaning</emphasis> and use them together in integrated ways.
                    An electronic interface provides an avenue, or connection point, for sharing
                    data in a meaningful, coherent way between two disparate systems. Without an
                    interface, two disparate systems are unable to communicate in a common language.
                    In the U.S. and elsewhere, the most common and accepted messaging structural
                    standard for EHR-to- Reference Lab interfacing is the Health Level Seven (HL7)
                    Version 2.x (V2.x) standard. While other messaging standards exist and can be
                    used, the HL7 V2.x messaging standard, first released in 1987, is used in 95% of
                    U.S. healthcare organizations and in more than 35 countries. [26] </para>
                <para>To illustrate how standards for <emphasis role="italic">structure
                        </emphasis>and<emphasis role="italic"> meaning</emphasis> may be currently
                    implemented, we will explore a scenario of a typical hospital-to-reference lab
                    order message generated by a hospital EHR system sent electronically to a
                    Reference Lab. This laboratory order message is received, processed, and acted
                    upon by which the laboratory will perform the test specified in the order
                    message received. After a laboratory test is performed and a test result is
                    available, the Reference Laboratory in this scenario will return a Laboratory
                    Result message to the hospital EHR system.</para>
                <para>Figure 3 below shows an example of an HL7 v2 Observation (OBX) segment from
                    two different mock lab result messages. In this scenario, a laboratory has
                    conducted two distinct blood glucose tests on two distinct specimen sources. For
                    the first test, a specimen from serum or plasma was used. For the second test,
                    the specimen was from whole blood. The figure below illustrates how the HL7 v2
                        <emphasis role="italic">structure</emphasis> standard is populated using
                    existing terminology standards for <emphasis role="italic">meaning,
                    </emphasis>in this case LOINC. In the first HL7 segment for test 1, the LOINC
                    code is for a “Glucose [Mass/volume] in Serum or Plasma”, whereas for test 2,
                    the LOINC code is for a “Glucose [Mass/volume] in Blood”. Different tests were
                    conducted and therefore different LOINC codes were used in the HL7 v2 messages.
                    The local laboratory information system and EHR also define and use their own
                    code systems to encode the tests; these are called “local codes.” Although not
                    universal, local codes are another way for health information systems to
                    represent <emphasis role="italic">meaning</emphasis> for clinical concepts. The
                    HL7 v2 observation data in Figure 3 shows blue text representing a local code,
                    and the observation data denoted in red represents a corresponding LOINC code. </para>
                <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?><emphasis
                        role="bold">Figure 3: Erroneous LOINC
                    Mapping</emphasis><?oxy_custom_end?></para>
                <para>The figure shows how the same local code can be erroneously mapped to
                    different LOINC codes and transmitted in a Lab Result message. In this case
                    example we see the same laboratory conducting two distinct tests and encoding
                    each test with a different LOIN1C code; however, both are mapped to the same
                    local code. This mock scenario highlights one example of the myriad of
                    interoperability challenges faced in healthcare today. [26] Successful
                    interoperability is dependent on either using universal code systems for data
                    capture or through mapping local content to a universal code system. Local code
                    systems serve the same function as universal coding systems such as SNOMED CT
                    and LOINC, however are internal identification schemas that consist of a set of
                    local codes and their associated definitions. </para>
                <para>Because the receiving system will parse the identical local codes from the two
                    mock HL7 v2 segments above, it will interpret the lab result as having been
                    produced from identical lab tests. In simpler terms, the receiving system will
                    interpret these messages as the same glucose test with a “count of 2
                    observations” rather than two different glucose tests, each with a “count of 1
                    observation.” Since the source specimen and lab tests are different, but
                    represented identically in the data transmission, semantic meaning is lost
                    compromising patient safety and accurate reporting. The receiving system will
                    interpret these two HL7 v2 segments as meaning the “same thing” or representing
                    the “same glucose test”; however, any terminologist or laboratory professional
                    would interpret this as “different glucose tests.”</para>
                <para>To improve the quality and safety of patient care, there is a need to refine
                    data exchange within the healthcare ecosystem. We often hear comments like, “Why
                    is the problem of data exchange in healthcare so difficult? After all, other
                    industries—banking, for example— have solved the problem. Healthcare
                    transactions can’t be that much more complicated than those managed by a
                    geographically distributed, multiple line-of-business banking system.”</para>
                <para>While other industries, like banking, have resolved issues with their
                    transmission and exchange of complex banking data across geographical locations
                    and between numerous unaffiliated businesses, the complexity with healthcare
                    data arises, in part, because neither the standards for structure (i.e.,
                    statement model) nor standards for meaning (i.e., terminology model) can
                    represent clinical data alone in the current data structures. Both types of
                    models can be arbitrarily complex, and, at some point, semantics not represented
                    in one must be represented in the other if one is to achieve interoperability.
                    [9]</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Spackman K, Guillermo R. Examining SNOMED from the perspective of formal
                        ontological principles: Some preliminary analysis and observations. KR-MED
                        2004 Proceedings 2004; 72-80. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Campbell KE. Distributed development of a logic based controlled medical
                        Terminology. PhD Dissertation, Stanford University, June 1997. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Analysis Normal Form Informative Ballot. HL7 CIMI Work Group. Sept 2019.
                        http://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/public/ballots/2019SEP/downloads/HL7_CIMI_LM_ANF_R1_I1_2019SEP.pdf.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>What is Health IT? [Internet]. HealthIT.gov. [cited 2023Jan13]. Available
                        from: <link xlink:href="https://www.healthit.gov/faq/what-health-it"
                            >https://www.healthit.gov/faq/what-health-it. </link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Net Health. The History of Electronic Health Records (ehrs) - updated
                        [Internet]. Net Health. 2022 [cited 2023Jan13]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.nethealth.com/the-history%20of-electronic-health-records-ehrs/"
                            >https://www.nethealth.com/the-history
                            of-electronic-health-records-ehrs/.</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>McMains V. Johns Hopkins study suggests medical errors are third-leading
                        cause of death in U.S. [Internet]. The Hub. 2016 [cited 2023Jan13].
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://hub.jhu.edu/2016/05/03/medical-errors-third-leading-cause-of-death"
                            >https://hub.jhu.edu/2016/05/03/medical-errors-third-leading-cause-of-death/.
                        </link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>McGinley P. Malpractice claims analysis confirms risks in ehrs [Internet].
                        Patient Safety &amp; Quality Healthcare. 2014 [cited 2023Jan13]. Available
                        from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.psqh.com/analysis/malpractice-claims-analysis-confirms-risks-in-ehrs/"
                            >https://www.psqh.com/analysis/malpractice-claims-analysis-confirms-risks-in-ehrs/.</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Shortliffe EH, Cimino JJ, editors. Biomedical Informatics: Computer
                        Applications in Health Care and Biomedicine. 5th ed. Cham, Switzerland:
                        Springer Nature; 2021.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>How Doctors Feel about Electronic Health Records [presentation]. Stanford
                        Medicine. National Physician Poll by The Harris Poll. [cited
                        2023Jan13].</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kahn MG, Brown JS, Chun AT, Davidson BN, Meeker D, Ryan PB, et al.
                        Transparent reporting of data quality in Distributed Data Networks. eGEMs
                        (Generating Evidence &amp; Methods to improve patient outcomes) [Internet].
                        2015;3(1):7. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4434997/"
                            >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4434997/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kahn MG, Callahan TJ, Barnard J, Bauck AE, Brown J, Davidson BN, Estiri H,
                        Goerg C, Holve E, Johnson SG, Liaw ST, Hamilton-Lopez M, Meeker D, Ong TC,
                        Ryan P, Shang N, Weiskopf NG, Weng C, Zozus MN, Schilling L. A Harmonized
                        Data Quality Assessment Terminology and Framework for the Secondary Use of
                        Electronic Health Record Data. EGEMS (Wash DC). 2016 Sep 11;4(1):1244. doi:
                        10.13063/2327-9214.1244. PMID: 27713905; PMCID: PMC5051581.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cholan RA, Weiskopf NG, Rhoton DL, Colin NV, Ross RL, Marzullo MN,
                        Sachdeva B, Dorr DA. Specifications of Clinical Quality Measures and Value
                        Set Vocabularies Shift Over Time: A Study of Change through Implementation
                        Differences. <emphasis role="italic">AMIA Annu Symp Proc. 2018 Apr
                            16;2017:575-584. PMID: 29854122; PMCID: PMC5977609. </emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cholan RA, Weiskopf NG, Rhoton D, Sachdeva B, Colin NV, Martin SJ, Dorr
                        DA. From Concepts and Codes to Healthcare Quality Measurement: Understanding
                        Variations in Value Set Vocabularies for a Statin Therapy Clinical Quality
                        Measure. <emphasis role="italic">EGEMS (Wash DC). 2017 Sep 4;5(1):19. doi:
                            10.5334/egems.212. PMID: 29881739; PMCID: PMC5983064. </emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hemler JR, Hall JD, Cholan RA, Crabtree BF, Damschroder LJ, Solberg LI,
                        Ono SS, Cohen DJ. Practice Facilitator Strategies for Addressing Electronic
                        Health Record Data Challenges for Quality Improvement: EvidenceNOW.
                            <emphasis role="italic">J Am Board Fam Med. 2018 May-Jun;31(3):398-409.
                            doi: 10.3122/jabfm.2018.03.170274. PMID: 29743223; PMCID: PMC5972525.
                        </emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Colin NV, Cholan RA, Sachdeva B, Nealy BE, Parchman ML, Dorr DA.
                        Understanding the Impact of Variations in Measurement Period Reporting for
                        Electronic Clinical Quality Measures. EGEMS (Wash DC). 2018 Jul 19;6(1):17.
                        doi: 10.5334/egems.235. PMID: 30094289; PMCID: PMC6078150. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hogan WR, Wagner MM. Accuracy of data in computer-based patient records.
                            <emphasis role="italic">J Am Med Inform Assoc. 1997 Oct;4(5):342–55.
                        </emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Aronsky D, Haug PJ. Assessing the quality of clinical data in a
                        computer-based record for calculating the pneumonia severity index. J Am Med
                        Inform Assoc. 2000 Feb;7(1):55–65.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Arts D, de Keizer N, Scheffer G-J, de Jonge E. Quality of data collected
                        for severity of illness scores in the Dutch National Intensive Care
                        Evaluation (NICE) registry. Intensive Care Med. 2002 May;28(5):656–9.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Thiru K, Hassey A, Sullivan F. Systematic review of scope and quality of
                        electronic patient record data in primary care. BMJ. 2003 May
                        15;326(7398):1070. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hasan S, Padman R. Analyzing the effect of data quality on the accuracy of
                        clinical decision support systems: a computer simulation approach. AMIA Annu
                        Symp Proc. 2006:324–8. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cruz-Correia RJ, Rodrigues P, Freitas A, Almeida FC, Chen R, Costa-Pereira
                        A. Data quality and integration issues in electronic health records. In:
                        Hristidis V, editor. Information discovery on electronic health records.
                        Chapman and Hall/CRC; 2009:55–95. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Botsis T, Hartvigsen G, Chen F, Weng C. Secondary use of EHR: Data quality
                        issues and informatics opportunities. AMIA Summits on Translational Science
                        proceedings AMIA Summit on Translational Science. 2010;2010:1–5. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hripcsak G, Knirsch C, Zhou L, Wilcox A, Melton G. Bias associated with
                        mining electronic health records. J Biomed Discov Collab. 2011;6:48–52.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Brown JS, Kahn M, Toh S. Data quality assessment for comparative
                        effectiveness research in distributed data networks. Medical care.
                        2013;51:S22–S29. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Rusanov A, Weiskopf NG, Wang S, Weng C. Hidden in plain sight: bias
                        towards sick patients when sampling patients with sufficient electronic
                        health record data for research. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2014;14:51.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Health Level Seven international [Internet]. HL7 Standards Product Brief -
                        HL7 Version 2 Product Suite | HL7 International. [cited 2023Jan12].
                        Available from:
                        https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=185</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>

