<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Laboratory Data Touch Points, Methods, and Associated Risks </title>
    <section><title>Laboratory Data Accuracy and Transparency in the Laboratory</title>
        
            <para>Until the widespread adoption of the electronic health record (EHR),
                    laboratory test results were communicated by phone,fax, or paper. While clinical
                    laboratories adopted information and automation technologies to deliver test
                    results more efficiently to clinicians beginning in the 1970‘s, the model of
                    patient care remained a single institution-centric model. Most patients could be
                    expected to receive care from a single institution through long periods of their
                    life.</para>
                <para>Physical copies of laboratory results and notes moved with a patient between
            facilities if they required care from more than one institution. In the past decade, the
            electronic transfer of the patient’s history, diagnosis and laboratory results has never
            been technologically easier, but this process has been far from seamless and fraught
            with risk. Individual laboratories develop and select local test codes, tests names,
            normal range values, and formats of test results and associatedunits. While the lack of
            data standardization may work well in a single institution healthcare model and does not
            impact the daily operations of individual laboratories, it does pose a significant
            barrier when data are compared or aggregated across institutions and creates
            inefficiencies and ambiguity for secondary data users.</para>
        <para>Accurate mapping of local laboratory codes to standardized terminologies would enable
            semantic interoperability in data sharing and aggregation across systems for a variety
            of purposes. In the case of laboratory data, accuracy does not simply mean successfully
            transmitting the test and result value without error, it also means successfully
            transmittingthe data elements that allow for meaningful interpretation and use of the
            laboratory result. Laboratory test results require additional data elements besides the
            result (e.g., units of measure, reference range values, specimen type, methodology) to
            be correctly interpreted and to meet interoperability standards and requirements. In
            vitro diagnostic (IVD) vendor products’ analytical techniques, reagents, and equipment
            calibration vary between IVD platforms and testing kits. These methodological
            differences can produce significant variation in results for similar laboratory tests
            across different IVD vendor platforms. Data necessary (e.g., instrument and test kit
            information) to determine equivalence and interpret results originating from differing
            locations or performed on differing IVD platforms are currently not communicated to
            and/or are suppressed in the EHRs which can impact patient care and safety.</para>
                <para>The figure below illustrates the touch points outside of the laboratory that
            produce risk for data quality degradation. Accurate interpretation and equivalence
            determination of tests and a shared understanding of the laboratory data as it moves
            across the healthcare ecosystem requires a standardized digital representation of
            laboratory tests. Enhanced laboratory data accuracy holds the potential to improve
            patient care transfers, reduce redundant laboratory testing, implement automated
            clinical decision support, aid in the monitoring of infectious disease outbreaks, and
            accelerate translational research based on real-world evidence. To realize the full
            potential of interoperable laboratory data, we must abandon the single institution model
            of healthcare and evaluate laboratory data in its role in the healthcare ecosystem
            through the lens of systems safety. </para>
        <figure xml:id="LaboratoryDataTouchpointandWorkflow">
            <title>Laboratory Data Touchpoint and Workflow</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/Laboratory%20Data%20Touchpoints%20and%20Workflow.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Current Laboratory Data Transmission Methods</title>
        <section>
            <title>Fax and PDF</title>
            <para>Faxes and PDF represent modes of transmission of data that do not support
                interoperability because the data they convey are unstructured and uncoded. These
                are usually fax and PDFs of laboratory test reports and would be expected to include
                data elements required under the Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA)
                standards such as patient identification, laboratory where the test was performed,
                test report date, test performed, specimen source as appropriate, test result and
                applicable units of measure and interpretation, information regarding the condition
                and disposition of specimens not meeting the laboratories criteria for acceptability
                and reference intervals.</para></section>
            <section>
                <title>Manual Data Entry</title>
                <para>Manual data entry may occur in an attempt to convert non-interoperable data
                such as faxes and PDFs into an interoperable format in a receiver system. It may
                also be used to fulfill data reporting requirements through the use of specialized
                portals developed by public health agencies. The data degradation risks of manual
                entry include not only operator error in entering the data, but also that the
                metadata and coding associated with the original result in the sending system is
                lost. Standardized coding may occur as part of the record build for the manual entry
                test record in thereceiver system, however, the coding assigned by the receiver
                system may not match the intended meaning of the original code assigned by the
                performing laboratory.</para>
                </section>
            <section>
                <title>Flat File or Database Extract</title>
              
                <para>Flat file or database extractions may be used as a tool to fulfill the
                    requirement of transmitting data and associated metadata to public health
                    agencies, research organizations and quality organizations. The database
                    extracts usually require further manipulation by the sender in order to fulfill
                    requirements by the receiving organization. Standardized codesmay have to be
                    added to the data if they are not already coded in the LIS or EHR systems.
                    Additional contextual information such specimen or collection information may
                    also be required. Database extractions are useful for transmitting large amounts
                    of data, however, the curation of the data after the point of generation
                    introduces risk of data degradation as inaccurate information may be introduced
                    as part of the curation process.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Interface</title>
                <para>Currently, most interfaces used in healthcare function using HL7 messaging.
                They are utilized for a variety of purposes including the transmission of laboratory
                orders and results within and between systems. They can also be used for reporting
                results to public health agencies. The Laboratory Order Interface (LOI) and
                Laboratory Results Interface (LRI) HL7 Implementation Guides are applicable for
                laboratory test orders and results, respectively. The Electronic Laboratory
                Reporting (ELR) and Electronic Case Reporting (eCR) Implementation Guides apply to
                interfaces used for public health reporting.</para>
                <para>Unfortunately, very few laboratories have the resources necessary to implement
                more than a handful of interfaces with outside institutions, laboratories, and
                public health agencies due to the significant costs associated with current
                non-standardized interface requirements. These implementation costs cannot be
                recouped at scale and have driven the increasing popularity and dependency on
                HIEs.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    <section>
        <title>Laboratory Data Recipients</title>
       
            <section>
                <title>Internal Electronic Health Record Systems</title>
                <para>Internal EHR systems represent the digitized version of the patient’s chart
                within the same healthcare system as the performing laboratory. The Health
                Information Technology for Economic and Clinical Health (HITECH) Act adopted in 2009
                was designed to encourage healthcare providers to move away from paper charts and
                utilize electronic data recording and sharing technology such as EHR systems to
                improve clinical quality and care transparency. According to The Office of the
                National Coordinator for Health Information Technology (ONC), EHR adoption in U.S.
                hospitals has climbed from 72% to 96% over the past ten years. While some healthcare
                systems utilize an integrated laboratory information system (LIS) and EHR solution
                from a single vendor, many institutions have adopted a best-of-breed strategy with
                separate vendors for their LIS and EHR systems.</para>
                <para>Integrating LIS and EHR systems requires overcoming obstacles that pose a
                threat to laboratory data quality and accuracy. LIS and EHR systems may have
                disparate data formats and different technological stack and integration
                requirements. Third-party EHR and LIS systems can be integrated using a variety of
                methods including native HL7, FHIR APIs, EHR integration modules, or middleware.
                Just because LIS and EHR have been integrated does not guarantee that the capture
                and transmission of standardized data elements are necessarily seamless. Fields for
                certain standardized codes may exist in one system and not the other. For example,
                currently none of the major EHR products can capture and transmit instrument and
                test kit unique device identifiers, despite transmission of test methodology being
                essential for equivalence determination.</para>
                <para>The ONC’s Cures Act Final Rule (Cures Rule) adopted the United States Core
                Data for Interoperability (USCDI) as a new standard that is a required part of new
                health IT certification criteria for standardized application programming interface
                (API) for patient and population services. The USCDI comprises a core set of
                structured and unstructured data needed to support patient care and is intended to
                establish a consistent baseline of harmonized data elements that can be broadly
                reused across use cases. It is currently relatively rudimentary as it pertains to
                laboratory data and USCDI version 1, as the currently adopted version only includes
                tests and their values/results as required supported elements in the laboratory
                domain. Interfaces utilize HL7 messaging and the Laboratory Order Interface (LOI)
                and Laboratory Results Interface (LRI) are HL7 Implementation Guides for creating a
                HL7 Version 2.5.1 OML^O21 message for laboratory test orders and results,
                respectively. Data elements required under the Clinical Laboratory Improvement
                Amendments (CLIA) standards such as patient identification, laboratory where the
                test was performed, test report date, test performed, specimen source as
                appropriate, test result and applicable units of measure and interpretation,
                information regarding the condition and disposition of specimens not meeting the
                laboratories criteria for acceptability and reference intervals are required for
                internal EHR systems.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Provider Portal</title>
                <para>Some community providers ordering tests from a particular laboratory may have
                    not full access to the EHR of the healthcare system in which the laboratory
                    operates. The data in the provider portal may be coded with standardized data.
                    The provider may receive their results through a provider portal that allows for
                    ordering of tests and viewing and printing of results, but does not allow for
                    automated incorporation of the results into notes or decision support
                    algorithms. The format of the test report seen by the provider is dictated by
                    the required CLIA data elements in a test reportas discussed above. If the
                    provider sends testing to multiple referral laboratories, determining the
                    equivalence of similar tests may not be possible as units of measure may differ
                    across laboratories and methodology is not a required CLIA reporting
                    element.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Patient Portal</title>
                <para>Patients and their legal guardians are able to view their health information
                through patient portals established by healthcare institutions as extensions of the
                EHR. The information displayed in the patient portal is not necessarily inclusive of
                everything in their EHR. Congress prohibited “information blocking” under the 21st
                Century Cures Act in 2016. This theoretically allows patients access to everything
                in their patient record with very few exceptions, however, determining how to
                implement patient access to their health information and defining what constitutes
                information blocking was left to the discretion of the ONC. The ONC’s Cures Act
                Final Rule (Cures Rule) currently utilizes the data set defined in USCDI version 1
                as the set of components that must be shared with the patient if it is available.
                This currently includes only tests and values/results. Some of the data may be coded
                with standardized codes, but the USCDI standard rather than CLIA sets the required
                data elements under the Cures Rule.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>External Electronics Health Record Systems and Laboratory Information
                Systems</title>
                <para>Laboratorydata may need to be transmitted to an external LIS or EHR system.
                    This transmission may occur through a variety of modalities. Some laboratories
                    may perform testing for healthcare entities outside of their system. If the
                    volume of referral testing is enough to justify the cost, the laboratory and
                    external institution may choose to invest in a HL7 interface. Orders and results
                    can then be transmitted electronically between the performing laboratory and the
                    receiving institution. If the volume is insufficient to warrant investing in an
                    interface, the test reports are often delivered via fax or PDF. The required
                    data elements in the test report would fall under the purview of CLIA.</para>
                <para>In order for the data in the fax or PDF to be interoperable, the receiving
                    institution may have to manually enter the results as discrete data elements. In
                    this case, the original coding and metadata associated with the results in the
                    originating LIS system is lost and replaced by whatever coding is used as part
                    of the test record creation in the externalLIS or EHR. For interfaced data
                    transmission, the data integrity depends on the configuration of the interface
                    and on the functionality available in the LIS or EHR systems involved to
                    capture, transmit, and receive the standardized data elements.</para>
                <para>The Laboratory Order Interface (LOI) and Laboratory Results Interface (LRI)
                HL7 Implementation would apply for laboratory test orders and results, respectively.
                Some interfaces may be configured with translation tables that automaticallyswap out
                incoming LOINC® codes or SNOMED CT® codes that do not match what is in the receiving
                LIS or EHR system for given tests. This poses a risk in data quality as the code
                replacement may not match the intended meaning of the original code assigned by the
                performing laboratory.</para>
                <para>As discussed above, none of the major EHR vendors currently have fields to
                    support capturing or receiving the instrumentand test kit UDI. Determining test
                    equivalence and interpretation usually relies on units of measure and reference
                    range as specific platform and methodology information is usually not available
                    in either the report or associated metadata.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Health Information Exchanges</title>
                <para>Health Information Exchanges (HIEs) allow for the ability to move clinical
                information including laboratory data across different healthcare information
                systems within a region, community, or customer base. Instead of having to establish
                individual interfaces with numerous other organizations, participants in the Health
                Information Network (HIN) are able to exchange healthcare data with all other
                participants. Individual HIEs do not necessarily support the same data elements and
                information may be lost as data is exchanged between the two. Even with participants
                of the same HIN, there may be enormous variation in what information is included
                when laboratory test data is exchanged. This is because there are no established
                guidelines on what data must be included with laboratory test results as HIEs fall
                outside of the purview of the CLIA required data elements and federal and state
                regulations regarding HIEs are still being defined.</para>
                <para>The Trusted Exchange Framework and Common Agreement (TEFCA) is an attempt by
                    the ONC to establish a universalfloor for interoperability. The goal of TEFCA is
                    to establish the infrastructure model and governing approach for users in
                    different HINs to securely share basic clinical information with each other,
                    with commonly agreed-to expectations and rules, regardless of which network they
                    participate in. Although TEFCA is a step toward more standardization of data
                    exchange for HIEs, no framework for the standardization of laboratory data as
                    part of TEFCA has yet been formulated.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Public Health Agencies</title>
                <para>Laboratories are required to report tests results pertaining to a variety of
                diseases considered to be of great public health importance to public health
                agencies and registries. The requirements for reporting, including the method of
                reporting and what information must be included, varies from jurisdiction to
                jurisdiction and is sometimes set by statute. Reporting takes many forms, ranging
                from PDF and faxes of individual patient reports to interfaced reporting and flat
                file extracts.</para>
                <para>As discussed above, PDF and fax copies of result reports must contain CLIA
                    required data elements and require additional manipulation by the receiver to be
                    interoperable. Some jurisdictions receive result reporting through manual entry
                    of results through a portal. This may introduce risk of data degradation through
                    manual entry error, but has the benefit of making the data interoperable for the
                    public health agency once it has been entered by either the laboratory
                    orhospital personnel. Flat file/database extractions may occur from either the
                    LIS or EHR database systems. The data components reported as part of the extract
                    depends on the configuration of the report to meet requirements. For
                    laboratories serving a large catchment area, different report parameters may
                    need to be developed to satisfy the requirements of different jurisdictions.
                    Interfaced reporting occurs through HL7 messaging and are subject to the
                    Electronic Laboratory Reporting (ELR) and Electronic Case Reporting (eCR)
                    Implementation Guides along with more specific requirements of the individual
                    requirements.</para>
                <para>The COVID-19 Pandemic Response, Laboratory Data Reporting Memo issued by the
                    Department of Health &amp; Human Services released on June 4, 2020, was the
                    first time laboratories had been asked to provide LOINC® and SNOMED CT codes
                    associated with their testing along with instrument and kit information. This
                    highlighted the importance of this information for interpretation of results and
                    identifying disease trends and tracking disease outbreaks, but also highlighted
                    the lack of current functionality to capture, track, and transmit these data
                    elements.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Research Organizations</title>
                <para>Laboratories may submit laboratory data to research organizations either as a
                voluntary member of a research consortium such as PCORnet® or as a requirement of
                being a study site in a clinical trial. The data must first be extracted as a flat
                file/data base extraction. The flat file/database extraction is seldom sent without
                some manipulation by the sender. The FDA requires data from regulated research to
                include standardized coding with laboratory data such as LOINC® codes. Although some
                organizations may have already coded their test menu with the appropriate codes,
                many sites have to add the LOINC® codes after the extraction. This introduces risk
                of error as it occurs after the point of generation of the data.</para>
                <para>In addition, additional metadata such as the clinical setting from which the
                    testing was derived may also be added to theoriginal extracted data to fulfill
                    the particular requirements of a given study. Manual curation of laboratory data
                    has been cited as one of the reasons laboratory data is so difficult and
                    expensive to use as real-world evidence due to insufficient coding necessary to
                    determine equivalence and appropriate interpretation.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Quality Organizations</title>
                <para>Laboratories enrolled in proficiency testing (PT) programs as a requirement of
                CLIA may choose direct transmission of their proficiency testing results to PT
                vendors to decrease the burden of manual data entry on their personnel. The data
                requirements of a PT vendor are similar to what would be required to determine test
                equivalence and correct interpretation. The vendor must be able to determine what
                test was performed, what unit of measure was used and what platform and kit the test
                was performed on in order to grade the participant against their appropriate peer
                group. The barriers PT vendors face in trying to automate PT data transmission are
                therefore similar to those facing a laboratory director in trying to determine
                whether or not external laboratory derived values should be allowed to trend on the
                same line as local laboratory values. Local test names and local codes are
                impractical to use as they vary from laboratory to laboratory. LOINC® codes alone
                are not sufficient to determine equivalence due to the many tests to one LOINC®
                mapping that occurs because of the unique features of the ontology.</para>
                <para>As discussed previously, methodology information, including instrument and
                    test kit information, is not currently captured and available for transmission
                    for any of the major LIS and EHR vendors. The method and platform information
                    must be obtained separately from the direct transmission process and paired with
                    the proficiency testing result to allow for appropriate grading of the result.
                    This is a cumbersome workaround and prone to error. In addition, themethodology
                    information is not available to be transmitted to patient results to allow for
                    accurate interpretation and equivalence determination.</para>
                <para>Integrating the Healthcare Enterprise (IHE) is working with stakeholders to
                develop a profile for laboratory proficiency testing that would provide a
                standards-based framework for sharing methodology information for PT purposes. The
                proficiency testing IHE profile is being proposed as the data requirements for PT
                are not currently covered by any existing stand</para>
            </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
