<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Open-Source</title>
    <section>
        <title>How to Contribute</title>
        <para>For community members and users who would like to collaborate and contribute, please
            visit the 'Community' tab on the<emphasis>
                <link xlink:href="https://www.ikm.dev/">IMK.dev</link></emphasis> website or go
            directly by typing <emphasis>ikm.dev/community</emphasis>. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What is Open-Source?</title>
        <para>Open-source software makes its source code, blueprints, documentation, and other
            products publicly available for users to modify, contribute to, and distribute.
            Open-source software uses a decentralized approach to software development that supports
            open collaboration, testing, and improvements from the community of users. In
            open-source, no one group is solely responsible for maintaining or improving software
            because peer-to-peer production of code and documentation is encouraged. While a
            governing body may exist in practice to maintain the software and ensure contributions
            meet community guidelines, they may not hold special rights to the software. Reasonable
            guidelines, such as extensive documentation procedures, enhance the benefits and trust
            in open-source solutions, while simultaneously preventing an “anything goes”
            mentality.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Why Does Open-Source Matter?</title>
        <para>The current restrictive and proprietary nature of software licensing within the
            healthcare ecosystem significantly hinders interoperability, particularly by preventing
            or restricting community engagement and contributions that could improve the software or
            code to meet emerging needs. To achieve lossless data exchanges between and within
            systems, the Health Information Technology (HIT) community must consider open-source
            software and open-source licensing models.While these licenses enable use, regardless of
            intent, and the ability to modify, adapt, and extend software with minimal restrictions,
            they also establish rules of the road and codify best practices to ensure adoptability
            and ease of use for both the initial user and the broader downstream community.
            Open-source licensing will support the public-private consortium needed to address gaps
            created by varying rates of adoption and implementation of proprietary software.</para>
        <para>Due to the decentralization and wide-spread availability of open-source software,
            errors and bugs are found much quicker because the code is utilized in a variety of
            contexts and stretched much farther. Instead of a single development team being tasked
            with identifying and repairing errors, users can serve as developers and contribute to
            addressing errors much faster. As a result, open-source software employs a high degree
            of modularity where it can be adaptive and flexible to the diverse needs of its
            users.</para>
        <para>Allowing for open licensing encourages improvements to terminology and standards by
            ancillary bodies. The open licensing also creates a more robust and flexible system that
            can adapt to the varying needs of organizations.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Preference for Open-Source</title>
        <para>Open-source software is preferred and is managed through open-source licensing. A
            permissive license will provide source code to users, carries minimal restriction over
            adaption, modification, and distribution of intellectual property of organizations, and
            allows the issuing body to impose some restrictions, such as monetization. However, the
            permissive license does not exert special rights to derivative works. Permissive
            licensing throughout the foundational architecture, terminology knowledge, and statement
            model layers removes barriers imposed on modifications and extensions and improves the
            compatibility of different terminologies to support a common understanding of knowledge. </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
