<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Patient Data Privacy</title>
    <section>
        <title>Important of Patient Data Privacy</title>
        <para>Patient data privacy refers to patients’ legal protection of their personal health
            information by healthcare providers. All healthcare professionals must protect the
            confidentiality and integrity of patients’ health information, while simultaneously
            providing patients access to their data, including medical histories, test results,
            treatments, and other personal information collected during patient interactions.
            Patient data privacy stems from the branch of medical ethics that focuses on
            doctor-patient confidentiality and is critical for building trust and ensuring patients
            feel confident disclosing important information about their health. As well as having
            access to their data, patients also have the right to correct any errors in their record
            and to allow others to access their health data. These rights are protected both by the
            medical code of ethics and the law, with violations leading to legal penalties. Several
            laws exist in the United States and abroad to advance patient data privacy, including
            the following: </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) (United States):
                    Protects the confidentiality, integrity, and accessibility of health
                    information. HIPAA provides patients with a legal right to access and receive
                    copies of their personal health data upon request and is broken down into
                    Privacy, Security, and Breach Notification Rules [1]:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Privacy Rule:</emphasis> The Privacy portion of
                            HIPAA dictates that health care providers and health plans must provide
                            access to protected health information (PHI) in “designated record
                            sets”. These record sets are maintained by the provider and contain all
                            information collected or stored by the healthcare entity, including
                            paper records, data in electronic systems, remote/archived information,
                            or data pertaining to where the PHI originated. It also ensures that
                            patients can access and edit their records if they find an error. [2]
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Security Rule:</emphasis> Healthcare providers
                            must enact safeguards to protect PHI and ensure that PHI data is not
                            improperly disclosed. Several measures including access control tools,
                            encryption, and audit trails are types of security measures that can be
                            built into systems containing PHI. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Breach Rule:</emphasis> Federal law requires
                            doctors, hospitals, and other health care providers to notify patients
                            and the Secretary of Health and Human Services if a breach of PHI
                            security occurs. If a breach affects more than 500 residents of a state
                            or jurisdiction, the health care provider must also notify prominent
                            media outlets serving the state or jurisdiction. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        
            <listitem>
                <para>21st Century Cures Act Information Blocking Rule: Prohibits health information
                    technology vendors from blocking exchange of health information or restricting
                    patient access to such information. The information blocking rule within this
                    act is of particular importance to patients because it includes provisions
                    ensuring that patients can electronically access all their electronic health
                    information (EHI), structured and/or unstructured, at no cost, and with the
                    application of their choice. Patients have the recourse to report information
                    blocking by healthcare systems and other vendors. [3-4] </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security Act: Advanced data privacy for
                    patients’ Substance Use Disorder (SUD) records and mandated that Health and
                    Human Services (HHS) issue guidance during the COVID-19 Pandemic regarding
                    sharing patients’ protected health information (PHI). [5] </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR): An EU policy that safeguards all
                    personal data including healthcare data. It grants patients’ rights over their
                    data and mandates healthcare organizations provide data protection measures.
                    This policy extends beyond the EU and protects EU citizens wherever they are
                    globally. [6-7] Several key principles outline the GDPR approach to data
                    protection: </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Lawfulness, fairness, and transparency </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Purpose limitation </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Data minimization </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Accuracy </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Storage limitation </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Integrity and confidentiality </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Patient Data Privacy and Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM)</title>
        <para>Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) does not handle or store individual patient records, and therefore does not
            directly have authority over the security or dissemination of these records. IKM is a
            contributed knowledge management application that will serve as a quality care driver to
            improve healthcare data quality and support the downstream accuracy of patient
            treatments and public health decisions. The contributed IKM application provides a space
            for healthcare knowledge to be managed in a single centralized area and improves
            clinical support systems to help healthcare providers. While IKM does not directly
            handle or store individual patient records, it plays a vital role in preserving the
            integrity and quality of healthcare data that are transferred within and between systems
            in the healthcare labyrinth. </para>
        <section>
            <title>HIPAA v. GDPR and Patient Data Privacy</title>
            <para>Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) is a law designed
                specifically to protect individuals’ medical information while General Data
                Protection Regulation (GDPR) is a broader regulation that encompasses protection of
                various types of personal data, including health data. However, both laws protect an
                individual’s right to the safe and secure handling of their personal information and
                are designed to protect an individual’s privacy. </para>
            <para>HIPAA rules only apply to covered entities including health care providers, health
                plans, and healthcare clearinghouses. Below are examples of each covered entity
                [8]:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Healthcare provider: doctors, clinics, chiropractors, nursing homes,
                        pharmacies</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Health plans: health insurance companies, HMOs, company health plans,
                        Medicare/Medicaid</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Healthcare clearinghouse: entities that process nonstandard health
                        information received from another entity into a standard. </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>GDPR rules apply to “Controllers” and “Processors”. Controllers are typically the
                same as HIPAA Covered Entities, and generally <emphasis role="italic"
                    >collect</emphasis> personal information, whereas a Processor is similar to the
                HIPAA business associate and usually <emphasis role="italic">processes</emphasis>
                personal information. Unlike HIPAA, GDPR has extraterritorial reach to locations
                outside of the EU where EU persons personal information is in use. </para>
            <para>Most relevant to IKM is the GDPR rules that extend extraterritorial reach to
                personal data “processors” in the United States when the controller is in the EU,
                and has heightened protections for data concerning health, genetics, or biometrics.
                US healthcare providers can satisfy the GDPR security requirements for electronic
                personal data by complying with the HIPAA Security Rule or by following the security
                framework of the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) (from which
                the HIPAA Security Rule is based). </para>
            <para>Although IKM does not qualify under HIPAA as a covered entity, nor under GDPR as a
                controller or processor, IKM values patient data privacy and upholds the highest
                security standards. [9]</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Understanding Different Entities and Their Roles in Patient Data Privacy </title>
        <para>Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms® (SNOMED CT®) and Logical
            Observation Identifiers Names and Codes® (LOINC®) are similar to IKM as they do not
            directly handle patient data nor collect any PHI. Below are SNOMED CT® and LOINC®’s
            commitment to data privacy:</para>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED CT®</title>
            <para>SNOMED CT®’s statement on data privacy [10]:</para>
            <para>SNOMED CT® itself doesn't directly handle patient data privacy. However, it
                contributes indirectly to patient data privacy by providing a standard language for
                clinical data. SNOMED International Services provides a detailed description of
                Personal Data processed for the purposes of Analytics, Contacting the User, Hosting
                and other uses. The privacy policy also provides details of an individual’s rights
                to their data and how to access and control personal information, and even includes
                a point of contact for questions specifically concerning privacy. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>LOINC®</title>
            <para>As LOINC's privacy policy states, LOINC does not collect any personal health
                information. LOINC® is a catalog of measurements that includes laboratory tests and
                clinical measures, that are not limited to vital signs and anthropometric measures,
                and standardized survey instruments. LOINC® also contains codes for the collection
                types for these items, such as panels, forms, and documents. [11]</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>Patient data privacy is an important aspect of delivering safe and effective
            healthcare and is protected by HIPAA and other laws. The EU’s General Data Privacy
            regulation ushered in an era of stringent and protective data privacy standards and have
            even influenced new policies, such as the California Consumer Privacy Act (CCPA). [12]
            As we navigate the complexities of data privacy regulations, our team remain committed
            to protecting patient data and patient privacy. Though not directly governed by HIPAA or
            GDPR, we believe patient data privacy should remain at the forefront of our operations,
            reinforcing our commitment to quality healthcare.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>HIPAA Guide. HIPAA Updates [Internet]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.hipaaguide.net/hipaa-updates/"
                            >https://www.hipaaguide.net/hipaa-updates/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Department of Health &amp; Human Services. Privacy, Security, and
                        Electronic Health Records [Internet]. Washington (DC): HHS;. Available from:
                            <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/for-professionals/privacy/index.html"
                            >https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/for-professionals/privacy/index.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>21st Century Cures Act Information Blocking Rule" [Internet]. Available
                        from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://oig.hhs.gov/reports-and-publications/featured-topics/information-blocking/"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology
                        (ONC). Information Blocking [Internet]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.healthit.gov/topic/information-blocking"
                            >https://www.healthit.gov/topic/information-blocking</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Congress. Care Act [Internet]. Washington, DC: Congress; 2020. Available
                        from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/748"
                            >https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/748</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>GDPR.eu. General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) [Internet]. Available
                        from: <link xlink:href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr"
                            >https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>GDPR Advisor. GDPR Compliance in the Healthcare Industry: Protecting
                        Patient Data [Internet]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.gdpr-advisor.com/gdpr-compliance-in-the-healthcare-industry-protecting-patient-data/"
                            >https://www.gdpr-advisor.com/gdpr-compliance-in-the-healthcare-industry-protecting-patient-data/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>U.S. Department of Health &amp; Human Services. Covered Entities and
                        Business Associates [Internet]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/for-professionals/covered-entities/index.html"
                            >https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/for-professionals/covered-entities/index.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The National Law Review. Does GDPR Regulate Clinical Care Delivery for US
                        Health Care Providers [Internet]. Available from:
                        https://www.natlawreview.com/article/does-gdpr-regulate-clinical-care-delivery-us-health-care-providers#:~:text=Unlike
                        the HIPAA Privacy Rule which makes obtaining,another lawful basis for
                        processing the Personal Data.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Iubenda. Privacy Policy [Internet]. Italy: iubenda; Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.iubenda.com/privacy-policy/46600952"
                            >https://www.iubenda.com/privacy-policy/46600952</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LOINC. Privacy Policy [Internet]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://loinc.org/privacy-policy/"
                            >https://loinc.org/privacy-policy/</link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Deloitte. CCPA Compliance and Readiness [Internet]. Available from:
                        https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/pages/advisory/articles/ccpa-compliance-readiness.html</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
