<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Summary of Findings – Current State of RWE Analytics</title>
    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>In an effort to resolve the challenges posed by data interoperability and unlock the
            full potential of RWD and RWE across the health care system, the SHIELD collaborative
            was formed. The SHIELD collaborative is a multi-agency/stakeholder public-private
            initiative to develop and implement collaborative policies and business models to
            overcome lab interoperability barriers. Due to the complexity and vastness of this
            issue, SHIELD has embraced an ecosystem perspective that recognizes no single entity has
            the authority or influence to meaningfully impact the state of lab interoperability.
            SHIELD stakeholders include in vitro diagnostic (IVD) manufacturers, commercial and
            clinical center laboratories, professional organizations, EHR vendors, Pew Charitable
            Trusts, numerous federal agencies, standards development organizations, and patient
            advocates. SHIELD’s overall objective is to ensure lab interoperability such that the
            same type of device is described the same way throughout EHRs. </para>
        <para>The purpose of this Summary of Findings – current state of RWE analytics including but
            not limited to information retrieval and Knowledge Management and discovery – is to
            explore the current state of real world data and real world evidence as it pertains to
            lab data interoperability, FDA market approval and post-market surveillance, public
            health, clinical care, and related areas. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <section>
            <title>Executive Summary</title>
            <para>RWD and RWE have received significant attention in recent years from the health
                care community and federal health organizations. The potential value of RWD which
                can include information from electronic health records, laboratory testing, pharmacy
                records, environmental testing, and patient self-reports offers the possibility to
                harness the day-to-day aspects of health care delivery and outcomes as a source of
                information and evidence (i.e., RWE) that is far broader than typical, “closed loop”
                clinical trial data sets. The applications of RWD and RWE, both in isolation and in
                conjunction with traditional clinical trial methodologies, represent immense
                potential in advancing medical research, developing and evaluating new therapies,
                assessing post-market safety and efficacy, improving patient care, expanding public
                health surveillance, and enabling effective pandemic response measures. </para>
            <para>Unfortunately, RWD and RWE face numerous obstacles that hinder their reliable
                widespread use. The realization of RWD’s full potential is faced with a variety of
                challenges, ranging from data quality and bias, lack of standardization, data access
                challenges, and privacy concerns. One of the most significant challenges is that of
                data interoperability. Data interoperability does not simply mean the ability to
                electronically share health information between and across health systems, this is
                relatively trivial, and is done routinely. Data interoperability implies that health
                data created in one environment can be “picked up and moved” to another environment
                and be computationally processed safely and reliably to convey exactly the same
                meaning as the source institution intended and computed. The movement of a Portable
                Document Format (PDF) medical report from institution A to institution B is done
                routinely, but none of the data held within the report is computable, thus not
                interoperable. Discrete EHR data can be computable within its source system but
                cannot be electronically exchanged to a second institution and reliably and safely
                computed to convey the exact same meaning as initially intended because these data,
                even data between identical EHR systems, do not carry sufficient context to convey
                appropriate meaning to be safely and reliably reconstructed between system
                instances. Finally, even data encoded using standardized medical terminology, such
                is laboratory data, that is electronically exchanged and computable between systems
                does not safely guarantee the data will be considered to have the exact same meaning
                between systems. Numerous examples of this phenomenon have been discussed in
                literature. [1] To realize the potential of RWD which is suitable as RWE for
                regulatory, research, public health and clinical care purposes, data
                interoperability must be achieved. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Real World Data (RWD) and Real World Evidence (RWE) Background</title>
        <para>RWD is defined as data relating to patient health status and/or the delivery of health
            care routine collected from a variety of sources as part of receiving care or daily
            living. It encompasses most sources of health data derived from common sources such as
            traditional clinical trial settings, including EHRs, claims and billing activities,
            disease registries, pharmacy records, as well as non-standard sources such as social
            media and wearable devices. [2] </para>
            <para>Large quantities of clinical data are generated throughout the various stages of
                an individual’s health care journey. When a patient visits a care provider, has
                their vitals recorded, reports their symptoms, undergoes laboratory tests, receives
                a prescription, and submits an insurance claim, valuable clinical data is created at
                each step. The data from each individual stage is stored in a variety of ways. Some
                data is discrete in nature, some is encoded, and still other data is recorded using
                natural language or text. In addition, data collected is contained within a siloed
                data ecosystem based on software system specific parameters that are different from
                other systems. Though information can be shared between entities to facilitate care
                from step to step, aggregation and standardization is difficult to reliably perform
                meaningful analytics without substantial data curation efforts. </para>
            <para>Similar to RWD, RWE is defined as clinical evidence about the usage and potential
                benefits, or risks of medical treatments, technology, drug, or intervention derived
                from sources other than clinical trials. [3] It refers to analysis of data that has
                been collected outside the traditional randomized clinical trial (RCT) setting. RWE
                has immense value in advancing medical research, particularly when deriving the
                required information in a clinical trial would be unfeasible or unethical. [4]. By
                design, RWD and RWE are generated independent of a specific research question or
                study design. This can be a benefit in some cases and a barrier in others.
                Independent of the research question(s) of interest, aggregating RWD across multiple
                sites is necessary to establish sufficient representation of the study and control
                cohorts is difficult based due to data interoperability barriers. </para>
       </section>
    <section>
        <title>RWD Applications and Limitations</title>
        <para>Despite significant challenges, RWD and RWE present immense untapped potential within
            public health, research, safety and regulation, and post-market surveillance. A variety
            of health care entities have taken interest in RWD in recent years, including federal
            agencies, pharmaceutical companies, medical device manufacturers, and patients. One of
            the primary applications of RWE thus far has been in post-market surveillance monitoring
            drug safety and efficacy as well as researching health outcomes that are difficult to
            study with traditional methods, such as with lesser understood conditions, smaller
            patient populations, and long follow-up periods. [4] However, during the SARS-CoV-2
            pandemic, RWD comprised the primary source of information available to the medical
            community to understand COVID, evaluate the safety and efficacy of IVD testing, antigen
            testing, and vaccination safety/efficacy. As an example, the State of Nebraska
            Department of Epidemiology and the Nebraska Public Health Laboratory operated large
            numbers of specimen collection centers for COVID testing. Each patient was required to
            report symptom status for loss of smell or taste prior to testing by antigen or
            polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Analysis showed that the presence of one or both
            symptoms had a positive predictive value (PPV) of 80% for COVID. These RWD provided the
            RWE to support pool testing of specimens to conserve testing reagents during a period of
            severe test supply shortages. [5] </para>
        <para>The use of RWD that is of sufficient quality to be used as RWE for market approval,
            post-market surveillance of medicines, and in IVD presents a potentially rich
            environment and supplement to the current gold-standard controlled clinical trial
            methodologies. To this effect, Congress signed the 21st Century Cures Act (Cures Act)
            into law in 2016 to help accelerate the development of medical products and bring new
            innovations to patient populations. [2] The law intends to increase federal focus on
            evaluating RWD and RWE for regulatory decision making for new approvals, support
            post-approval study requirements, and evaluate additional indications for approved
            treatments. [2] Unfortunately, the broad readiness of the U.S. healthcare ecosystem was
            not, and is not, in place to broadly harness and safely and effectively use the data in
            the U.S. healthcare domain as captured in the EHR systems, public health agencies,
            administrative systems, and potentially patient reported information. Such a gap in
            surveillance, data capture, data exchange, data harmonization and subsequent analytics
            place the U.S. at risk to repeat the “data scramble” in the event of another emerging
            disease, as experienced during COVID. Despite existing issues with widescale use of RWD,
            there are multiple examples of where and how RWD is being used effectively from which
            future direction can be informed. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Current RWD Uses</title>
            <para>There are several national and international efforts to aggregate and expose
                EHR/RWD for use by researchers and public health scientists. Such efforts include
                the National Patient-Centered Clinical Research Network (PCORnet), Observational
                Health Data Sciences and Informatics (OHDSI), National COVID Cohort Collaborative
                (N3C) and its potential spin offs. Common to each of these efforts is the extraction
                of EHR data from participating entities, transforming these data to a common data
                model, annotating/managing the data with standardized medical terminologies and
                aggregating entities’ datasets in consolidated or federated mechanisms for analyses. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>National Covid Cohort Collaborative (N3C)</title>
            <para>N3C is one of the largest collections of COVID-19 clinical data in the United
                States. The cloud-based collection of secure and de-identified data is part of the
                N3C’s vision to use RWD for advancing knowledge to address COVID-19. N3C aims to
                create a data pipeline to harmonize EHR into a common data model, allowing the
                research and clinical communities better access to reliable COVID-19 data to
                generate novel approaches to address the impact of COVID-19 and mitigate future
                pandemics. </para>
            <para>The National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS) N3C Data Enclave
                contains RWD as collected in contributing sites’ EHR systems on COVID-19 positive
                patients and patients with symptoms consistent with COVID-19, Severe acute
                respiratory syndrome coronavirus 1 (SARS 1), Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS)
                and H1N1 flu (a.k.a. Swine flu). De-identified data is contributed monthly and is
                augmented by public health laboratory data and whole genome sequence data of paired
                patient/specimen isolates. </para>
            <para>NCATS N3C Data Enclave data sets are well described and include data levels
                ranging from Limited Data Sets, De-identified Data Sets, and Synthetic Data sets all
                with in depth descriptions of the data and eligibility and access requirements.
                NCATS guarantees the confidentiality and security of all data in the enclave, and
                oversight is achieved through user registration, federated login, data use
                agreements and requests. The cloud-based environment is Federal Risk and
                Authorization Management Program (FedRAMP) certified. To further protect the
                security of the enclave, downloading data is impermissible and all work must be done
                within the enclave. </para>
            <para>N3C has paved the way as a successful model for other data enclaves. Data
                codification is well described, and the data harmonization team ingests limited data
                sets and transforms them according to a harmonized Observational Medical Outcomes
                Partnership (OMOP) analytics data set. Data and code provenance are tracked through
                the platform. Privacy Preserving Record Linkage (PPRL) is used to securely connect
                records while maintaining the anonymity of an individual across multiple records and
                may enhance COVID-19 RWD research in N3C through de-duplication of patient records,
                linking patient records from different sources, and cohort discovery. Organizations
                submitting data must have an approved Data Transfer Agreement (DTA), and an optional
                Linkage Honest Broker Agreement (LHBA), through which organizations maintain control
                over their data. Data analyses must be performed within the platform and is
                supported through R, Python, and Slate. R packages include SciPy and scikit-learn
                and are pre-installed, and others can be added by contacting the data enclave
                support team. Overall, the enclave provides a secure and focused space for research
                collaboration and has proven its impact through hundreds of peer reviewed,
                scientific publications. </para>
            <para>The successes of the N3C data enclave are not without limitations. Data sets are
                geographically limited to the U.S., and only patients with known COVID-19 positive
                tests are included. This may preclude large populations of patients with alternative
                methods of diagnosis from being included. Those whose results were not recorded in
                an EHR but were performed else where such as at a Public Health Lab (PHL), or who
                had viral sequencing performed are not included. Control cohort methods are not well
                described and thus there is lacking any RWD on non-covid patients. The strength of
                security does not come without some downsides and can limit the participation and
                quality of data contributed by participants. There is no method for testing for data
                equivalence between sites, and data is not in real-time or near real-time. The
                enclave would benefit from expanding its horizon beyond COVID-19 to other conditions
                and general disease surveillance. [6] </para>
    </section>
            <section>
                <title>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute (PCORI) and National Patient-Centered Clinical Research Network (PCORnet)</title>
                <para>The Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute (PCORI) is an independent,
                nonprofit, and leading funder of patient-centered comparative clinical effectiveness
                research in the United States. The primary goal of PCORI is to increases useful
                information, speed the uptake and use of information, and influence funded research
                to be more patient centered. PCORI funded research includes comparative clinical
                effectiveness research (CER) which helps patients and other stakeholders to compare
                two or more medical treatments, and other research that focuses on patient centered
                outcomes. PCORI funds researchers to share their data sets and documentation for
                reanalysis and reuse. PCORI encourages use of data from the studies and provides
                funds to allow other researchers to verify and build on those findings to generate
                new evidence and make this information available to healthcare decision makers.
                PCORI funded more than 2,000 research studies and related projects, including
                project that support the methods and capacity for conducting that research. [7]
                PCORI approved $1 million to fund the development of automated ways to identify
                people more efficiently and accurately identify people with rare diseases via EHRs,
                enabling treatments to start sooner and helping researchers offer individuals
                opportunities to participate in studies. [7]</para>
                <para>In 2013, PCORI funded development of the PCORnet, a national resource for
                health data and research expertise, with the goal of providing patient centered
                outcomes research in a timely manner. [8] PCORnet is a well established and fully
                integrated network with a research ecosystem uniquely networked to offer RWE
                essential to support major public health issues. [7] The Primary goal of PCORnet is
                to expand the role of patients and care providers in the research process and
                leverage EHR and registries to conduct research that is inexpensive, faster, and
                patient-centered in its design. [9] </para>
                <para>Data is accessible via the PCORnet distributed network drawn from millions of
                EHRs with growing links to patient-reported and payer data to create a standardized
                data set that facilitates large-scale research. These data are accessible via
                Clinical Research Networks (CRNs) and facilitated by a coordinating center. [10]
                PCORnet CRNs are integrated delivery systems with one or more hospitals, outpatient
                clinics (primary and specialty care), and emergency departments. Across the 9 CRNs,
                there are 251 institutions that are organized into 61 data contributors. A data
                contributor manages the PCORnet data mart for one or more institutions. Overall,
                PCORnet Clinical Research Networks currently include 337 hospitals, 169,695
                physicians, 3,564 primary care practices, 338 emergency departments, and 1,024
                community clinics serving medically underserved populations. These healthcare
                institutions and their clinicians serve as a diverse set of clinical trial sites for
                pragmatic research conducted in everyday clinical care settings. [8]</para>
                <para>In PCORnet, 66 million patients’ health records are available for
                observational studies and provide vast scale to power research for conditions
                affecting even small numbers of people. Data quality must pass rigorous standards
                that meet conformance, completeness, plausibility, and persistence criteria. Every
                network partner operates under the shared Common Data Model, which standardizes data
                points from across the network into a common data format on which users can query.
                Data security in ensured by not aggregating it all into a single data pool but
                keeping it protected behind network partner’s firewalls. Queries and responses are
                controlled through a secure Distributed Research Network Portal. Although the data
                is safe, a limitation of this approach is that queries are returned with answers,
                not data. Therefore, a researcher does not have access to the data. </para>
                <para>The scope of PCORnet-accessible data, plus its embedded expertise and patient
                insights, makes the Network a powerful tool for researchers. Studies supported by
                PCORnet infrastructure answer clinical questions that impact patients’ lives,
                including 2 recent studies that leverage PCORnet to study which populations are
                impacted by Long COVID and highlights PCORI-funded research results. [7, 11]</para> 
                </section>
        <section>
            <title>Observational Health Data Sciences and Informatics (OHDSI)</title>
            <para>Founded in 2014, the OHDSI is an interdisciplinary collaborative that aims to
                maximize value in health data through large-scale analytics and a common data model.
                The stated mission of OHDSI is “to improve health by empowering a community to
                collaboratively generate the evidence that promotes better health decisions and
                better care”. In terms of scale, the program consists of over 3,000 contributors
                (including universities, private companies, government agencies, and others) with
                data records that represent 810 million unique individuals. OHDSI works to the
                benefit of patients, providers, and researchers as well as larger organizations such
                as hospital systems and government agencies. The solutions and products that OHDSI
                develops are all open source. [12]</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Successes</emphasis></para>
            <para>OHDSI has made significant progress in the 8+ years since its founding, emerging
                from the legacy OMOP program. Among its largest accomplishments, the collaborative
                has pieced together a federated database with patient records amounting to about 12
                percent of the world’s population. From a publicity standpoint, OHDSI has been
                referenced by the European Medicines Agency and other policy makers as well as
                journals, including Journal of the American Medical Association (JAMA).</para>
            <para>OHDSI organizes into working groups and currently operates 27 of them, ranging in
                topic from focus regions (Asia-Pacific and Latin America regions) to specific care
                areas (oncology, psychiatry). In addition, they have working groups that focus on
                FHIR, the OMOP Common Data Model (CDM), and Natural Language Processing
                (NLP).</para>
            <para>In April 2022, OHDSI and SNOMED International formalized a five-year collaborative
                agreement in which OHDSI and the associated user communities will receive
                “comprehensive ontologies on specific healthcare domains and content such as
                devices, social determinants of health, disease severity scores and modifiers of
                cancers, as well as better concept definitions and resolutions of composite concepts
                in large-scale observational research.” While this is an enormous benefit to OHDSI,
                the benefit to SNOMED International manifests in the form of user data from
                interaction with their product. OHDSI also has an existing agreement with HL7 to
                integrate FHIR with the OMOP common data model in hopes of improving abilities to
                track and share data in the healthcare and research industries.</para>
            <para>OHDSI has ventured into product development, including the Health Analytics
                Data-to-Evidence Suite (HADES), which is a set of open-source R packages
                specifically focusing on population level estimations, patient-level prediction,
                cohort construction, and evidence quality. They have also created ATLAS, a web-based
                application that supports design and execution of observational analyses to generate
                RWE from patient level data. [13]</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Shortcomings</emphasis></para>
        <para>While OHDSI has demonstrated significant value, there are obstacles limiting its
                applications. OHDSI’s broad reach and many collaborative partnerships add value to
                the completeness and generalizability of information, the fact that the data is
                largely international complicates its use in federal regulatory applications.
                Similarly, the structure of multiple disparate contributors restrictions data
                flexibility and transparency. The data is fully and irreversibly de-identified,
                which can limit analyses that require more individual or time stamped data, as well
                as complicating retrospective quality control. The lack of transparency is
                exacerbated by the fluidity of medical terminology, as the rigidity of black-box
                data wrangling limit the agility required to respond to standard terminology
                changes.</para> 
            <para>One large consideration with OHDSI data is that of correlation versus causation.
                The nature of OHDSI’s data collection lends itself well towards evaluating trends,
                identifying associations, and investigating intersections of drugs, treatments, and
                diseases. While a number of variables for multiple associations can be examined, it
                is a significant challenge to assess potential causation from observed correlation.
                Data attributes that enable causation analysis, such as timestamping and
                longitudinality, are lacking with OHDSI. These limitations demonstrate common
                sacrifices that are often made when prioritizing data standardization and
                interoperability, especially when the privacy requirements of medical data require a
                base level of manipulation to obscure incoming data.</para>
    </section> 
        <section>
        <title>Electronic Medical Records and Genomics (eMERGE)</title>
        <para>The Electronic Medical Records and Genomics (eMERGE) Network is a National Human Genome 
            Research Institute (NHGRI) funded organization that combines genetic data with EHRs to 
            support genomic medicine research. Genetic data is collected and stored within biorepositories 
            at nine eMERGE sites, combined with EHRs, and then researched to determine how an 
            individual’s genetics increase their disease risk or make them better suited for specific 
            medications. Since its initiation in 2007, eMERGE has grown to develop 777 publications, 
            discover 68 phenotypes, and encompass over 136,000 network participants. [14]</para>
        <para>eMERGE conducts genome wide association studies (GWAS) with EHRs to sequence patients’ 
            genes, evaluate disease risk, return actionable results to clinicians and patients, and contribute 
            findings to patient EHRs. [15] One facet of the research is using broad GWAS results to calculate 
            disease risk in values known as polygenic risk scores (PRS). Additional work is performed to 
            compare International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision (ICD-9) codes across network 
            sites to assess comparability of large populations taken from different institutions, evaluate 
            privacy concerns surrounding patient consent and continuing genomic research, and identify 
            optimal methods for the development and cross-site deployment of algorithms to identify case 
            and control cohorts. [6] The overall goals of eMERGE, in addition to advancing research 
            regarding genetic disease and treatment associations, are to develop analytical tools, identify 
            and communicate genomic research best practices, and return genomic results to patients and 
            practitioners to improve clinical care. [14]</para>
        <para>Since its inception, eMERGE has provided valuable insights into both genomics research
                and methodologies to effectively analyze data across various institutions. Early
                into eMERGE’s work, investigators found projects had better outcomes when performed
                across the entire network versus within individual sites. Phenotype algorithms were
                typically developed within one site and then deployed at secondary sites where
                observed issues could guide iterative revisions to make the algorithm more robust
                and generalizable. Moreover, incorporating multiple networks allowed for larger
                population sizes and added statistical power. For example, eMERGE’s expansion to
                include pediatric sites in addition to the existing adult data was challenging but
                enabled researchers to examine heritable diseases that presented in childhood and
                continued into adulthood. This type of analysis would have been unfeasible for one
                site alone. [16] Data quality is of paramount importance when collaborating across
                multiple sites. eMERGE has demonstrated effective quality assurance procedures by
                ensuring common definitions and coding exists for phenotype variables being
                deposited into the database of Genotypes and Phenotypes (dpGaP) and facilitating
                Quality Assurance/Quality Control (QA/QC) of data as it comes in. [17]</para>
        <para>Similarly, the size, scope, and diversity of eMERGE’s data allows the network to develop and 
            execute additional analyses as data evolves and medical interpretations change. Cultivating a 
            diverse biobank and a rich EHR linkage allows for cost-effective longitudinal genomic studies. 
            Moreover, the continued collection of clinical data enriches the depth and value of the network 
            while incurring minimal added costs. [16] The ability to build upon existing data is particularly 
            valuable in fields where scientific understanding is still evolving, as with genomics and novel 
            diseases or treatments. Despite the challenges inherent with multi-site collaboration, eMERGE 
            12
            has demonstrated that interoperability risk can be mitigated to allow for robust and powerful 
            analytics.</para>
        <para>Despite its many successes, the eMERGE network experienced several challenges. The
                personal nature of genetic data emphasizes the requirements for patient privacy and
                de-identification. When aggregating data across various timepoints and institutions,
                there may be additional timepoints where privacy can be compromised. As such, proper
                de-identification must be prioritized at each phase of data collection. Also
                inherent to genetic data is the issue of patient consent. Within eMERGE’s
                ever-evolving network, ethical questions exist regarding whether an individual’s
                original consent allows for the sharing of data with database of Genotypes and
                Phenotypes (dpGaP) or expanding research to include additional phenotypes. [14] As
                data in consolidated systems grows, applications for its use evolve, and metadata
                analyses become possible, focus must remain on how to ethically honor patient
                consent as scope changes.</para>
        <para>One of the primary obstacles eMERGE experienced was that of data interoperability.
                While data was checked for quality and common data codes were established,
                limitations within the transferability of information persist. There is no guarantee
                of data completeness within EHRs, especially when care is received outside the
                primary provider’s system. Additionally, while nomenclatures and ontologies such as
                SNOMED-CT® and LOINC® exist to uniformly represent medical concepts, there are no
                established processes to facilitate the secure, generalizable, and interoperable
                data exchange required to provide continued care between different health care
                systems. [16] This issue is exacerbated by the ever-changing knowledge and medical
                interpretations surrounding genomic data as any interoperability solutions must
                remain flexible to keep up as the field evolves. eMERGE developed various practices
                to address these challenges and communicated findings to the larger genomic research
                community. However, a consensus on data standards and data harmonization, while
                laborious, is required to perform multi-site analytics effectively. [14]</para>
    </section>
        <section>
    <title>Sentinel</title>
    <para>The FDA launched the Sentinel Initiative to help develop new ways of evaluating the safety of 
        approved drugs, devices, and treatments in response to the FDA Amendments Act (FDAAA) of 
        2007 that mandated the use of EHR to perform safety assessments more effectively. [18]</para>
    <para>The primary goal of the Sentinel system is to inform FDA decision-making using RWE generated 
        from a distributed data network, a common data model, curated RWD, and flexible analytic 
        tools. [19]</para>
    <para>Sentinel collects EHRs that cover covers approximately 700 million person-years of longitudinal 
        observation time, much of which comes from insurance claims and pharmacy records. [17] It 
        pulls from a network of established data partners containing over 170 inpatient facilities and 
        some of the nation’s largest health insurance providers, including Aetna, Anthem, Humana, and 
        Kaiser Permanente. [18] The Sentinel System is not a data repository, but rather a distributed 
        network in which each data partner maintains ownership and operational control of their data. 
        In addition to the collected partner data, which is delivered quarterly or annually, Sentinel can
        access select full-text medical records, inpatient data, including lab results from the nation’s 
        largest hospital network that covers approximately five percent of inpatient care and over 10 
        billion pharmacy and medication encounters. [17]</para>
    <para>Data is transformed into the Sentinel Common Data Model (SCDM) format for standardization, 
        allowing for efficient analysis across data sources. Sentinel has developed a collection of flexible 
        computer programs to run routine queries and perform analyses that inform FDA decision making, ranging from medication utilization patterns among patient cohorts to evaluation of 
        drug and device safety. </para>
    <para>The Sentinel System presents significant potential with respect to the research, approval,
                and maintenance of medical treatments. The combination of expansive standardized
                data and flexible analytics allows the FDA to generate RWE and associated analytics
                rapidly and reliably with relative ease, all while minimizing risk to patient
                privacy. The capabilities of the Sentinel System are varied, including the ability
                to access full-text medical records, support RCTs, and streamline the collection of
                patient data from mobile devices. [17] This system has enhanced the FDA’s central
                purpose by allowing it to design and execute post-market studies that would have
                previously been required of medical product sponsors. [19] Similarly, the FDA
                maintains authority to mandate companies perform post-approval studies when
                potential safety concerns arise, and Sentinel could be used to drive those
                decisions. Sentinel’s Active Risk Identification and Analysis (ARIA) System
                evaluates the safety of approved medical devices and drugs and has performed
                hundreds of such analyses to date. [22] The operations of ARIA are of particular
                significance when considering the known limitations of the FDA’s Adverse Event
                Reporting System (FAERS), which the FDA itself estimates to have received only one
                to ten percent of adverse events that occur. [23]</para>
    <para>Although the Sentinel System has already provided measurable impact since its
                implementation, it has some desirable holes. The most notable one reveals the
                limitations inherent to the data sources Sentinel accesses. The majority of
                Sentinel’s data is derived from administrative claims data, which often lacks the
                precision and accuracy required to perform sound analytics on health outcomes.
                Claims data may diagnose and code conditions unreliably and often in an
                oversimplified manner, a complication that is further confounded by the
                prioritization of insurance coverage over medical precision. While a heart attack
                may be diagnosed and billed accurately, outcomes like psychiatric side effects,
                digestive problems, cognitive impairment, and countless others are often reflected
                unreliably or not at all. [17]</para>
    <para>The data within the Sentinel System exhibits additional flaws. There is a strong potential for 
        selection bias, leading to unknown generalizability to underrepresented populations, 
        particularly those lacking health insurance. Even among included individuals, data can vary. For 
        example, follow-up times within commercial health care plans are often shorter than those 
        within Medicare and Medicaid, making it difficult to perform parallel longitudinal studies. Data 
        is delivered to Sentinel quarterly or annually with a lag time of six to nine months, limiting its 
        usefulness when addressing rapidly developing situations like COVID-19. Finally, data
        consistency and interoperability are additional concerns, as data can vary in content,
        accessibility, and completeness across the multiple data partners. [17]</para>
    <para>There exist functional gaps that limit potential applications, but once improved, the Sentinel 
        System can further improve as a powerful centralized tool for RWE generation, regulation, 
        analytics, research, and patient care. As with all applications of RWD, strategies for how to best 
        capture, maintain, and analyze RWD and RWE must continue to develop and expand. </para>
            </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Learnings</title>
        <para>Electronic health records have been in use in the U.S. since the 1970’s. However, the
            rush to implement the EHR nationwide did not occur until the introduction of the
            Meaningful Use (MU) in 2009. [24] The EHR has provided a large pool of patient records
            and healthcare data from across the globe for secondary research. As of 2021, 85% of
            physicians in the US electronically recorded social determinants of health (SDOH) data
            and 97% electronically recorded broad determinants of health (BDOH) data. Rates of
            electronic recording of SDOH and BDOH data were slightly higher among primary care
            physicians, with 89% of primary care physicians electronically recording SDOH data and
            98% electronically recording BDOH data in 2021.</para>
       <para>In the past, research relied upon billing data from the UB-04 billing form as the
            source of structured data for research purposes. The UB-04 medical billing form is the
            standard claim form that healthcare organization use for the billing of inpatient or
            outpatient medical and mental health claims. [25-26] Although developed by CMS, the form
            has become the standard form used by all insurance carriers. This form captures all data
            in a structured format and captures diagnoses, treatments and procedures, type of
            admission, medications, and demographic information. While the UB-04 and similar
            administrative data have been considered rich sources of data for research and can be
            readily de-identified, shared, and stored, much valuable information is lost. Coding
            systems used for billing purposes dilute data by use of non-specific coding systems
            which bundle similar conditions or procedures under the same code. Diagnosis data is
            captured using ICD10CM codes which will bundle similar diagnoses under the same
            code.</para>
        <para>Limitations to using RWD cannot be overlooked, ignored, or dismissed. Aggregation of data 
            from multiple sources may impact the availability of data in real-time. Time and effort to clean 
            or harmonize data from multiple or disparate sources increases time between availability of 
            RWD for researchers compared to when the data was collected. This delay may impact the 
            accuracy or quality of research data, meaning researchers are analyzing data no longer true of a 
            given scenario. </para>
        <para>Patient reported data is information reported directly by patients to the healthcare providers or 
            researchers. Patient-reported data provides a rich source of data for researchers yet is 
            challenging to collect and share due to a lack of data standards. Data standardization is 
            challenged by the various sources of patient reported data from paper or digital surveys, EHR 
            portals, medical devices, or other sources.</para>
        <para>Ideally RWD for RWE is extracted directly from clinical documentation. EHR
            vendor-agnostic data and interoperability standards such as Health Information Exchanges
            (HIEs), MU, HL7, and FHIR were created to encourage or mandate data interoperability
            across healthcare organizations. Yet healthcare organizations continue to consider their
            healthcare data as a proprietary asset. Adding complexity to RWD is inconsistent and/or
            proprietary implementation health information technologies to meet the needs and
            requests of the healthcare organization. Data analysts or data wranglers are charged
            with making data understandable. Adding complexity to this challenge is inconsistent
            and/or proprietary implementation of each EHR implementation to meet the needs and
            requests of the healthcare organization. This inconsistent and/or proprietary database
            design and EHR implementation impacts query methodology for secondary use of clinical
            data across healthcare systems. Each EHR vendor database structure is different and
            proprietary. EHR vendors did not provide standardized terminology implementation
            support, resulting in overreliance on third party terminology vendors to provide the
            linkages between “provider-friendly” terminology and standardized clinical
            terminologies. These ‘provider friendly terms’ are often mapped to a broader than or
            inaccurate standardized language concept. Insight to the quality of these mappings is
            opaque and error prone.</para>
        <para>Clinical documentation by nursing or allied health professionals is rarely considered
            as a source of data for research. Yet, their documentation may yield a rich source for
            data. Additionally, their documentation is more likely to be captured in a structured
            manner in the form of structured (and often researched and validated) assessments and
            flowsheets. Ideally, RWD for RWE is extracted directly from clinical
            documentation.</para>
        <para>To address this issue, research databases were created to allow researchers access
            clinical data without actual access to the EHR. EHR database managers utilize “extract,
            transform, load” (ETL) to move data from EHR database(s) or other sources to a unified
            repository—typically a data warehouse. However, the ETL process relies on structured and
            standardized data. Much of the rich, useful data within a patient’s EMR is found beyond
            the reach of ETL. Narrative text with progress notes, diagnostic imaging and surgical
            reports, scanned pdf documents and free text fields contain a rich source of data to
            support RWE.</para>
        <para>Manual data curation and NLP are possible solutions to extract data from unstructured
            text. Manual data curation is a labor-intensive, time-consuming process involving human
            review of clinical documentation to read, interpret and extract information into a
            structured database. Well-defined heuristics and quality assurance processes are
            required to ensure accurate and consistent data extraction. Data available from data
            curation may not meet time-sensitive requirements due to the time and effort required
            for data extraction and any associated QA processes. NLP is a form of AI that can be
            used for computers to understand human generated language and process the data to
            understand the full meaning of the original intent. NLP combines algorithms with machine
            learning and models to correctly 16 extract and label data and assign meaning. Today,
            the most common models used to support NLP include convolutional neural networks (CNNs)
            and recurrent neural networks (RNNs). Yet, even the most well-defined data curation
            heuristics and processes may find clinician prose a challenge. Clinical findings with a
            diagnostic imaging or pathology report may not be expressed using explicit language. The
            actual clinical finding must be inferred from the clinical prose used by the provider in
            their report. Data curators or NLP may be challenged to interpret the actual clinical
            finding being described. Similarly, the presence or absence of a clinical finding may be
            hidden in the clinical prose as well.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Stram M, Gigliotti T, Hartman D, Pitkus A, Huff SM, Riben M, et al. Logical
                    Observation Identifiers Names and Codes for Laboratorians. Archives of Pathology
                    &amp; Laboratory Medicine. 2020 Feb;144(2):229–39.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Office of the Commissioner. Real-World Evidence [Internet]. U.S. Food and Drug
                    Administration. 2019. Available from:
                    https://www.fda.gov/science-research/science-and-research-special-topics/real-world-evidence</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. 21st Century Cures Act [Internet]. U.S.
                    Food and Drug Administration. 2016. Available from:
                    https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/selected-amendments-fdc-act/21st-century-cures-act</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Beaulieu‐Jones BK, Finlayson SG, Yuan W, Altman RB, Kohane IS, Prasad V, et
                    al. Examining the Use of Real‐World Evidence in the Regulatory Process. Clinical
                    Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics. 2019 Nov 14;107(4):843–52.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Abdalhamid B, Bilder CR, McCutchen EL, Hinrichs SH, Koepsell SA, Iwen PC.
                    Assessment of Specimen Pooling to Conserve SARS CoV-2 Testing Resources.
                    American Journal of Clinical Pathology. 2020 Apr 18;153(6):715–8.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>National Center for Advancing Translational Science. National COVID Cohort
                    Collaborative [Internet]. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. NCATS
                    2022. Available from: National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C) | National
                    Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (nih.gov)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute. Highlights of PCORI-Funded
                    Research Results [Internet]. PCORI 2022. Available from: Highlights of
                    PCORI-Funded Research Results | PCORI</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Forrest CB, McTigue KM, Hernandez AF, Cohen LW, Cruz H, Haynes K, et al.
                    PCORnet® 2020: current state, accomplishments, and future directions. Journal of
                    Clinical Epidemiology [Internet]. 2021 Jan [cited 2022 Dec 20];129:60–7.
                    Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7521354/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Timbie JW, Rudin RS, Towe VL, Chen EK, Hunter LE, Case SR, et al. National
                    Patient-Centered Clinical Research Network (PCORnet) Phase I: Final Evaluation
                    Report [Internet]. RAND Corporation About this book; 2015 [cited 2022 Dec 20].
                    Available from: https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7249/j.ctt19rmdhd.10</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Data [Internet]. The National Patient-Centered Clinical Research Network.
                    [cited 2022 Dec 20]. Available from: https://pcornet.org/data/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Home [Internet]. The National Patient-Centered Clinical Research Network.
                    Available from: https://pcornet.org/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Who We Are – OHDSI [Internet]. [cited 2022 Dec 20]. Available from:
                    https://ohdsi.org/who-we-are/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>OHDSI – Observational Health Data Sciences and Informatics [Internet]. [cited
                    2022 Dec 20]. Available from: https://www.ohdsi.org/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Welcome to eMerge [Internet]. [cited 2022 Dec 20]. Available from:
                    https://emerge-network.org/about-emerge/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Electronic Medical Records and Genomics (eMERGE) Network [Internet].
                    Genome.gov. [cited 2022 Dec 20]. Available from:
                    https://www.genome.gov/Funded-Programs-Projects/Electronic-Medical-Records-and-Genomics-Network-eMERGE#history</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Gottesman O, Kuivaniemi H, Tromp G, Faucett WA, Li R, Manolio TA, et al. The
                    Electronic Medical Records and Genomics (eMERGE) Network: past, present, and
                    future. Genetics in Medicine. 2013 Jun 6;15(10):761–71.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>McCarty CA, Chisholm RL, Chute CG, Kullo IJ, Jarvik GP, Larson EB, et al. The
                    eMERGE Network: A consortium of biorepositories linked to electronic medical
                    records data for conducting genomic studies. BMC Medical Genomics. 2011 Jan
                    26;4(1).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>About the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) Sentinel Initiative | Sentinel
                    Initiative [Internet]. www.sentinelinitiative.org. Available from:
                    https://www.sentinelinitiative.org/about</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Brown JS, Maro JC, Nguyen M, Ball R. Using and improving distributed data
                    networks to generate actionable evidence: the case of real-world outcomes in the
                    Food and Drug Administration’s Sentinel system. Journal of the American Medical
                    Informatics Association. 2020 Apr 11;27(5):793–7.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Adimadhyam S, Barreto EF, Cocoros NM, Toh S, Brown JS, Maro JC, et al.
                    Leveraging the Capabilities of the FDA’s Sentinel System To Improve Kidney Care.
                    Journal of the American Society of Nephrology. 2020 Oct
                    19;31(11):2506–16.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Findlay S. The FDA’s Sentinel Initiative [Internet]. Health Affairs. 2015
                    [cited 2022 Dec 20]. Available from:
                    https://www.healthaffairs.org/do/10.1377/hpb20150604.936915/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Drug Studies | Sentinel Initiative [Internet]. www.sentinelinitiative.org.
                    [cited 2022 Dec 20]. Available from:
                    https://www.sentinelinitiative.org/studies/drugs</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>World of Drug Safety Module [Internet]. World of Drug Safety Unit List:
                    Overview Of Drug Safety. [cited 2022Dec16]. Available from:
                    https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cderworld/index.cfm?action=drugsafety%3Amain&amp;unit=1&amp;lesson=1&amp;topic=8&amp;page=</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The American Recovery and Reinvestment Act, enacted in February 2009, includes
                    many measures to modernize our nation’s infrastructure, one of which is the
                    Health Information Technology for Economic and Clinical Health (HITECH) Act. The
                    HITECH Act supports the concept of meaningful use (MU)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>National Uniform Billing Committee Official Data Specifications Manual.
                    National Uniform Billing Committee (UBC) [Internet]. www.nubc.org. [cited 2022
                    Dec 20]. Available from: https://www.nubc.org/subscription-information.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Professional paper claim form (CMS-1500) | CMS [Internet]. www.cms.gov.
                    Available from:
                    https://www.cms.gov/Medicare/Billing/ElectronicBillingEDITrans/1500</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
        
