<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Summary of Findings – RWE Search and Query Methods</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Real World Evidence (RWE) Introduction</title>
        <para>Search and query methods are used for information retrieval to access unstructured
            data. Most health information is stored in an electronic health record (EHR), and most
            laboratory data are stored in a laboratory information system (LIS). It is important to
            understand how data is stored and retrieved from these sources, and how to aggregate
            this data from different sources. Information systems record and manage clinical
            statements using a variety of standard or ad-hoc models. However, reliable querying and
            information retrieval requires consistency not only at the format level (e.g., Clinical
            Document Architecture (CDA), FHIR, HL7 V2) but also the content model (i.e., the
            information model such as HL7 CIMI model, or Observational Medical Outcomes Partnership
            (OMOP)), and, finally, the semantic and terminology model. There is not only a potential
            for a lack of consistency with representing disparate health data with current data
            models efforts but also further variation in how the data are entered into information
            systems by end-users. These differences pose challenges for how the data are modeled and
            stored, thereby generating implications on data retrieval, data analysis, and accuracy
            of clinical analysis results. For these reasons, the ability to test for equivalence
            across multiple data points is important. A well-defined query that yields accurate
            results in one health system is not guaranteed to be successful in another system
            because of a difference in the underlying data models. If normalization can occur at the
            data level, time and resources can be saved through sharing queries across different
            systems to achieve data fluidity and the ability to build layers of data from different
            sources.</para>
        <para>Organizations like the National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C), Sentinel,
            Observational Health Data Sciences and Informatics (OHDSI) and others prove it is
            possible to develop, support and use real-world data (RWD) at “scale” across US and
            internationally in research, public health, and clinical quality improvement. However,
            the limitations highlighted provide the FDA the opportunity to address gaps commonly
            observed across efforts such as data quality and interoperability and access to timely
            data, while replicating the successes. </para>
        <para>A specific, yet generalizable, use case serves to elucidate the current FDA need for
            real-world evidence (RWE) analytics, identify gaps, and form the basis of requirements
            necessary to establish a health data ecosystem capable for widespread use in FDA
            regulatory efforts, public health surveillance, research, and care delivery. The long
            COVID use case, describes the need to broadly survey and analyze large data sets to
            identify and define poorly understood health conditions for which new and/or existing
            regulated technologies or substances can be evaluated for safety and efficacy. RWD needs
            to be collected, queried, and evaluated to test and validate the “hypothesis” of the
            regulatory exercise.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Long COVID Use Case: Loosely Defined and/or Poorly Understood Scenarios</title>
        <para>Long COVID is a poorly understood sequela to a COVID infection. In general, it is
            characterized by a wide range of ongoing health symptoms lasting weeks or months
            following a COVID infection, including fatigue, post-exertional malaise, fever,
            respiratory symptoms, neurological effects, and more. Even the CDC’s definition notes
            that the symptom list is not comprehensive and that post-COVID conditions may vary in
            symptom type, effect, and timespan, demonstrating how incomplete our medical
            understanding remains. [1] The NIH has stood up the Researching COVID to Enhance
            Recovery (RECOVER) Initiative, allocating $1.15 billion to better understand the
            development and symptoms of long COVID. [2] Similarly, the UK has invested over £50
            million into long COVID research initiatives. [3] Countless other countries and research
            institutions are doing the same as evidence mounts demonstrating the significant public
            health risk of this largely undefined condition.</para>
        <para>Our incomplete understanding of long COVID is akin to the HIV/AIDS epidemic of the
            1980s and 1990s where the differentiation between HIV and AIDS was not yet known. Only
            after substantial research was the distinction between HIV infection and AIDS understood
            and effective treatments and secondary preventative treatments developed. [4] Likewise,
            Alzheimer’s disease and related dementias (RD) were once considered syndromic; that is,
            poorly understood and only clinically characterized. After further research, we now
            recognize Alzheimer’s as a biologically diagnosed condition- a definitive diagnosis that
            is unfortunately only determined postmortem. [5]</para>
        <para>The use of RWD resources has shown promise for hard-to-diagnose conditions. For
            example, Rheumatoid Arthritis related interstitial lung disease (RA-ILD) is a difficult
            diagnosis often only diagnosed reliably by rheumatologists in conjunction with
            substantial diagnostic work-up. However, studies at the VA and UNMC PCORnet and VA
            datasets demonstrate that commonly discrete data elements in the EHR can be used to
            identify RA-ILD patients based on their data phenotype. With the addition of low-level,
            basic NLP for radiology report evaluations, high levels of PPV identification of RA-ILD
            patient by data phenotype is possible.</para>
        <para>To address the long COVID use case, the FDA must have access to substantial amounts of
            data for patients positively diagnosed for COVID, for patients who exhibit identified
            long COVID symptoms (with and without a positive COVID diagnosis), and patients who have
            had no known COVID infection(s) and do not exhibit long COVID symptoms. These data need
            to be complete and have all appropriate data elements coded with standard values to
            enable meaning to be determined across facilities. Complete, standardized patient data
            across time and facilities will allow researchers to access symptoms, existing
            morbidities, demographics (including weight and age), treatments taken (for COVID or
            other conditions), vaccinations received, screening and diagnostic test data, and
            potentially other information like drug use, alcohol use, and smoking. This will enable
            the use of statistical methods and advanced analytics to quickly determine the relevant
            data elements and values necessary to more accurately establish a clinical definition
            for diagnosing an emerging condition like long COVID, along with identifying risk
            factors for contracting it, and provide evidence to develop tests and drugs for
            confirming and treating the condition. </para>
        <para>In addition to “validated” data such as existing laboratory and other diagnostic test
            data, provider-level patient reports and physician interpretation data must be
            collected. Furthermore, patient-reported, non-physician translated data should be
            considered, collected, and incorporated with the more clinically oriented data. Existing
            RWD ecosystems could add value to long COVID research. For example, the Sentinel system,
            which collects large quantities of claims records, could assist in identifying patient
            cohorts or determining secondary variables that may indicate long COVID symptoms.
            However, the known limitations of systems like Sentinel must be considered, such as
            potential incompleteness, poor association to actual patient outcomes, or diagnosis
            oversimplification within billing applications. </para>
        <para>There are several conditions that must be considered to effectively address
            misunderstood conditions like long COVID with RWD. Though it may be incomplete, there
            needs to be a baseline description of the condition to identify variables and data
            sources of interest. This definition may be treated as fluid and updated as research
            progresses, so there must be adequate agility to evaluate, collect, and integrate new
            data elements inclusive of existing health care as well as novel observations. As with
            all varied data collections, an emphasis on standardization and normalization is key to
            achieve interoperability. In the capture process, non-discrete data will need to be
            harvested and converted to discrete data. Effective analysis will rely on the ability to
            query the data in multiple ways with multiple parameters, both within and across care
            sites.</para>
        <para>As long COVID continues to grow as a public health priority, a proactive RWD research
            approach could provide valuable insights into the condition that may be difficult to
            discern through other research methods. To effectively understand and treat long COVID
            and other poorly understood diseases, researchers must be able to differentiate case and
            control patients with high reliability to then test the efficacy and safety of new
            diagnostic and treatment options. RWD may have considerable potential in clearly
            identifying patient cohorts to advance understanding of the disease and develop
            effective treatments. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>CDC. Post-COVID Conditions [Internet]. Centers for Disease Control and
                    Prevention. 2022. Available from:
                    https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/long-term-effects/index.html#:~:text=People%20with%20post%2DCOVID%20conditions%20(or%20long%20COVID)%20may</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>NIH launches new initiative to study “Long COVID” [Internet]. National
                    Institutes of Health (NIH). 2021. Available from:
                    https://www.nih.gov/about-nih/who-we-are/nih-director/statements/nih-launches-new-initiative-study-long
                    COVID</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Researching long COVID | NIHR [Internet]. www.nihr.ac.uk. Available from:
                    https://www.nihr.ac.uk/covid-19/researching-the-long-term-impact.htm</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Deeks SG, Overbaugh J, Phillips A, Buchbinder S. HIV infection. Nature Reviews
                    Disease Primers. 2015 Oct 1;1(1).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Karantzoulis S, Galvin JE. Distinguishing Alzheimer’s disease from other major
                    forms of dementia. Expert review of neurotherapeutics [Internet].
                    2011;11(11):1579–91. Available from:
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22014137</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

