<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Summary of Findings – RWE Advanced Analytics Methodologies</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Real World Evidence Introduction</title>
        <para>Real world evidence (RWE) using data collected as part of routine clinical care, has
            been heralded as an answer to many of the woes of our medical system. A vision has been
            made popular that suggests a wealth of untapped data – electronic health records,
            medical imaging, mobile apps, and more recently low-cost gene sequencing and wearable
            devices, unlocked using artificial intelligence and cloud computing – is a path to
            better diagnostics, personalized treatments, and early disease prevention for millions.
            Data interoperability of health data may help medicine realize the future in the same
            way in which other industries have advanced – such as banking, the “internet of things”
            and online shopping. The vision of a national interoperable health information system
            has been elusive; however, because of clinical care data in data siloes, incompatible
            health information technology (IT) systems, and proprietary software that make health
            information difﬁcult to exchange, analyze, and interpret. </para>
        <para>Given the number of distinct information systems and care delivery organizations in
            the ecosystem (e.g., primary care, specialists, laboratories, other care teams), there
            is a lot of variation in how data is collected, manipulated, transmitted, and
            effectively used. The problem is not the systems per se, but rather the difficulty of
            data exchange between systems or data incompatibility. Medical data range in format from
            narrative, textual data to numerical measurements, recorded signals, photographs,
            drawings, and more. There is also the challenge of the volume of data recorded. Several
            different observations of a patient are often made concurrently, the observation of the
            same patient parameter made at several points in time, or both. [1] It is also important
            to keep a record of the circumstances under which data are obtained. For example, is a
            blood pressure reading taken on the arm or the leg, had the patient just exercised, what
            kind of device was used, etc. </para>
        <para>Representing these data in various, disparate information systems introduces
            additional opportunities for inefficiencies, redundancies, and inconsistencies. Each
            system has a proprietary, standard, or ad-hoc information model and is typically
            configured to satisfy organization-specific needs, resulting in differences in data
            capture and storage between and within systems. This is the current reality, as
            electronic health data are represented in unpredictable and denormalized forms. This
            reduces the quality of data processing and ability to conduct safe and reliable
            analytics. Numerous scholarly and practical efforts illustrate the challenges of using
            observational data for safe patient care, comparative effectiveness research, and
            analysis including recording biases, workflow differences, and issues with variations in
            data collection, such as invalid, inconsistent, and missing data. [2] </para>
        <para>The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has a need for aggregated RWE and reliable
            analytics and would benefit from implementable methodologies that address
            interoperability and data aggregation gaps to help establish a health data ecosystem
            capable for widespread use in FDA regulatory efforts, public health surveillance,
            research, and care delivery. To achieve safe and effective information retrieval and
            reproducible search and query practices across various settings, the following
            constructs are needed to successfully build, maintain, and analyze data/resources across
            key biomedical concepts of interest.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Data Interoperability Tooling</title>
        <para>A generalized definition of interoperable health data that supports reliable RWE
            analytics asserts that data recorded and encoded at the time of creation should
            accurately reflect the meaning intended by the health care professional who created the
            data. In the current ecosystem, it can be a very manual, error-prone, and sometimes
            impossible process to determine if data received from entity A is equivalent to data
            from entity B and if it is interpreted across each setting as the data was originally
            intended at the point of origin. Data interoperability tooling, such as a Knowledge
            Management Platform, that can ingest disparate health data and knowledge sources and
            harmonize them into a common model and change management system could help in ensuring
            that the data are reliably computed and/or transmitted between health information
            systems without any change in meaning. The original meaning as intended by the first
            entity should be fully communicated electronically and understood upon receipt equally
            by the receiving entity. This type of knowledge platform could serve as data
            interoperability tooling to be able to determine equivalence between concepts and data
            sets from various organizations. </para>
        <para>To facilitate such tooling, data much be represented by a normal form that can safely
            and reliably support data analysis that can be used to aggregate data creating using
            standard or non-standard input form or exchange mechanism. Examples of such data models
            include Health Level 7 (HL7) Clinical Information Modeling Initiative (CIMI) efforts,
            including the HL7 Analysis Normal Form (ANF) specification. The model to support a
            Knowledge Management Platform should meet the following evolutionary design criteria: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Understandable: The data model for normalizing disparate health data can be
                    processed by health IT systems and understood by most healthcare providers
                    without reference to private or inaccessible information.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Reproducible: Multiple users or systems apply the model and normal form to the
                    same situations and source data with an equivalent result.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Useful: The model is fit-for-purpose—it has practical value for data analysis,
                    in support of clinical decision support, research, and population health that
                    requires information aggregated across health IT systems.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Normalization of disparate health data and knowledge is defined as "the ability to
            identify every representational format that confers the same meaning as being equivalent
            (i.e., unambiguous representation)." [3] To be clear, the transformation/normalization
            would involve a data instance to data instance transformation. An example could be John
            Doe's Systolic Blood Pressure measurement taken on June 4, 2019 represented as a Fast
            Health Interoperability Resources (FHIR) Observation instance, which is then transformed
            to a common data model/normal form instance representing this same data. Transformation,
            in this case, is not a simple endeavor that one can hope to implement on clinical data.
            It will likely involve navigating disparate data structure trees and include variable
            representations to then generate a well-formed terminology expression. It is most likely
            possible to target sub-domains for consistent transformation, such as all quantitative
            laboratory results, but in some cases, it may be that each detailed clinical model needs
            its own unique transformation.</para>
        <para>Currently, there are three basic categories of errors that might be associated with
            attempts at normalizing clinical data representation:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Errors associated with normalization of content of the terminology</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Errors associated with normalization of the semantics of the
                    terminology</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Errors that result from ambiguous or misleading interaction between the
                    structured clinical input and presentation of compound terminology to clinician
                    end-users</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>A number of options exist for expressing transformation logic and for executing the
            transformation on specific instances of clinical data for normalization. These range
            from transformation languages to expensive middleware options commonly used in
            healthcare interfaces. The suitability of a chosen transformation language highly
            depends on the format of the source data, and the quality and accuracy of the
            transformation is left to the transformation author. Examples of transformation
            languages include eXtensible Stylesheet Language Transformations (XSLT), FHIR Mapping
            Language, and Query/View/Transformation (QVT). Often referred to as “data wrangling”
            these transformation processes often require mapping data from one “raw” data form into
            another format with the intent of making it more valuable for downstream purposes such
            as analytics.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Data Liquidity</title>
        <para>To support RWE analytics and data aggregation, there is a desire to “reduce the amount
            of data wrangling” and one-off transformations across the ecosystem and instead enable
            “data liquidity”, or the ability of data to flow throughout the health data ecosystem
            easily and securely so that it is quickly available to clinicians, decision makers,
            laboratories, patients, and others when where they need. A robust information
            architecture and scalable solution to enable this ideal state requires a common
            understanding of data and a method to support knowledge-representation and assertional
            and procedural rules based on common terminology and statement models. If a shareable
            architecture were able to be implemented across the ecosystem, health data and knowledge
            could potentially be represented in a way that is both applicable at the
            interoperability-enterprise and project-specific levels. </para>
        <para>Another pragmatic methodology would be to engage vendors and incentivize them to
            implement an open, common data model and produce shareable output in interoperable,
            reproducible, and understandable formats that could then be ingested by other systems.
            Major US electronic health records (EHR) vendors including Epic and Cerner which
            represent > 80% of the US healthcare EHR implementations represent a possible avenue to
            normalizing and aggregating EHR-based data in the US on a broad scale. Individually,
            each vendor has independently attempted to create such clinical data resources and
            product offerings for their user communities. These efforts entail attempts to align,
            normalize and aggregate the EHR data held by each individual client into a large,
            de-identified data enclave for purposes of data analytics, quality improvement and
            research. Unfortunately, these independent efforts are proprietary and do not extend
            beyond the vendor user community. Further, the data normalization and representation
            process remains "black box" and cannot be independently verified for semantic
            correctness, data and information loss or gains, or appropriate application of metadata
            standards. In fact, these vendor-centric face the same issues on a smaller scale as the
            FDA SHIELD effort. Issues with vendor-centric data alignment and reuse are known. [4-5]
            Despite these weaknesses, an opportunity exists to collaborate with EHR vendors to
            normalize and apply metadata standards safely and reliably to the EHR data created by
            their clients. To capitalize on this opportunity, vendors must be allowed to create
            unique value in their data offerings to the clientele but also be required to expose
            these data to the broader community such that data collected by numbers of vendors can
            be safely and reliably aggregated for research, public health, clinical quality
            improvement and regulatory uses as described by SHIELD.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Metadata</title>
        <para>An important construct for enabling RWE analytics, knowledge management, data
            integration, and decision support, is adoption and reproducible encoding of health data
            using biomedical terminologies. Acceleration and development of EHR systems has
            precipitated the emergence of “standard terminologies” and their widespread adoption in
            the health data community. These standard terminologies include Systematized
            Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT®), the Logical Observation
            Identifiers, Names, and Codes (LOINC®) and RxNorm. </para>
        <para>While these standards are widely implemented and adopted, aggregation and analytics
            can be difficult because there is no standard representation across these terminologies.
            Traversing the data models of these various terminology standards in an integrated way
            is non-trivial because SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm each use different formalisms and
            tools for their representation. Various terminologies have different semantics, models,
            release cycles, and versioning mechanisms. [6]</para>
        <para>Ideally, to support RWE analytics and aggregation, enterprise terminology requires an
            integrated terminology using a common representation (metadata) and management. A common
            terminology model, such as HL7 Standardized Terminology Knowledgebase (also known as
            Terminology Knowledge Architecture or Tinkar) would allow analytics on top of aggregated
            RWE data sets the following [7]:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ability to recognize equivalence between data from disparate health IT systems
                    that use codes/terms from various standard terminologies (e.g., “Feels Feverish”
                    in the Temperature Symptoms SNOMED CT hierarchy versus “Feels Hot/Feverish” in
                    the Observation and Sensation SNOMED CT hierarchy. Both concepts are Findings in
                    SNOMED CT but there is no unifying way to identify equivalence).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ability to represent local concepts using codes and terms that are modeled
                    extensions to standard terminologies (e.g., “COVID-19 negative test result” was
                    needed in practical use before official SDO releases, or gaps like “mild
                    anemia”, which was proposed, but not accepted, by both the international and
                    U.S. SNOMED CT release)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Identify flawed information or incorrect usage or representation of concepts
                    from standard terminologies due to a lack of harmonization and multiple
                    representations that exist across disparate standards (e.g., LOINC and SNOMED CT
                    have overlapping concepts)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ability to safely change over time in a clear way so that changes are easily
                    understood by implementers. (e.g., redundancy, major name)</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Analytic Environments</title>
        <para>Integrated analytics environments assist in creating and automating data pipelines and
            workflows to deliver actional information to a wide variety of end users. These
            environments extract data from various data sources, ideally into an integrated
            knowledge base, housed in a central ecosystem – thereby reducing data silos, enhancing
            security and governance, and eliminating system redundancies. For data analytics
            conducted using RWE, analytics environments used by FDA and others will be dependent on
            a variety of knowledge bases and datasets that may have some common fields but also
            differing fields. A vast variety of biomedical and administrative knowledge present the
            basis for RWE analytics and knowledge management of these disparate datasets is a major
            element of consideration to facilitate RWE analytics. Knowledge management includes the
            creation, discovery, and application of knowledge assets to facilitate sharing and
            re-use across the ecosystem. </para>
        <para>The ability to use interoperable syntax and semantics between data sources is a
            critical requirement to support effective knowledge management and reliable analytics of
            disparate RWE datasets. Use of industry standards for syntax and semantics helps
            facilitate integration; however, not all implementation considerations are planned for
            and adopted and additional efforts are needed to advance standards to improve data
            quality. The standards themselves update over time and there is a requirement for
            knowledge management in analytics environments to consider how standards and underlying
            code sets have changed over time and relaying these changes to data analysts and users
            who interpret data reports to best understand the information. </para>
        <para>The following are best practices for the establishment of the Laboratory
            Interoperability Data Repository taken from the SHIELD Community Roadmap:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>“Develop a freely accessible knowledge management architecture for
                    laboratorians, clinicians, researchers, and regulators, which is needed to
                    promote clinical interoperability, enabling the determination of equivalency
                    between different test results to decide whether they can be safely used for
                    trending, data aggregation, post-market efficacy studies, and research. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Determine the usefulness of clinical interventions to improve patient care,
                    based on relevant laboratory knowledge and reporting data, such as public health
                    reporting and clinical surveillance.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Harmonize meaningful laboratory terminology standards, such as SNOMED CT® and
                    LOINC®.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enhance the reproducibility of data exchange structures used to express
                    laboratory procedures and outcomes, such as Clinical Data Interchange Standards
                    Consortium (CDISC), FHIR, and Integrating the Healthcare Enterprise (IHE)
                    Laboratory Analytical Workflow (LAW).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Promote the understandability of the laboratory test knowledge as interpreted
                    and processed by supporting health IT systems such as Laboratory Information
                    Systems (LIS), Laboratory Information Management Systems (LIMS), and Electronic
                    Health Records (EHRs).”</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Establishment of this infrastructure will help facilitating reliable data governance
            and knowledge management that will assist understandable, reproducible, and useful RWE
            analytics. Widespread promotion across disparate health information systems will help
            reduce variation for large national analytic enclaves, such as the National COVID Cohort
            Collaborative (N3C) Data Enclave which aggregates and analyzes data from numerous,
            disparate electronic health record systems.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Shortliffe EH, Cimino JJ, editors. Biomedical Informatics: Computer
                    Applications in Health Care and Biomedicine. 5th ed. Cham, Switzerland: Springer
                    Nature; 2021.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Kahn MG, Brown JS, Chun AT, Davidson BN, Meeker D, Ryan PB, Schilling LM,
                    Weiskopf NG, Williams AE, Zozus MN. Transparent reporting of data quality in
                    distributed data networks. EGEMS (Wash DC). 2015 Mar 23;3(1):1052. doi:
                    10.13063/2327-9214.1052.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Elkin, P. Terminology and Terminological Systems. London: Springer; 2012.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Bernstam EV, Warner JL, Krauss JC, Ambinder E, Rubinstein WS, Komatsoulis G,
                    Miller RS, Chen JL. Quantitating and assessing interoperability between
                    electronic health records. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2022 Jan 7:ocab289. doi:
                    10.1093/jamia/ocab289. Epub ahead of print. PMID: 35015861.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wong A, Otles E, Donnelly JP, et al. External Validation of a Widely
                    Implemented Proprietary Sepsis Prediction Model in Hospitalized Patients. JAMA
                    Intern Med. 2021;181(8):1065–1070. doi:10.1001/jamainternmed.2021.2626</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Bodenreider O, Cornet R, Vreeman DJ. Recent Developments in Clinical
                    Terminologies - SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm. Yearb Med Inform. 2018
                    Aug;27(1):129-139. doi: 10.1055/s-0038-1667077. Epub 2018 Aug 29.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Logica Health, Health Level Seven International, Vocabulary Working Group. HL7
                    Standardized Terminology Knowledgebase, Release 1. [Internet]. Creative Commons
                    Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0); 2021. Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/private/standards/HL7_LM_TERM_KB_R1_INFORM_2021AUG_FINAL.pdf"
                        >HL7 Standardized Terminology Knowledgebase, Release</link></para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

