<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>System Safety Within Laboratory Data Exchanges Overview</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>System Safety FDA BAA Task 1.3 Background</title>
        <para>Task 1.3 includes an initial review of the laboratory data ecosystem based on our FDA
            BAA team member health system laboratories to baseline the current state of the
            laboratory data sources (Task 1.3.1), including data inputs, processes, and outputs.
            Other laboratory differences will also be documented based on support from CAP who has
            access to numerous labs for verification and validation of ecosystem information. The
            laboratory data workflow (Task 1.3.2) will be documented, validated, and verified. A
            table of existing lab data standards and requirements across the ecosystem (Task 1.3.3)
            will be mapped and documented across labs, patient portals, EHRs, LISs, HIEs, and Public
            Reporting platforms to baseline system operation. Lab data coding methods (including
            industry coding standards, such as LOINC and SNOMED CT) and local codes will be examined
            (Task 1.3.4). The similarities and differences between EHR/LIS/HIE and other laboratory
            data systems (Task 1.3.5) across the operations will be documented and described between
            laboratories, including performance barriers and enablers due to differences and
            similarities. Our team will generate simulated patient lab requests within two test
            laboratories. These simulated lab data exchanges between the labs and across the
            ecosystem current state will provide baseline system performance evaluation of data
            fidelity, integrity, quality, and semantic loss. Two or more reviewers will review the
            transactions to independently validate and verify the results. Statistical process
            control methods will be applied to measure system performance, such as using bivariate
            comparison of reviewer agreement and Cohen’s Kappa, or similar methods will be used to
            measure inter-rater reliability. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Task 1.3.1, 1.3.2, 1.3.3, and 1.3.4 Overview</title>
        <para>These tasks included interviews with internal project SMEs Raja Cholan, Dr. Scott
            Campbell, Dr. Hung Luu, and Dr. Samantha Spencer. Additionally, our team discussed
            Public Health Reporting with Dr. Vicky Derbyshire. From these interviews, we developed
            an initial mapping (Figure 1) of a hospital or health system laboratory operations
            (yellow) with laboratory professionals, technology, processes, and data/operational
            standards organizations (blue) and other/external health systems, agencies, and
            information system components (green). The solid lines represent regular flow,
            connections, and feedback between system components. Dashed lines represent irregular
            flows, communication, or connections. Dotted lines represent informal flows,
            communication, or connections. Laboratory data can take multiple different pathways
            based on local configurations within the internal system or when shared with external
            laboratories, other health systems, health registries, and public health agencies. The
            use of HL7 electronic standard messaging is ubiquitous across a unique hospital/health
            system laboratory data workflow yet likely applied differently across different
            hospital/health systems. Data movement protocol (v2 and FHIR) and content protocols
            vary, and data quality is usually <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> a consideration.
            The variability in workflow, application of standards (e.g., coding, terminology,
            messaging, reporting, etc.), and system configuration that exists across different
            laboratory systems creates the need for robust controls to ensure patient safety and
            data quality. </para>
        <para>In this workflow, a <emphasis role="bold">provider/prescriber</emphasis> orders a
            patient laboratory test through the hospital/health system electronic health record
            (EHR). The <emphasis role="bold">EHR</emphasis> records the request in the patient
            record and sends a laboratory request message to the Laboratory Information System
            (LIS/LIMS). </para><figure xml:id="HospitalandHealthSystemLaboratoryWorkflow">
                <title>Hospital/Health System Laboratory Workflow, Standards Integration, and Reporting</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/Hospital%20and%20Health%20System%20Laboratory%20Workflow,%20Standards%20Integration,%20and%20Reporting.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">LOINC and SNOMED codes</emphasis> (and other codes such as
            genomic coding used in precision medicine) are assigned to each laboratory test. LOINC
            and SNOMED codes are manually assigned by either laboratory personnel or LIS analysts
            with or without input from the laboratory medical directors. This coding is either done
            when a new test record is created or as was the case for Meaningful Use compliance, as
            part of an institutional initiative. When no code exists, local codes are created by the
            local laboratory analyst/professional. Agreement between LOINC and SNOMED code selection
            varies by as much as 50% among laboratory professionals across different clinical
            laboratories (Bernstam et al., 2022, Cholan et al., 2022). This manual process is
            foundational to data interoperability. Once in the LIS system, LOINC and SNOMED codes
            are not regularly updated in most instances. </para>
        <para>There is currently no centralized knowledge base for laboratories to verify LOINC and
            SNOMED codes that are assigned to tests and results in LISs. In situations where a
            precise concept/code is missing from LOINC or SNOMED, labs will make (arbitrary) choices
            to either code to a more general concept that does exist in LOINC/SNOMED or will choose
            to create a local code to represent the concept of interest. LOINC In Vitro Diagnostic
            (LIVD) Test Code Mapping specification exists and could help remove the coding guesswork
            by inexperienced laboratorians and the imprecision within LOINC and SNOMED for certain
            concepts. The LIVD file for SARS-CoV-2 reporting is publicly available on a CDC-hosted
                <link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/csels/dls/livd-codes.html"><emphasis
                    role="underline">website</emphasis></link> and has been required for use by HHS
            since summer 2020. The <emphasis role="bold">LIS</emphasis> signals the clinical
            laboratory of the patient test request. </para>
        <para>U.S. laboratory operations are certified by the Center for Medicare and Medicaid
            Services (CMS) using the <emphasis role="bold">Clinical Laboratory Improvement
                Amendments (CLIA) standards</emphasis>. CLIA does not govern laboratory data
            quality. CMS publishes the CLIA rules and regulations (including test results reporting)
            under 42 CFR § 493.1291. The test report must indicate the following: </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>For positive patient identification, either the patient's name and
                    identification number, or a unique patient identifier and identification number.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The name and address of the laboratory location where the test was
                    performed.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The test report date. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The test performed. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Specimen source, when appropriate. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The test result and, if applicable, the units of measurement or
                    interpretation, or both. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Any information regarding the condition and disposition of specimens that do
                    not meet the laboratory's criteria for acceptability. </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Pertinent “reference intervals” or “normal” values, as determined by the laboratory
            performing the tests, must be available to the authorized person who ordered the tests
            and, if applicable, the individual responsible for using the test results. </para>
        <para>CDC and FDA also provide CLIA regulation and oversight functions. The clinical
            laboratory conducts the test using an <emphasis role="bold">In-Vitro Device</emphasis>
            (IVD). LOINC and SNOMED codes are currently manually entered by either laboratory
            personnel or the LIS analyst team. These codes do not currently flow from any IVD
            instrument automatically. The IVD sends the test results to the LIS/LIMS using a
                <emphasis role="bold">middleware</emphasis> designed to communicate with the
            specific device and the LIS/LIMS. Middleware varies from vendor to vendor. Middleware is
            also known as interface engines. Middleware converts message syntax between systems (HL7
            v2) and devices (IEEE – a lower level engineering standard). The test results are then
            transmitted to the patient record within the EHR, back to the provider/prescriber, and
            ultimately, to the patient by the provider and/or through a patient portal. </para>
        <para>Laboratory results requiring <emphasis role="bold">external reporting</emphasis>(i.e.,
            to outside agencies (i.e., public health), health data registries (i.e., cancer,
            vaccine, etc.), and other hospitals/health systems (i.e., EHR 1 to EHR 2) use <emphasis
                role="bold">Health Information Exchanges</emphasis> (HIEs) or direct point-to-point
            communications via middleware. Each external lab or other hospital/health system has
            some form of their own LIS/lab operation. Manual data transformations are usually
            required when sending EHR data outside one system via an HIE, although middleware may
            automate information/data transfer. Between systems, interface engines/middleware
            converts/adjusts HL7 syntax requirements as required by senders/receivers. Some LIS/LIMS
            and EHRs have automated reporting functionality to outside agencies that bypasses the
            HIE or uses another third-party broker for transmission. In some cases, the <emphasis
                role="bold">public health agency </emphasis>may directly populate the <emphasis
                role="bold">registry database</emphasis> instead of the hospital/health system.
            Mandatory reportable conditions (e.g., infectious diseases, vaccine administration,
            cancer, chronic diseases, etc.) to public health agencies vary by State and Federal
            agency.Not all public health agencies are configured to receive some essential
            laboratory test data elements from the hospital/health system test results. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Current Insights Gained from Tasks 1.3.1, 1.3.2, 1.3.3, and 1.3.4 </title>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The ubiquitous nature of HL7 messaging across the laboratory electronic
                        information workflow. HL7 laboratory interfaces are often not reusable when
                        each external reporting request triggers a new HL7 message adding additional
                        laboratory IT resources. The amount of manual encoding required within each
                        laboratory adds additional laboratory IT/analyst burden and can introduce
                        errors. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Internal laboratory professionals have low trust in laboratory reports
                        from external laboratories—requiring significant manual data curation to
                        derive equivalence and ensure data quality before allowing test results into
                        internal systems (e.g., mapping external system test names, codes, and
                        results to the same “line” within the receiving LIS). This “healthy
                        skepticism” likely prevents clinical errors and adverse events but slows
                        data sharing scalability. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Laboratory test requests and results usually begin and end at the EHR or
                        LIS/LIMS. An order exception is Point of Care (POC) testing where a test can
                        be performed without a Computerized Provider Order Entry (CPOE) order. The
                        results are used for clinical care and then documented as part of the
                        patient progress note or manually entered into the EHR system, resulting in
                        laboratory data blind spots. This variability can result in patients not
                        being notified of critical lab values in a timely manner. While most POC
                        testing can be considered low risk (pregnancy test, urinalysis), some are
                        used to monitor and make treatment decisions for acutely ill patients (e.g.,
                        blood gas); therefore, further system analysis should be considered for POC
                        testing. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Middleware varies from vendor to vendor (there are many more middleware
                        vendor systems than EHR/LIS vendors performing numerous laboratory system
                        functions), which increases system complexity. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Many laboratory ecosystem interactions have irregular or absent feedback
                        loops, especially between terminology and standards organizations. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Task 1.3.5 and Next Steps</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Task 1.3.5</emphasis></emphasis>aims
            to develop a case example for identifying hazards, unsafe control actions, inadequate
            system constraints, data quality deficiencies, and insufficient feedback loops between
            two different health systems laboratories conducting the same laboratory tests. More
            specific details of the case example sampling, methods, and analysis will be developed
            during Phase II as the ecosystem safety control structure evolves. The following is an
            overview of the case example approach. This approach will be further refined based on
            client feedback. </para>
        <para>Initially, simulated patient laboratory test data will be collected between the
            University of Nebraska Medical Center (UNMC) laboratory and the University of Texas
            Southwestern (UTSW) Children’s Health. No Protected Health Information (PHI) data will
            be collected or used. UNMC and UTSW will create simulated patient records within their
            respective EHRs for initiating the test requests across EHR systems. </para>
        <para>Laboratory tests will not actually be performed on specimens. Instead, our team will
            create test patients with identical demographic information in the UNMC and UTSW
            systems. Simulated test results for a variety of qualitative and quantitative tests will
            be entered into the test patient record at both institutions. Patient encounters will be
            entered for the patient, triggering the transfer of test results between the two
            institutions via the Epic Systems Care Everywhere, an HIE platform available to Epic
            Systems customers. Specific analysis plan for the orderable and performable will be
            defined, including a statistically adequate patient sample, number of tests, and minimum
            reported data elements in accordance with CLIA standards plus additional information
            related IVD, EHR, LIS, and middleware configurations. </para>
        <para>The original test result at the originating institution will be compared using an
            Independent Verification and Validation (IV&amp;V) methodology with what has been
            transmitted to the receiving institution with an analysis of 1) how the transmitted data
            compares to CLIA requirements, 2) whether or not enough information about the test has
            been transmitted to determine equivalence, and 3) the safety and quality implications if
            the results were assumed to be equivalent and trended on the same line. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Next Steps: </emphasis>As our AIM 1 Phase II begins, Task 1.3
            will serve as an initial “zoom-in” source of laboratory ecosystem operations for the
            System-Theoretic Process Analysis (STPA), Phase III case examples, and Phase IV
            deliverables. </para>
        <para>Additional zoom-in analysis based on Task 1.3 will include the following in Phase II: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Inclusion of global extensions and local extensions </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Laboratory Developed Tests (LDTs) consideration as local extensions.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Consider the various genomic systems as global extensions. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Laboratory Data flow – Rename to Data Flow for Encoding </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Could be how data is encoded and sent to LOINC (e.g., LIS to LOINC).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Could be how LOINC distributes the new test names and sent from LOINC
                            (e.g., secondary). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Could be between the laboratory and LOINC. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Could be between the IVD manufacturers and LOINC. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Where do LOINC, SNOMED, and other codes (e.g., genomics) fit? </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Need to include National Library of Medicine (NLM) in system. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Explore Case Example Scenario expansion: </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Scenario A – Flow of Patient’s data (follow the number everywhere) –
                            PHI. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Scenario B – Flow of how the PHI went through a transformation (LIS –
                            HIS for example). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Scenario C – Process for things that don’t exist yet (Emergency Use
                            Authorization [EUA] for a COVID test), or where there are errors (e.g.,
                            flow back from SNOMED). </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>These scenarios could inform a set of new control points (e.g., what is the
                    quality of the LOINC release, etc. and D-dimer in LOINC error-prone without a
                    third party audit, like IV&amp;V, also genomics coding). </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Focus on instances in certain categories in a more generic sense (e.g., AST,
                    B1 supplemented, etc.). </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Include interviews of LOINC and SNOMED. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

