<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <info>
        <title>Terminology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar) Modeling Guide [Draft]</title>
        <subtitle>Subtitle</subtitle>
    </info>
    
        <chapter>
            <title>Tinkar Modeling Guide Introduction</title>
        <para>This modeling guide establishes the process and outputs for modeling domain concepts
            in the Terminology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar) specification. This guide does not
            encompass all the details and information about the Tinkar model. Therefore, it is
            encouraged to review the <link
                xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/documentcenter/private/standards/HL7_LM_TERM_KB_R1_INFORM_2021AUG_FINAL.pdf"
                >HL7 informative ballot</link> before this guide.</para>
        <section>
            <title>What is Tinkar?</title>
            <para>Tinkar is a logical model that aims to provide a foundation for a knowledge
                architecture that will integrate medical and laboratory terminologies like SNOMED
                CT®, LOINC®, RxNorm, etc. and local systems, to support clinical information that
                can communicate effectively across multiple systems.​ Tinkar is intended to support
                health care organizations’ standard terminology modules, value sets, and coding
                systems as well as local terms and equivalence mappings. It allows enterprises to
                extend their terminology standards and implement extensions quickly.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Why Tinkar?</title>
            <para>Information systems that are used across the healthcare enterprise record and
                manage clinical data using clinical statements and clinical terminologies in
                non-standardized ways. Interoperability specifications aim to require terminology
                bindings to concepts, code systems, and reusable value sets. Currently, there is
                variation in clinical data exchange across the enterprise, as existing payloads and
                clinical statements use inconsistent and highly variable enterprise terminologies.
                The management of the concepts, code systems, and value sets is non-trivial because
                developers, implementers, and end users are forced to manage “unnecessary
                complexity.” For example:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Representation of medications: RxNorm codes overlap with CVX codes.
                        Investigational vaccines from the FDA are not represented in RxNorm, CVX, or
                        SNOMED CT®.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Representation of COVID-19 result codes are inconsistent and are not
                        equivalent (e.g., detected, undetected, positive, negative, etc.).</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Tinkar Logical Model</title>
        <para>The Tinkar logical model consists of three different attributes: concepts, patterns, and semantics . The model can represent any knowledge standard, while still allowing for transparency of the data and traceability.
            <figure xml:id="TinkarLogicalModel">
                <title>Tinkar Logical Model</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/Tinkar%20Logical%20Model.svg" scale="70" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            Before modeling a data set in the logical Tinkar model, the current Tinkar logical model starter data concepts, patterns and semantics should be understood.  The goal is to use what already exists in Tinkar as much as possible and only create new concepts/patterns/ semantics when needed.  This section gives a basic rundown of the Tinkar logical model.  The full description of the logical model is in the HL7 ballot, linked in the Introduction of this document.
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Components</title>
            <para>All components in Tinkar are uniquely identified using UUIDs. A component will be
                represented by an array of UUIDs with at least one UUID but can be represented by
                more than one UUID in the case of a concept being derived from multiple sources. For
                example, the concept Acetaminophen (which exists in SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, and RxNorm)
                could have a UUID from each terminology and be represented as an array of UUIDs for
                this single concept within a Tinkar implementation. Concepts, patterns, and
                semantics are types of components. </para>
            <section>
                <title>Concepts</title>
                <para>A concept in Tinkar is a component identified using Universally Unique
                    Identifiers (UUIDs) and a STAMP. It contains no information other than what’s
                    contained within the STAMP. Concepts have emergent meaning. For example,
                    Acetaminophen can be represented by attaching the description “Acetaminophen” to
                    a concept. The concept has no meaning without additional information. Additional
                    information is provided by semantics. The specific meaning, purpose, and data
                    elements of a semantic are defined by a pattern. </para>
                <para>For example, for the concept of Acute Pelvic Pain, there needs to be
                    information to describe it, which is all asserted by one or more semantics of
                    one or more patterns (possibly multiple descriptions, a logical definition, …).
                    Examples of that assertion include descriptions of the concept, the fully
                    qualified name, and unique relationships related to the concept.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Patterns</title>
                <para>A pattern defines a meaning and purpose for its semantics, and a set of
                    fields, which also have a specific a purpose, and a meaning, in addition to a
                    datatype. Every semantic of a pattern exactly follows that pattern. These fields
                    describe what type of information and what format the data in a semantic
                    following this pattern will be. Using the pattern, semantics with varying fields
                    and field types can be specified to represent any structure needed to provide
                    meaning to a component. The table below shows the Description Pattern. <table>
                        <title>Description Pattern</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="center"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="center"/>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Description Pattern</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                                    <entry>Description Semantic</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                                    <entry>Description Semantic</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 1: Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                    <entry>Language for Description</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                    <entry>Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Field Type</entry>
                                    <entry>Component Field</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 2: Description</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                    <entry>Text for Description</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                    <entry>Description</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Field Type</entry>
                                    <entry>String</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 3: Description Case
                                        Significance</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                    <entry>Description Case Significance</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                    <entry>Description Case Significance</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Field Type</entry>
                                    <entry>Component Field</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Field 4: Description
                                        Type</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Meaning</entry>
                                    <entry>Description Type</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                    <entry>Description Type</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Field Type</entry>
                                    <entry>Component Field</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table> The meaning and purpose concepts shown in the above table for the
                    Description Pattern also are concepts in Tinkar with definitions. The table
                    below shows the definition for the meaning and purpose concepts from the
                    Description Pattern table. </para>
                <table>
                    <title>Description Pattern Meaning and Purpose Concepts</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern Field</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition </emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Description Pattern Semantic Meaning
                                            and Purpose</emphasis></para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Description Semantic </entry>
                                <entry>Purpose and meaning for the description pattern and dialect
                                    patterns</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field 1: Language
                                    Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Language for Description </entry>
                                <entry>The semantic value indicating which language is used in the
                                    description text</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field 1: Language
                                    Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Language </entry>
                                <entry>Specifies the language of the description text.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field 2: Description
                                    Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Text for Description</entry>
                                <entry>Captures the human readable text for a description in
                                    Komet</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field 2: Description
                                    Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Human readable text for a concept</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field 3: Description Case Significance
                                        Meaning and Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Description Case Significance </entry>
                                <entry>Specifies how to handle the description text in terms of case
                                    sensitivity</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field 4: Description Type Meaning and
                                        Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Description Type </entry>
                                <entry>Specifying what type of description, e.g., fully qualified or
                                    regular, etc.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Semantics</title>
                <para>To give computer-processable meaning to components, Tinkar uses Semantics. A
                    Semantic is a component containing a set of fields about the subject (the
                    meaning and purpose defined by its pattern). A Semantic adds meaning to the
                    components it references through the fields it contains. A Semantic supports the
                    specification of value sets, compositional definitions, and other components
                    requiring internal structure, and it specifies the nature of the compositional
                    relationship explicitly. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>STAMP</title>
            <para>The STAMP in the Tinkar Reference Model allows for capturing a complete change
                record of all changes to a component including the Status, Time, Author, Module, and
                Path. As a model changes and evolves, with each change made in a component, a new
                change record is created for that change and a new STAMP Coordinate is assigned. To
                track information like when and who made the changes, a STAMP is assigned to each
                version, so the history is recorded and preserved.</para>
            <para>The following describes each of these attributes:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis> – A status is identified by a Concept and
                may be annotated with additional information. For example, inactive or active. The
                tables below show the parent and children Concepts aligned to Status.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Status Parent Concept</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status Value </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The status represented by the STAMP (Active, Cancelled, Inactive,
                                Premundane, Withdrawn)</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table>
                <title>Status Children Concepts</title>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                    <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Business Rules</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Use Case Example</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Premundane Status</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for the default status. It’s
                                the original default status when creating a Concept that has not
                                transitioned to a different status.</entry>
                            <entry>In the Premundane status, components can move to the Cancelled or
                                Active statuses. Since primordial components were never committed to
                                a database there would be no reason to move them to the Inactive or
                                Withdrawn statuses.</entry>
                            <entry>When a new component has been created but nothing is assigned nor
                                has it been approved, it would have a Premundane status.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Canceled Status</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for components that are
                                canceled – Canceled means it was never successfully committed to the
                                database, and so this state would be local only, and also transient…
                                It will eventually be removed from memory and from the database and
                                will not propagate from one database to another.</entry>
                            <entry>The Cancelled status is a terminal status, meaning it cannot be
                                moved from the Cancelled status back to a different status.</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>If a new component is:</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Created accidentally</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Created initially in the Premundane status but is
                                            deemed unnecessary </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                                <para>It would be moved to Cancelled status. </para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Active Status</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for components that are
                                active.</entry>
                            <entry>In the Active status, components can move to the Inactive status
                                if a component is no longer active or the Withdraw status, if the
                                component is realized to be a mistake.</entry>
                            <entry>A component that was in Premundane status that has been fully
                                reviewed and vetted will move to the Active status.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Inactive Status</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for components that are no
                                longer active.</entry>
                            <entry>In the Inactive status, components can move to the Withdraw
                                status, if the component is realized to be a mistake. In special
                                circumstances with a good business reason, components may be moved
                                from Inactive back to Active.</entry>
                            <entry>A component that is no longer needed that was in the Active
                                status. For example, the model changed or was made obsolete by a new
                                component.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Withdrawn Status </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Concept used to represent a status for components that are
                                withdrawn. Withdrawn indicates that a component was successfully
                                released, but that the component’s release was a mistake, and all
                                references to a withdrawn component should be reassigned. </entry>
                            <entry>The Withdrawn status is a terminal status. </entry>
                            <entry>If a component was accidentally created and committed to the
                                Active status, it would be moved to the Withdrawn status.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>When representing a new data set using the Tinkar Reference Model, only the status
                values above are allowed and must follow the business rules defined. The business
                rules do not account for the accidental moving of a component. The diagram below
                shows the mapping between each status.</para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="StatusDiagram">
                    <title>Status Diagram</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Status%20Diagram.svg" scale="70"
                                align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>If the data set has additional status values, for example the LOINC® Discouraged
                Status, they should be represented via an additional Pattern and Semantic. The STAMP
                status values should never be extended beyond the provided starter set. In the
                LOINC® example, the status would be Active since it was in use, but a Semantic would
                be assigned to say it was Discouraged to take note of that extra information.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Time </emphasis>– The timestamp is captured with precision
                and a time zone. The table below shows the parent Concept aligned to Time.</para>
            <para>
                <table>
                    <title>Time Parent Concept</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The timestamp is captured with precision and a time
                                        zone</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Author – </emphasis>The author is identified by a Concept
                and may be annotated with more information and represents the change's author. The
                tables below show the parent Concept aligned to Author.</para>
            <para>
                <table>
                    <title>Author Parent Concept</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The author is identified by a Concept, and may be
                                        annotated with other identifying information and represents
                                        the author responsible for authoring the change</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Module </emphasis>– This is the assignment to the
                appropriate terminology (e.g. LOINC®) or terminology component (SNOMED CT®). A
                module is identified by a Concept and may be annotated with additional information.
                The tables below show the parent and children Concepts aligned to Module.</para>
            <para>
                <table>
                    <title>Module Parent Concept</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A module is identified by a Concept and may be annotated with
                                    additional information such as organizing content for
                                    maintenance and publication purposes.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>Module Child Concept</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Child Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold"
                                        ><?oxy_comment_start author="tocrow" timestamp="20240627T101554-0400" comment="Premundane?"?>Primordial<?oxy_comment_end?>
                                        Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>The base/foundational/default module assigned prior to
                                    creating other model/module Concepts, the primordial module is
                                    reserved for starter set information that all Tinkar Reference
                                    Models require. Information that is specific to a particular
                                    data set (i.e., SNOMED CT® or LOINC®) should be contained in a
                                    module specific to that data set (i.e. a SNOMED CT® or LOINC®
                                    starter set module)</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Path –</emphasis> Specification of version control within a
                development lifecycle, for example development, testing, staging, or production. A
                path is identified by a Concept and may be annotated with additional information.
                The tables below show the parent and children Concepts aligned to Path.</para>
            <para><table>
                    <title>Path Parent Concept</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Parent Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A set of assets under version control that can be managed
                                    distinctly from other assets. Paths “branch” from other paths
                                    when established and can be “merged” with other paths as well.
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table><table>
                    <title>Path Children Concepts in the starter set. Additional paths may be
                        created as need to organize development activities appropriately for a
                        particular purpose (sandbox paths, feature paths, …) </title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Prerequisite Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A path that contains components that are shared across all
                                    paths and contain infrastructure components.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sandbox Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A path “branch” for components under testing.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Development Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A path “branch” that specifies that the components are
                                    currently under development</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Master Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A default path “branch” for components. This path represents
                                    those finalized or published components in production</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table> The diagram below shows the relationship between different Paths. <figure
                    xml:id="PathDiagram">
                    <title>Path Diagram</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Path%20Diagram.svg" scale="70" align="center"
                            />
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>The STAMP attributes are used to help describe versions of components. As a
                model changes and evolves, with each change made in a component, a new version is
                created for that change. To track information like when and who made the changes, a
                STAMP is assigned to each version, so the history is recorded and preserved. </para>
            <section>
                <title>STAMP Progression Examples in Component Versions</title>
                <para>To understand how STAMP are being assigned to component versions, the
                    following examples below illustrate how STAMP functions and the design process
                    behind it. </para>
                <section>
                    <title>Example 1: Proposing a New SNOMED CT® Regular Name (Synonym)
                        Locally</title>
                <para>In this example, a new Regular Name description to a SNOMED CT® Concept as a
                    local extension is proposed. Since a new Semantic is being created, which is a
                    component, the new component version needs a STAMP. In this example, the
                    following parts are assigned:</para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">STAMP</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Value</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Reasoning</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Active</entry>
                                <entry>Status is set to Active since the Semantic should be active
                                    and visible.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Current Date Time</entry>
                                <entry>The current date and time when the Semantic was
                                    created.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>User Account</entry>
                                <entry>The specific user account as a Tinkar Concept should be
                                    assigned.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Local Extension Module to SNOMED CT®</entry>
                                <entry>This is a local extension not any official SNOMED CT®
                                    release.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Development Path</entry>
                                <entry>This is a proposal for the new Semantic and not an official
                                    reviewed Semantic.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Example 2: Testing Different Pattern Designs for Approval and Moving
                        Forward with One</title>
                <para>In this example, three different Patterns to simulate storing experimental
                    data in different ways are tested. Those can be sent off to another user and
                    they decide which one they like best and propose to keep that one and get rid of
                    the others.</para>
                <para>To start out, all three different Patterns would have similar STAMP
                    assignments:</para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">STAMP</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Value</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Reasoning</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Active</entry>
                                <entry>Status is set to Active since the Semantic should be active
                                    and visible.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Current Date Time</entry>
                                <entry>The current date and time when the Semantic was
                                    created.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>User Account</entry>
                                <entry>The specific user account as a Tinkar Concept should be
                                    assigned. For this example, “Author 1” is used.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Experimental Data Module</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Unique Module to specify the domain or data set that is
                                        being used.</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Sandbox Path</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The proposed Patterns are just made for testing the data
                                        and not official or in progress yet.</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                <para>A second person might then look at those testing Patterns and if they decide
                    they like one design over the others, they can update the Patterns to new
                    versions and reflect their decision in the STAMP for those Pattern
                    versions.</para>
                <para>The Pattern they would like to keep:</para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">STAMP</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Value</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Reasoning</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Active</entry>
                                <entry>Status is set to Active since the Semantic should be active
                                    and visible.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Current Date Time</entry>
                                <entry>The current date and time when the Semantic was
                                    created.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>User Account</entry>
                                <entry>The second person who chose the Pattern or “Author
                                    2”.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Experimental Data Module</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Unique Module to specify the domain or data set that is
                                        being used.</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Development Path</entry>
                                <entry>The proposed Pattern now has moved into development and is
                                    waiting for official approval and review before it can
                                    potentially be moved to the “Master Path”.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                <para>The other Patterns they would like to remove:</para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">STAMP</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Value</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Reasoning</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Inactive</entry>
                                <entry>The status is changed to inactive since the users no longer
                                    want these Patterns and aren’t going to use them.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Time</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Current Date Time</entry>
                                <entry>The current date and time when the Semantic was
                                    created.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>User Account</entry>
                                <entry>The second person who chose the Pattern or “Author
                                    2”.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Experimental Data Module</entry>
                                <entry>Unique Module to specify the domain or data set being used.
                                    Remains the same.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Sandbox Path</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>The proposed Patterns are still just testing Patterns and
                                        not official or in development.</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
            </section>
        </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Tinkar Representation Examples</title>
            <para>The section below highlights examples of how common medical tests can be
                represented in Tinkar. The examples show how the tests, currently represented in
                both SNOMED CT® and LOINC® terminologies, can be modeled in the Tinkar Logical
                Model. </para>
            <section>
                <title>Example 1 - Urine Homocysteine</title>
                <para>The figure below illustrates a Urine Homocysteine Test represented in the
                    Tinkar Logical Model. The Concept contains both the description for the test as
                    well as its corresponding UUID. This Concept serves as the subject for further
                    classification. The Pattern uses field definitions to explain and categorize the
                    corresponding Semantic fields. For example, LOINC® records the interval of time
                    over which an observation was made. The time to conduct a Urine Homocysteine
                    Test is 24 hours. Therefore, under the Time field definition within the LOINC®
                    Pattern, the corresponding Semantic Field would be 24H. While there are separate
                    Patterns and Semantics for both SNOMED CT® and LOINC® terminologies, they are
                    both connected to the original Concept. </para>
                <para>
                    <figure xml:id="Example1UrineHomocysteineRepresentationinTinkar">
                        <title>Urine Homocysteine Representation in Tinkar</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata
                                    fileref="images/Urine%20Homocysteine%20Representation%20in%20Tinkar.svg"
                                    scale="70" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 2 - Substance Concentration of Glucose in Specimen at Point in
                    Time</title>
                <para>The below figure illustrates a Substance Concentration of Glucose in Specimen
                    Test represented in the Tinkar Logical Model. The Concept contains both the
                    description for the test as well as its corresponding UUID. This Concept serves
                    as the subject for further classification. The Pattern uses field definitions to
                    explain and categorize the corresponding Semantic fields. For example, this test
                    involves measuring the concentration of glucose in a given specimen. Therefore,
                    under the Method field definition within the SNOMED CT® Pattern, the
                    corresponding semantic field would be Measurement – action. While there are
                    separate Patterns and Semantics for both SNOMED CT® and LOINC® terminologies,
                    they are both connected to the original Concept.</para>
            <para>
                    <figure xml:id="Example2SubstanceConcentrationofGlucoseinSpecimeninTinkar">
                        <title>Example 2: Substance Concentration of Glucose in Specimen in
                            Tinkar</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata
                                    fileref="images/Substance%20Concentration%20of%20Glucose%20in%20Specimen%20in%20Tinkar.svg"
                                    scale="70" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Modeling Principles</title>
        <para>There are specific principles to try and follow while executing the modeling process.
            These principles are detailed below. </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Encapsulate rather than
                            specialize.</emphasis></emphasis>: For example, if a device identifier
                    is sourced from a database like the Global Unique Device Identification Database
                    (GUDID), you would not create a new Pattern to handle it. You should continue to
                    use the Identifier Pattern already created in GUDID, but instead create a new
                    Pattern to add any additional information needed (i.e. Is it a Primary DI or a
                    Secondary DI?, etc.) This new Pattern could then have Semantics referencing the
                    identifier Semantic components to give meaning.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">A Pattern/Field Definition
                            cannot have the same purpose as its meaning.</emphasis></emphasis>: In
                    cases where a pattern has more than one field definition, we want the purpose
                    and meaning to be unique for each field definition. If there is only one field
                    definition it is okay if the meaning and purpose are the same but in general we
                    want to be as specific here as possible since the reasoner looks at these
                    purpose and meaning concepts to determine equivalence in patterns.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Creating a Representative Tinkar Model for a Dataset</title>
        <para>Converting a <emphasis role="bold">domain </emphasis><emphasis role="bold">data
                set</emphasis> into the Tinkar model involves several key steps. The sections below
            detail the current <emphasis role="bold">Tinkar starter data</emphasis> and the steps
            one will take to translate a dataset into the Tinkar logical model. <figure
                xml:id="KeyStepstoRepresentaDataSetinTinkar">
                <title>Key Steps to Represent a Data Set in Tinkar</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata
                            fileref="images/Key%20Steps%20to%20Represent%20a%20Data%20Set%20in%20Tinkar.svg"
                            scale="70" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Defining The Data Elements</title>
            <para>Once the current basic Tinkar Reference Model is understood, the data set’s
                required Patterns can be determined. Some Patterns will come from the current Tinkar
                starter set, other Patterns will be created specifically for the data set’s unique
                properties or may be reused from other systems such as SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, or
                RxNorm. </para>
            <para>In preparation to model in Tinkar, there are two different ways to start: from an
                existing system’s data set like SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, or RxNorm or a new model using
                elements that might already exist and/or have brand new elements that need to be
                represented (e.g., LIDR). The differences between a predefined data set and a new
                data set are minimal. The main difference is, with a predefined data set,
                information about the model is usually well documented so identifying a unique list
                of data elements and definitions is more straight forward. With a new data set,
                unique data elements and definitions will take more time to validates.</para>
            <para>The first step in modeling in Tinkar from any data set is analyzing the data set
                or source file that needs to be represented in Tinkar. The recommended starting
                point is pulling out all unique data fields in the data set or source file and
                giving them a meaning, purpose, and definition.</para>
            <para>In general, the term meaning refers to the Concept or idea that a word, phrase,
                symbol, or other form of communication represents. Within the Tinkar Reference
                Model, "meaning" is applied to a field within a Semantic and indicates the type of
                information or data the field is designed to hold. For example, a field used to
                describe an SDO's website would have the Meaning of "URL." This implies that the
                field is meant to contain a URL, which is a specific type of data representing a web
                address.</para>
            <para>The purpose within the Tinkar Reference Model refers to the specific role or
                function that a field within a Semantic is intended to serve. It provides a broader
                context for why the field and its data exist within the model. For example, in the
                field describing an SDO's website, the purpose is "Website." This indicates that the
                field's role is to provide the website address for the SDO, adding context to the
                meaning "URL.".</para>
            <para>For a data set that is part of a well-established source such as RxNorm and SNOMED
                CT®, definitions of fields can typically be found in documentation online of the
                terminology. For a data set that is not well-established, the definitions might have
                to be created.</para>
            <para>To show a practical example of a predefined data set, an image below shows a
                snippet of the LOINC®transformation. LOINC®is a predefined data set with definitions
                and fields listed in a source file. In this snippet, some of the unique LOINC®fields
                provided in the data set are added to an excel in preparation for a cross walk. The
                purpose, meaning, and definitions are added to give an example of what these
                definitions should be.</para>
            <figure xml:id="ExampleofLOINCDataElements">
                <title>Example of LOINC®Data Elements</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/Example%20of%20LOINC%20Data%20Elements.svg"
                            scale="70" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows a row of LOINC®data that will be used
                to show how the data set was represented using the Description Semantics.</para>
                <para>Once unique data elements have been recorded, the elements can be cross walked
                    to current Tinkar semantics/ concepts/ patterns.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Determine Description Semantics</title>
            <para>It is recommended to start with the description semantic and review the components
                and determine which of the fields in the data set being analyzed can be represented
                using the Tinkar description semantics. The Description Semantics are how names and
                definitions are assigned to components. The fields in the Description Pattern in
                Table 1 should be reviewed to determine what values/concepts to use in the data set
                being analyzed or if something new needs to be created. The meaning and purpose
                concepts are also below to reference are listed in Table 2.</para>
            <para>To understand how this has been done before, examples of terminology snippets from
                SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, RxNorm, and LIDR are provided below. As the following sections
                walk through modeling the Description Semantic, these snippets will be referred to
                as examples for how to model certain fields.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Example 1: SNOMED CT Regular Name</title>
            <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows a row of LOINC®data that will be used
                to show how the data set was represented using the Description Semantics. </para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="SNOMEDDescriptionDataExample">
                    <title>SNOMED Description Data Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/SNOMED%20Description%20Data%20Example.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
            </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 2: LOINC Long Common Name</title>
                    <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows a row of LOINC®data that will
                        be used to show how the data set was represented using the Description
                        Semantics.</para>
                
                <figure xml:id="LOINCDescriptionDataExample">
                    <title>SNOMED Description Data Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/LOINC%20Description%20Data%20Example.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 3: RxNorm Tallman Synonym</title>
            <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows a row of RxNorm data that will be used
                to show how the data set was represented using the Description Semantics.</para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="RxNormOWLFileExample">
                    <title>RxNorm OWL File Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/RxNorm%20OWL%20File%20Example.svg" scale="70"
                                align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 4: LIDR Device Model</title>
            <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows multiple rows in LIDR Data all
                corresponding to one Device. This data that will be used to show how the data set
                was represented using the Description Semantics for a Device concept.</para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="LIDRDescriptionDataExample">
                    <title>LIDR Description Data Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/LIDR%20Description%20Data%20Example.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Field 1: Language</title>
                <para>A language Concept is assigned as the first field value for the Description
                    Semantic. The language field's purpose is to identify the concept's language and
                    description. The table below outlines the current available languages to select
                    from. If the specific language concept does not exist in Tinkar, a new concept
                    to represent that specific language will need to be added.</para>
                <para><informaltable>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                            <tbody>
                                <row >
                                    
                                    <entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold" >Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">English Language
                                        </emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the English Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Spanish Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Spanish Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Chinese Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Chinese Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Czech Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Czech Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Danish Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Danish Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Dutch Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Dutch Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">French Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the French Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">German Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the German Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Irish Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Irish Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Italian Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Italian Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Korean Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Korean Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Lithuanian
                                        Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Lithuanian Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Polish Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Polish Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Russian Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Russian Language</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Swedish Language</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>A concept representing the Swedish Language</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </informaltable>Revisiting the examples provided above, the following
                    representations and/or gaps were identified: </para>
                <table>
                    <title>Language Examples</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED
                                    CT®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export file, language Code can be
                                    represented by the language Concept. In this case, 'en' would be
                                    used for English.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the LOINC® export file, the English version has been
                                    obtained, so all descriptions can be represented by the language
                                    Concept.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the RxNorm export file, the English version has been
                                    obtained, so all descriptions can be represented by the language
                                    Concept and English can be used.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 4: LIDR</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the LIDR Excel File, the data was entered using the
                                    English Language, so all descriptions can be represented by the
                                    language Concept and English can be used.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>No new concepts would need to be created since the above strings can be
                    represented with what already exists in Tinkar.</para>
                <para>If the data set has a language concept that currently is not in Tinkar, a new
                    concept representing the new language will have to be created.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">To add a language concept:</emphasis></para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a new concept.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Give it the Fully Qualified name of the specific language the concept
                            is representing.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>In the Stated Definition, add an is-A relationship to language under
                            the necessary set.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Field 2: Description String</title>
                <para>The description string field is the literal string representation of the data,
                    which is generally just the name of the element. </para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description String </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>The string value that represents the data.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                <para>Revisiting the examples provided above, the following representations were
                    identified:</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Description String Examples</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED
                                    CT®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export file, the string value of the Term
                                    field "Chronic lung disease" is taken to represent the Tinkar
                                    Description String value in the Description Semantic.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the LOINC® export file, the string value of the Long
                                    Common Name "Meadow Fescue IgG Ab [Units/volume] in Serum" is
                                    taken to represent the Tinkar Description String value in the
                                    Description Semantic.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the RxNorm export file, the string value of the text
                                    inside the quotations "amLODIPine (as amLODIPine besilate) 5 MG
                                    / HCTZ 25 MG / olmesartan medoxomil 40 MG Oral Tablet" is taken
                                    to represent the Tinkar Description String value in the
                                    Description Semantic.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 4: LIDR</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the LIDR Data File, the String Value of the text inside
                                    the Model cell “BD SARS-CoV-2/Flu for BD MAX System” is the
                                    description which can be represented using the Tinkar
                                    Description String value in the Description Semantic.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>No new concepts would need to be created since the above strings can be
                    represented with what already exists in Tinkar.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Field 3: Description Case Significance</title>
                <para>The description case significance specifies how the capitalization of the
                    string value should be handled, e.g., is it case sensitive or is it case
                    insensitive. If the data has more specific capitalization rules, a new concept
                    would need to be created to represent it.</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Description Case Significance</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Case
                                    Sensitive</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Assumes the description is dependent on
                                    capitalization</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Not Case Sensitive
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value which designates character as not sensitive for a given
                                    description</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>Revisiting the examples provided in section 3.2, the following representations
                    and/or gaps were identified: <table>
                        <title>Case Significance Example</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED
                                        CT®</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export, the caseSignificanceID can be
                                        represented using the Case Significance child Concept.
                                        Specifically, in this scenario, Description Not Case
                                        Sensitive would be used.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2:
                                        LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>In the LOINC® export file, there is no requirement to
                                        enforce case sensitivity on the long common name during a
                                        search, hence Description Not Case Sensitive would be used
                                        to represent its case significance.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3:
                                        RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>In the RxNorm export file, the Tallman synonym
                                        specifically incorporates certain capital letters with a
                                        particular purpose, thus Description Case Sensitive would be
                                        used to represent its case significance.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 4: LIDR</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>In the LIDR Data, there is no requirement to enforce case
                                        sensitivity during a search, hence Description Not Case
                                        Sensitive would be used to represent its case
                                        significance.</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>No new concepts would need to be created since the above Description
                    Case Significance can be represented with what already exists in Tinkar. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Field 4: Description Type</title>
                <para>The description type field is assigned to determine the type of description
                    the string represents about that component. For example, the Fully Qualified
                    Name is the main way a component is referred to. The Regular Name is any other
                    common way or synonym referring to that concept. The Definition Description Type
                    can be used to give a definition to any concept. If none of the description
                    types below represent the description specific to the data set, a new concept
                    would be created under Description Type to represent the new type of
                    data.</para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Type</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Specifying what type of description it is (i.e., is it fully
                                    qualified or regular and etc.)</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                <table>
                    <title>Description Type</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition Description Type
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Semantic value describing the description type for the
                                    description pattern is a definition</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Fully Qualified Name Description
                                        Type</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Fully qualified name is a description that uniquely
                                    identifies and differentiates it from other concepts with
                                    similar descriptions</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Regular Name Description Type
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>There may be descriptions/synonyms marked as
                                    “regular.”</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>Revisiting the examples provided above, the following representations and/or
                    gaps were identified: <table>
                        <title>Description Type Examples</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED
                                        CT®</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export file, typeId is represented
                                        using one of the Description Types. Specifically, Synonym is
                                        represented using the Tinkar Regular Name Description
                                        Type.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2:
                                        LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>From the LOINC® export file, the long common name can be
                                        represented using the Fully Qualified Name Description
                                        Type.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3:
                                        RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>From the RxNorm export file, considering the list of
                                        Tinkar Description Types above (Fully Qualified Name,
                                        Regular Name, etc.), none of them directly represent the
                                        Tallman Synonym. Given that the Tallman Synonym is
                                        specifically used to emphasize capitalizing certain
                                        portions, a new Concept is created as a child Concept under
                                        Description Type. This Concept is termed "Tallman
                                        Synonym".</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 4: LIDR</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>From the LIDR Data, only the Model is given to represent
                                        the Name of the Device. So in this case the Fully Qualified
                                        Name Description Type would be used.</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>One new concept was created to represent the Tallman synonym for RxNorm.
                    Otherwise, for SNOMED and LOINC®, no new concepts were created. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Determine Identifier Semantics</title>
            <para>The Identifier Semantics are used to assign unique identifiers to components that
                point to outside data sources in which the identifier is used. For example, SNOMED
                CT® Identifiers and LOINC®ID’s that can be assigned to concepts. The Identifier
                Pattern and children concepts are shown below.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Identifier Pattern</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center">Identifier
                                Pattern</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center">Field 1: Identifier
                                Source </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Field Type</entry>
                            <entry>Component Field</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center">Field 2: Identifier
                                Value</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>Identifier Source</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Field Type</entry>
                            <entry>String</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table>
                <title>Identifier Pattern Concept</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Identifier Source </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>An identifier that is used to label the identity of a unique
                                component.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Identifier Value </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The literal string value associated as the ID.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>To understand how this has been done before, examples of terminology snippets from
                SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, RxNorm, and LIDR are provided below. As the following sections
                walk through modeling the Identifier Semantic, these snippets will be referred to as
                examples for how to model certain fields.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Example 1: SNOMED CT®</title>
            
            <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows a row SNOMED CT® data that will be used
                to show how the data set was represented using the Identifier Semantics.</para>
            <para>Source: <link
                    xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCRELFMT/4.2.1+Concept+File+Specification"
                    >https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCRELFMT/4.2.1+Concept+File+Specification</link></para>
            <para>
                <figure>
                    <title>SNOMED CT® UUID Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/SNOMED%20Description%20Data%20Example.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 2: LOINC®</title>
                    
                    <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows a row LOINC® data that will be
                        used to show how the data set was represented using the Identifier
                        Semantics.</para>
                    <para>Source: <link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3"
                            >https://LOINC®.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3</link>. </para>
                
                <figure>
                    <title>LOINC®UUID® Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/LOINC%20Description%20Data%20Example.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 3: RxNorm</title>
            
            <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows a row RxNorm data that will be used to
                show how the data set was represented using the Identifier Semantics.</para>
            <para>Source File: <link
                    xlink:href="https://lhncbc.nlm.nih.gov/RxNav/news/RxNorm-in-OWL.html"
                    >https://lhncbc.nlm.nih.gov/RxNav/news/RxNorm-in-OWL.html</link></para>
            <para>
                <figure>
                    <title>RxNorm OWL File Identifier</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/RxNorm%20OWL%20File%20Example.svg" scale="70"
                                align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 4: LIDR</title>
            
            <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows multiple rows in LIDR Data all
                corresponding to one Device. This data will be used to show how the data set was
                represented using the Identifier Semantics.</para>
            <para>
                <figure>
                    <title>LIDR Data File Identifier</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/LIDR%20Description%20Data%20Example.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Field 1: Identifier Source</title>
                <para>The Identifier source is a unique identifier representing the data source it
                    comes from, such as SNOMED CT®  or LOINC®. In cases where a data set is being
                    represented for the first time in Tinkar, the source most likely will not exist
                    yet and a concept will need to be created for it.</para>
                <table>
                    <title>UUID Concept</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Universally Unique Identifier
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A universally unique identifier that uniquely represents a
                                    concept in Tinkar</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>Revisiting the examples outlined in Section 3.3, the following representations
                    and/or gaps were identified:</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Identifier Source Examples</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED
                                    CT®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">From the SNOMED CT® export file, given
                                        that the ID is not a UUID</emphasis><emphasis role="bold">,
                                        a new Concept is needed. This Concept, referred to as
                                        "SNOMED CT® Identifier Source", becomes a child Concept of
                                        Identifier Source. The Semantic Field Value references this
                                        newly created Concept.</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the LOINC® export file, absence of an Identifier Source
                                    like in Example 1 exists. Thus, creation of a new "LOINC®
                                    Number" Concept under Identifier Source is needed, and used for
                                    the Semantic Field Value.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>From the RxNorm export file, assignment of two different
                                        Identifiers to the Concept results in two separate
                                        Identifier Semantics. One Semantic references the RxNorm
                                        CUI, while the other references the SNOMED CT® ID</para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>In the case of the RxNorm CUI, creation of a new
                                                Concept under Identifier Source is required, named
                                                "RxNorm CUI". This becomes the Semantic Field Value
                                                for the first Identifier Semantic.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Regarding the SNOMED CT® ID, a new Concept needs
                                                creation, or utilization of the Concept from Example
                                                1 would be used if it was previously created in the
                                                model.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 4: LIDR</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the LIDR Data, the specific Issuing Agency and
                                    Jurisdiction have been combined to signify the source of the
                                    Name ID assigned. Thus, creation of a new “GS1_US FDA” Concept
                                    under Identifier Source is needed, and used for the Semantic
                                    Field Value.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>In these examples, each example needed a new concept to represent the Unique
                    Identifier.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Field 2: Identifier Value</title>
                <para>The identifier value is the string representation of the Identifier, usually a
                    random integer. Revisiting the examples provided in section 3.3, the following
                    representations and/or gaps were identified:</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Identifier Value Examples</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED
                                    CT®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the SNOMED CT® export file, the literal string value
                                    representing the ID column “413839001” is used for the field
                                    value.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the LOINC® export file, the literal string value
                                    representing the LOINC_NUM column “7364-3” is used for the field
                                    value.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>From the RxNorm export file, in the previous example, 2
                                        fields were created using 2 semantics. The string value
                                        representing each ID would be used to represent the field
                                        value.</para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>“1000001” For RxNorm CUI</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>“447089002” For SNOMED CT</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 4: LIDR</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>From the LIDR Data file, the literal string value
                                    representing the DI (Device Identifier “00382904453619” will be
                                    the field value</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Determine Stated Definition Semantics</title>
            <para>The Stated Definition Semantic represents the unique relationships that define a
                concept. This can be difficult to model against because it requires the
                determination of which data elements can go into the existing stated definition vs
                which elements will need new/ different patterns and semantics. </para>
            <para>In this step, the properties of concepts that need to be represented make the
                concept unique, i.e., what are the underlying properties that make one concept in
                the model different from another, need to be identified. </para>
            <para>The stated definition pattern is represented below along with the meaning and
                purpose concepts.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Stated Definition Pattern</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center">Stated Definition Pattern</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>Descriptum</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Semantic Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>Logical Definition</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center">Field 1: Logical Definition</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Meaning</entry>
                            <entry>EL++ Stated Terminological Axioms</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Purpose</entry>
                            <entry>Logical Definition</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Field Type</entry>
                            <entry>DiTree</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table>
                <title>Stated Definition Meaning and Purpose Concepts</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern Field</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Semantic Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Descriptum</entry>
                            <entry>The semantic meaning for the EL++ patterns</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Logical Definition
                                Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Logical Definition</entry>
                            <entry>The semantic value describing the purpose of the stated and
                                inferred terminological axioms. </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Logical Definition
                                Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>EL++ Stated Terminological Axioms</entry>
                            <entry>The stated relationships that uniquely define a concept in EL++
                                description logic.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Logical Definition </emphasis><emphasis
                                    role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>DiTree</entry>
                            <entry>A display field that references a graph obtained from an
                                undirected tree by replacing each undirected edge by two directed
                                edges with opposite directions.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>In cases where the data set is predefined, like SNOMED CT® or RxNORM, the OWL
                Description Logic String is provided which is used and transformed into the EL++
                Stated Terminological Axioms. When creating a new model, the following properties of
                EL++ Terminological Axioms must be investigated to see how to describe the
                uniqueness of the concepts being modeled. </para>
            <para>The stated definition child concepts are listed below.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Stated Definition Children Concepts</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Children Concept </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Implication
                                    Set</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Implication Set </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that indicate something has an
                                implication. Not necessarily or sufficient but implicated.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry ><emphasis role="bold">Necessary Set </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that is always true of a concept.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Property Set</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that are non-defining and are not used by
                                a description logic classifier.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sufficient Set </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>A set of relationships that differentiate a concept and its
                                subtypes from all other concepts. A concept that contains at least
                                one set of necessary and sufficient conditions is considered
                                defined.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold"
                                    >Roles</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role group </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>An association between a set of attribute or axiom value pairs
                                that causes them to be considered together within a concept
                                definition or post-coordinated expression.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>It is an abstract representation of a high-level role for a
                                therapeutic medicinal product; the concepts are not intended to
                                describe a detailed indication for therapeutic use nor imply that
                                therapeutic use is appropriate in all clinical situations.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role Type</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Refers to a concept that represents a particular kind of
                                relationship that can exist between two entities. It defines the
                                specific function or responsibility that one entity plays in
                                relation to another.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role Value</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>The Concept referred to by the is-a axiom relationship or the
                                axiom role relationship</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Is a </emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Designates the parent child relationship</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>To understand how the Stated Definitions Semantic has been modeled, examples of
                terminology snippets from SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, RxNorm, and LIDR are provided below.
                As the following sections walk through modeling the Stated Definitions Semantic,
                these snippets will be referred to as examples for how to model certain
                fields.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Example 1: SNOMED
                    CT®</title>
            
            <para>The example in the below screenshots, shows SNOMED Axiom example and then the
                Axiom expression that will be used to show how the data set was represented using
                the Stated Definitions Semantics. </para>
            <para>Source: <link
                    xlink:href="https://browser.loincsnomed.org/?perspective=full&amp;conceptId1=413839001&amp;edition=MAIN/LOINC/2023-10-15&amp;release=&amp;languages=en"
                    >https://browser.LOINC®snomed.org/?perspective=full&amp;conceptId1=413839001&amp;edition=MAIN/LOINC®/2023-10-15&amp;release=&amp;languages=en</link><figure
                    xml:id="SNOMEDExampleOWLExpression">
                    <title>SNOMED CT® Axiom Example for OWL Expression</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/SNOMED%20Example%20OWL%20Expression.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="SNOMEDExampleOWLExpression2">
                    <title>SNOMED CT® Example OWL Expression</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/SNOMED%20Example%20OWL%20Expression2.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 2:
                    LOINC®</title>
            
            <para>LOINC® does not have OWL String representation. However, the following information
                shown below shows the data from LOINC® that was used to represent LOINC® using the
                Tinkar Stated Definitions Semantics.</para>
            <para>Source: <link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3"
                    >https://LOINC®.org/search/?t=1&amp;s=7364-3</link></para>
            <para><figure>
                    <title>LOINC®Example OWL Expression</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/LOINC%20Description%20Data%20Example.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>Determine Description Logic</title>
                <para>Description logic is an attempt to represent and characterize classes of
                    objects and the relationships between them. SNOMED CT, for example, uses
                    description logic that corresponds to the EL++ language to define Stated and
                    Inferred relationships and axioms. </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Given that all source files differ, not all contain OWL Description
                            Logic. (If they do contain an OWL Description Logic String, it should be
                            utilized to avoid manually creating another string.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Revisiting the examples provided in section 3.4, the following representations
                    and/or gaps were identified:</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Description Logic Example</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 1: SNOMED
                                    CT®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Utilization of the owlExpression column allows for the
                                        representation of the field using the Tinkar description
                                        logic. This string can be imported using EL++ Description
                                        Logic, leading to the generation of Stated Axioms.</para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 2: LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>LOINC® lacks an OWL String representation unless SNOMED
                                        CT®-LOINC® collaboration files are used, but these files
                                        lack completeness. Documentation reveals six main parts
                                        comprising a LOINC® Code</para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Component</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Property</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Time</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>System</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Scale</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Method</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                    <para>Part definitions from LOINC® are treated as "Roles" in the
                                        stated definition. "Role Type" corresponds to one of the six
                                        parts above. "Role Value" corresponds to the Concept
                                        representation of the value</para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>To represent the data in the Stated Definitions
                                                Semantics, create a new Concept for each main LOINC®
                                                Part, and a new Concept for each unique value for
                                                each of the six parts so they can be assigned in the
                                                LOINC® Code Role</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>In addition to these six parts, there needs to be
                                                an “Is A” relationship to designate the parent
                                                Concept. In the SNOMED CT®-LOINC® Collaboration, all
                                                LOINC® Concepts are listed as a child of “Observable
                                                Entity”. So all LOINC® Codes will have an “Is A ->
                                                Observable Entity” relationship.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 3: RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>In the RxNorm OWL release file, the OWL Syntax literal
                                        string row can be used to represent the Tinkar description
                                        logic field in the Stated Definitions Semantics.</para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>“EquivalentClasses(:90708001
                                                ObjectIntersectionOf(:64572001
                                                ObjectSomeValuesFrom(:609096000
                                                ObjectSomeValuesFrom(:363698007
                                                :64033007))))”</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Example 4: LIDR</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>LIDR does not have an OWL String representation so one
                                        must be created based on properties that uniquely define a
                                        device. Based on the Data Provided, there are:</para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Manufacturer</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Labeler</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                    <para>These are treated as different “Roles” in the stated
                                        definition. “Role Type” corresponds to whomever the device
                                        was “Manufactured By” or “Labeled By”. The “Role Value” will
                                        be the Concept representing the Manufacturer or
                                        Labeler.</para>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>To represent the data in the Stated Definition
                                                Semantics, create a new Concept for each unique
                                                Manufacturer and Labeler so they can be assigned to
                                                the device</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>In addition to these two parts, there needs to be
                                                an “IsA” relationship to designate the parent
                                                Concept. To create device Concepts in the LIDR Data,
                                                a new Concept “Device” is created. Now all the
                                                Device Concepts will have an “Is A -> Device”
                                                relationship. </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </section>
        </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 4: LIDR</title>
                <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows the LIDR Data file that is used to
                    show how the data was represented using the Stated Definitions Semantics.
                        <figure xml:id="LIDRTestKitDeviceExample">
                        <title>LIDR Test Kit Device Example</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/LIDR%20Test%20Kit%20Device%20Example.svg"
                                    scale="70" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example 3: RxNorm</title>
                <para>The example in the below screenshot, shows the RxNorm OWL file that isfigur
                    used to show how the data was represented using the Stated Definitions
                    Semantics.</para>
                <para>Source File: <link
                        xlink:href="https://lhncbc.nlm.nih.gov/RxNav/news/RxNorm-in-OWL.html"
                        >https://lhncbc.nlm.nih.gov/RxNav/news/RxNorm-in-OWL.html</link></para>
                <para>
                    <figure xml:id="RxNormExampleOWLExpression">
                        <title>RxNorm Example OWL Expression</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="images/RxNorm%20Example%20OWL%20Expression.svg"
                                    scale="70" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Create New Patterns</title>
            <para>Once the current patterns are analyzed and representation using Tinkar is
                determined, there may be some outlying data that still needs to be extended into new
                Patterns in the Tinkar model. In this section, the steps for creating new patterns
                will be reviewed.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Filter for Data Elements associated to Concepts</title>
                <para>Start by filtering data elements that are associated with the concept being
                    modeled first. In other words, start with only the data elements that are
                    associated to the concept being modeled and are not describing other data
                    elements in the file rather than the concept itself. Because semantics
                    refer/point to any component (any concept, pattern, or semantic), start with the
                    patterns that refer/point to the concepts being modeled. </para>
                <section>
                    <title>Example 1: SNOMED CT ®</title>
                    <para>In SNOMED there are descriptions and dialects. Descriptions are the
                        patterns/semantics that are created and modeled first since they point to
                        the actual concepts (semantic referring to a concept) themselves while
                        Dialects refer/point to those Descriptions (semantic referring to a
                        semantic).</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Example 2: LOINC ® </title>
                    <para>In LOINC®we have a data element for STATUS. This directly describes an
                        attribute to a LOINC®Concept. However there are additional data elements:
                        STATUS_REASON, STATUS_TEXT, and CHANGE_REASON_PUBLIC. These 3 additional
                        data elements don’t directly describe attributes of the LOINC®Concept
                        itself, but are descriptive attributes of the STATUS. </para>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Group by Similar Data Elements </title>
                <para>Data fields with similar elements should be grouped together. Meaning, that
                    elements that seem similar purposes and occur at the same frequency should be
                    grouped together in a Pattern. They do not always have to have the same values
                    across concepts. Once the related concepts are represented, these groupings are
                    going to become new patterns. </para>
                <section>
                    <title>Example 1: RxNorm</title>
                    <para>In RxNorm, HUMAN_DRUG and PRESCRIBABLE are two data elements that are
                        closely related and seen together, but it’s not expected for them to occur
                        with a field like VET_DRUG. </para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> In this case to add these 3 data elements, there would need to be
                                2 different patterns <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>HUMAN_DRUG + PRESCRIBABLE</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>VET_DRUG</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist></para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Example 2: LIDR</title>
                    <para>In LIDR we have data elements like the Instrument Equipment Device, all
                        six LOINC®parts (Component, Property, Time, System, Scale, and Method), and
                        a Test Ordered and Test Performed LOINC®Code. The Instrument Equipment
                        Device is the only data elements that can sometimes not exist in the cases
                        of a take home test for example. So, we need a separate pattern for this
                        data element and add a semantic to depending on if there is data present or
                        not.</para>
                    <para>For the other six LOINC®parts and the two LOINC®Codes, if we look at the
                        occurrences of them, we see that there are 4 of the parts (Property, Time,
                        Scale, and Method) as well as the Test Ordered LOINC®Code that always exist
                        once. For the remaining elements (System, Component, and Test Performed
                        LOINC®Code), they can exist one or more times with different values for the
                        same test. Because of this the design needs to be able to account for these
                        situations and relationships so they are separated into two different
                        patterns: the Diagnostic Device Pattern, and the Test Performed
                        Pattern.</para>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Determine Field Types</title>
                <para>Once the new properties are grouped into the new patterns that need to be
                    modeled, each data element will be treated as a field type. For each field, it
                    needs to be determined how to represent the field in the model. A list of field
                    types is below:</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Field Types</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component Field </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A display field type that references a concept ID.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component ID List </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A display field that references an ordered list of Concept
                                    IDs.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component ID Set Field
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A display field that references an unordered list of Concept
                                    IDs.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">DiGraph Filed </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A display field that references a di-graph whose edges are
                                    ordered pairs of vertices. Each edge can be followed from one
                                    vertex to another vertex.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">DiTree Field </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A display field that references a graph obtained from an
                                    undirected tree by replacing each undirected edge by two
                                    directed edges with opposite directions.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Float Field </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Represents values as high-precision fractional
                                    values.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Integer Field </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A data type that represents some range of mathematical
                                    integers</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">String </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A sequence of characters, either as a literal constant or as
                                    a variable. Strings could be used to represent terms from code
                                    systems or URLs, textual definitions, etc.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>The most common field types to use are the Component Field, Component Set
                    Field, and String Field. Things to consider:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If it’s a unique element that can vary significantly between concepts
                            and rarely has a chance of two concepts having the same value, then it
                            should be treated as a String or something similar.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the value for the data element might be common across different
                            concepts that are being modeled, than it should be considered to make
                            that value its own concept and treat this field as a component field
                            that’s going to have a value of that concept.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If there could be multiple values for the data element that can be
                            shared or common across different concepts, then a Component Set Field
                            can be used, and all the values can be modeled as different concepts and
                            be in the “set”.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <section>
                    <title>Example 1: Diagnostic Device Pattern</title>
                    <para>For this example, Laboratory InVitro Diagnostic Repository (LIDR) is used
                        to explain how to approach creating new patterns. Starting by grouping
                        together similar concepts as outlined in Section 2.6.1, there are 5 data
                        elements that can be grouped together and applied to a Device
                        concept.</para>
                    <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Test Ordered</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Method</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Time</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Scale</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Property</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                    <para>Together they describe a Device concept in terms of it being a Diagnostic
                        Device in which a Test is ordered. The new pattern's meaning and purpose is
                        to show how a test being ordered for a diagnostic purpose should be coded in
                        a health system. The field values are LOINC®Parts that describe the
                        properties of the device. </para>
                    <para>When looking at the Field Types for the 5 data elements, they are all
                        LOINC®Parts. In defining a Test that would get ordered and have a LOINC®Code
                        assigned, there would only be 1 possible code which would translate to one
                        possible value for each property. It is possible to re-use these concepts
                        created by the LOINC®import and treat each field type as concept fields and
                        point to the corresponding concepts in the semantic values. The resulting
                        pattern format is shown below. In this example, a new concept was created
                        called “Test Ordered” to assign as the meaning and purpose of the field and
                        the pattern itself. The others assigned to the meaning and purpose can be
                        pulled from the LOINC®Import.</para>
                    <table>
                        <title>Diagnostic Device Pattern</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold"
                                            >Diagnostic Device Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Semantic Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Test Ordered</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Semantic Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Test Ordered</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Field
                                            1</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Test Ordered</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Test Ordered</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Concept Field</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Field
                                            2</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Method</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Method</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Concept Field</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Field
                                            3</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Time</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Time</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Concept Field</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Field
                                            4</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Scale</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Scale</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Concept Field</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Field
                                            5</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Property</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Property</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Concept Field</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>Example 2: Test Performed Pattern</title>
                    <para>For this next example, a pattern was needed to describe the properties of
                        a test being performed in LIDR. These properties are not specific to the
                        device like in the Diagnostic Device Semantic but are properties of a test
                        being performed by that device. Therefore, this semantic would be a semantic
                        of a diagnostic device semantic, not of the device concept. When looking at
                        it in this manner there could be multiple different tests being performed
                        for a single ordered test. Therefore, there could be multiple Test Performed
                        semantics to a single Diagnostic Device semantic.</para>
                    <para>When looking at the LIDR Information Requirements, the data elements to
                        include in this pattern/semantic, the following fields were analyzed:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Test Performed</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Analyte</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Target</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Specimen</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>These data elements all describe how a test being performed in a health
                        system should be properly coded. Since there is only one test performed per
                        semantic, the Test Performed and Analyte Fields are treated as Concept
                        Fields. There is only one concept value they should point to. However, for
                        Targets and Specimen, there could be multiple possible concepts each
                        describing a case for how to properly code the test. For these fields
                        component set fields are used. The resulting pattern format created is shown
                        below. </para>
                    <para>In this example, a new concept for each unique meaning and purpose did not
                        exist so they would be created. Additionally, when creating a semantic of
                        this pattern, all Field Values must be created before assignment (Analyte,
                        Target, Specimen). The Test Performed Values reference LOINC®Codes that are
                        available through importing LOINC.</para>
                    <table>
                        <title>Test Performed Pattern</title>
                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Test
                                            Performed Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Semantic Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Test Performed</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Semantic Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Test Performed</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Field
                                            1</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Test Performed</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Test Performed</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Concept Field</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Field
                                            2</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Analyte</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Analyte</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Concept Field</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Field
                                            3</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Target</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Target</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Concept ID Set Field </entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2" align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Field
                                            4</emphasis></entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Specimen</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Specimen</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field Type</emphasis></entry>
                                    <entry>Concept ID Set Field</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Build Data Model and Starter Data</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The Data Model is created using a modeling tool, mapping out the
                            patterns, semantics, and concepts</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Examples of current data models will be added here with
                            descriptions.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Validating Models </title>
            <para>To ensure the creation of a stable and reliable model, each model must go through
                a validation process. The validation process includes two key roles:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Domain Subject Matter Experts (SMEs)</emphasis>
                            who can provide critical feedback based on their specialized
                            knowledge.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Tinkar Reference Modelers </emphasis>the people who
                        initially build and document the model they create and additional modelers
                        who can provide insight on ways to reuse current Tinkar components and be
                        sure that any components that are reused, do so correctly.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The ultimate goal of this validation process is to achieve consensus on a stable
                model that all relevant parties agree upon, providing a solid foundation that
                ensures the model's accuracy and reliability for future developments.</para>
            <para>There are three key steps when initiating the validation process: Peer review
                sessions, reviewing the model with the domain SME(s) and having review cycles, and
                coming to a group consensus on the final state of the model.</para>
            <para>
                <figure xml:id="ValidatingModelsProcessFlow">
                    <title>Validating Models Process Flow</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/Validating%20Models%20Process%20Flow.svg"
                                scale="70" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>When the initial model is complete, modelers should work to collect and create
                documentation of the model. This documentation should include the logical data model
                drawing and documentation of all modeling decisions including Tinkar Patterns,
                Concepts, and Semantics that were reused and new Concepts, Patterns, and/or
                Semantics that were created. Rationale behind the decisions made should also be
                included. They should also work with other modelers to have peer review sessions to
                discuss the modeling decisions and rationale and come to agreed upon decisions about
                the model.</para>
            <para>Once the initial model is complete, documentation is gathered, and the model has
                been peer reviewed, the modelers should review the model with the domain SME(s). The
                domain SME(s) should ensure the information requirements are met and the information
                is modeled in an agreed upon way. All rationale for decisions, any questions the
                modelers may have, and also possible options to how to model certain things should
                be given to the domain SME(s) to review.</para>
            <para>Feedback gathered from the domain SME(s) should be captured and incorporated into
                the model. The modelers should then review the model again with the SMEs. The
                feedback process may continue to go back and forth for some time, but eventually
                when all feedback has been discussed and implemented where applicable, the model
                should be finalized, and all documentation of the changes and history of the model
                should be shared.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Model Documentation</title>
            <para>Throughout the modeling process, modelers should capture documentation that
                describes the rationale for decisions made when modeling, create the starter data
                set, and create the logical data model. Table 24 contains descriptions for the
                different types of artifacts modelers should be able to provide once the modeling is
                complete:</para>
            <para>
                        <table>
                            <title>Common Tinkar Documents</title>
                                <tgroup cols="2">
                                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                                    <tbody>
                                        <row>
                                            <entry>Artifact</entry>
                                            <entry>Description</entry>
                                        </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold"> Model Rationale</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Documentation that was captured during the modeling process
                                    that helps explain the reasoning behind modeling decisions, any
                                    assumptions made, and the decisions made for fields in the data
                                    set that are being represented using Tinkar should be captured.
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Starter Data Set</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A list of any new Tinkar components that should be created to
                                    represent the data set.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Data Model</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>A logical model representation of any new
                                    patterns/semantics/concepts.</entry>
                            </row>
                                    </tbody>
                                </tgroup>
                            </table>
                        
                
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Appendix</title>
        <section>
            <title>Glossary</title>
            <para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Term</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Reference</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Semantic</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Relating to or involving data which is structured and
                                        tagged according to its meaning or intention, allowing it to
                                        be read directly by computers.</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Semantic, adj. meanings, etymology and more | Oxford English
                                    Dictionary (oed.com)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>LOINC®</entry>
                                <entry>Logical Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes</entry>
                                <entry><link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/">Home –
                                    LOINC</link></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>SNOMED CT®</entry>
                                <entry>Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms</entry>
                                <entry><link xlink:href="https://www.snomed.org/">Home | SNOMED
                                        International</link></entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Tinkar Starter Data (in Alphabetical Order)</title>
            <para>
                <table>
                    <title>Tinkar Starter Data</title>
                    <tgroup cols="5">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                        <colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Fully Qualified Name</entry>
                                <entry>Synonym</entry>
                                <entry>Definition</entry>
                                <entry>Origins</entry>
                                <entry>Destinations</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Acceptable (foundation metadata
                                        concept)</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                                <entry>Specifies that a description is acceptable, but not preferred
                                    within a language or dialect.</entry>
                                <entry>DESCRIPTION_ACCEPTABILITY</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Active status </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Active</entry>
                                <entry>Concept used to represent a status for components that are
                                    active.</entry>
                                <entry>STATUS_VALUE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Author</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Author</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Canceled status </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Canceled </entry>
                                <entry>Concept used to represent a status for components that are
                                    canceled</entry>
                                <entry>STATUS_VALUE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Chinese Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component field</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Component field </entry>
                                <entry>A display field type that references a Concept ID.</entry>
                                <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component Id list</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Component Id list </entry>
                                <entry>A display field that references an ordered list of Concept
                                    IDs.</entry>
                                <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Component Id set
                                    field</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Component Id set </entry>
                                <entry>A display field that references an unordered list of Concept
                                    IDs.</entry>
                                <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Czech Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Danish Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Decription not case sensitive
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Case insensitive</entry>
                                <entry>Value which designates character as not sensitive for a given
                                    description </entry>
                                <entry>DESCRIPTION_CASE_SIGNIFICANCE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Definition description type
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Definition</entry>
                                <entry>Semantic value describing the description type for the
                                    description Pattern is a definition</entry>
                                <entry>DESCRIPTION_TYPE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                                <entry>Human readable text for a concept</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description acceptability
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Description acceptability </entry>
                                <entry> Whether a given human readable text for a Concept is
                                    permissible </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">ACCEPTABLE;
                                    PREFERRED</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description case sensitive
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Case sensitive </entry>
                                <entry>Assumes the description is dependent on capitalization </entry>
                                <entry>DESCRIPTION_CASE_SIGNIFICANCE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description case significance
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Description case significance </entry>
                                <entry>Specifies how to handle the description text interms of case
                                    sensitivity </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">DESCRIPTION_CASE_SENSITIVE;
                                        DESCRIPTION_NOT_CASE_SENSITIVE</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Pattern </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Description Pattern</entry>
                                <entry>Contains all metadata and human readable text that describes
                                    the Concept </entry>
                                <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description Semantic
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Description Semantic </entry>
                                <entry>Purpose and meaning for the description Pattern and dialect
                                    Patterns </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description type </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Description type </entry>
                                <entry>Specifying what type of description it is i.e. is it fully
                                    qualified or regular and etc. </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">DEFINITION_DESCRIPTION_TYPE;
                                        FULLY_QUALIFIED_NAME_DESCRIPTION_TYPE;
                                        REGULAR_NAME_DESCRIPTION_TYPE</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Descriptum </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Descriptum</entry>
                                <entry>The Semantic meaning for the EL++ Patterns </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Development path </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Development path </entry>
                                <entry>A path that specifies that the components are currently under
                                    development</entry>
                                <entry>PATH</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Dialect</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Dialect</entry>
                                <entry><link
                                        xlink:href="https://www.google.com/search?safe=active&amp;sca_esv=2802dad21c2aa82f&amp;rlz=1C1GCEA_enUS1093US1093&amp;q=peculiar&amp;si=AKbGX_qNq0Y8zql7SxzZAf2-HTTOVobuSeLnlL2tVO9M2fGNfebMB7TKBhol7Sqwuay6sY3kGrSwFLy9ZcG8n0EzEGwsbKROZpu_7GoFc3oiudVKoMYiSQE%3D&amp;expnd=1"
                                        >Specifies the dialect of the language.</link></entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">ENGLISH_DIALECT</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">DiGraph field </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Instant/ DiGraph</entry>
                                <entry>A display field that references a di-graph whose edges are
                                    ordered pairs of vertices. Each edge can be followed from one
                                    vertex to another vertex.</entry>
                                <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Display Fields </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Display fields </entry>
                                <entry>Captures the human readable terms</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">COMPONENT_FIELD;
                                        COMPONENT_ID_LIST_FIELD; COMPONENT_ID_SET_FIELD;
                                        DIGRAPH_FIELD; DITREE_FIELD; FLOAT_FIELD; INTEGER_FIELD;
                                        STRING</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">DiTree field </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>DiTree</entry>
                                <entry>A display field that references a graph obtained from an
                                    undirected tree by replacing each undirected edge by two
                                    directed edges with opposite directions.</entry>
                                <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Dutch Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">EL++ Inferred Axioms
                                    Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Inferred definition pattern</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">EL++ Inferred terminological axioms
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>EL++ Inferred terminological axioms</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">NECESSARY_SET; SUFFICIENT_SET;
                                        IMPLICATION_SET; ROLE; ROLE_GROUP</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">EL++ Stated Axioms
                                    Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Stated definition pattern</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">EL++ Stated terminological axioms
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>EL++ Stated terminological axioms </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">NECESSARY_SET; SUFFICIENT_SET;v
                                        IMPLICATION_SET; ROLE; ROLE_GROUP</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">English Dialect </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>English Dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Specifies the dialect of theEnglish language</entry>
                                <entry>DIALECT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">US_ENGLISH_DIALECT;
                                        GB_ENGLISH_DIALECT</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">English Language </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>English language </entry>
                                <entry>Value for description language</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Existential
                                    restriction</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Existential restriction</entry>
                                <entry> Existential restrictions describe objects that participate
                                    in at least one relationship along a specified property to
                                    objects of a specified class.</entry>
                                <entry>ROLE_OPERATOR</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Float field </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Float field </entry>
                                <entry> Represents values as high-precision fractional
                                    values.</entry>
                                <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">French Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Fully qualified name description type
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Fully quailified name </entry>
                                <entry>Fully qualified name is a description that uniquely
                                    identifies and differentiates it from other Concepts with
                                    similar descriptions</entry>
                                <entry>DESCRIPTION_TYPE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">GB Dialect Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>GB Dialect Pattern</entry>
                                <entry>Particular form of language specific form of English
                                    language, particular to Great Britian</entry>
                                <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">German Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Great Britian English dialect
                                    </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>GB English dialect / GB English</entry>
                                <entry>Great Britain: English Langauge reference set </entry>
                                <entry>ENGLISH_DIALECT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Identifier Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Identifier Pattern </entry>
                                <entry>An identifier Pattern is used to identity a Concept which
                                    containts the identifier source and the actual value</entry>
                                <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Identifier Source </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Identifier source</entry>
                                <entry>An identifier used to label the identity of a unique
                                    component.</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold"
                                        >UNIVERSALLY_UNIQUE_IDENTIFIER</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Implication set</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Implication set </entry>
                                <entry>A set of relationships that indicate something has an
                                    implication. Not necessarily or sufficient but
                                    implicated.</entry>
                                <entry>EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                    EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Inactive Status </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Inactive</entry>
                                <entry>Concept used to represent a status for components that are no
                                    longer active</entry>
                                <entry>STATUS_VALUE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Inferred Navigation</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Inferred Navigation</entry>
                                <entry>The origins and destinations for Concepts based on the
                                    reasoner generated inferred terminological axioms </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Inferred Navigation
                                    Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Inferred Navigation Pattern</entry>
                                <entry>A Pattern specifying the origins and destinations for
                                    Concepts based on the inferred terminological axioms </entry>
                                <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Integer Field </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Integer field</entry>
                                <entry>A data type that represents some range of mathematical
                                    integers</entry>
                                <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Integrated Knowledge
                                        Management</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Tinkar root Concept </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">MODEL_CONCEPT; PATTERN; STATUS_VALUE;
                                        USER; MODULE; PATH</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Irish Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Is-a</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Is a</entry>
                                <entry>Designates the parent child relationship</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Italian Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Korean Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Language </entry>
                                <entry>Specifies the language of the description text.</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">ENGLISH_LANGUAGE;
                                        SPANISH_LANGUAGE</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Language for
                                    Description</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Language for Description</entry>
                                <entry>The Semantic value indicating which language is used in the
                                    description text</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Lithuanian Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Logical Definition</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Logical Definition</entry>
                                <entry>The Semantic value describing the purpose of the stated and
                                    inferred terminological axioms. </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Master path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Master path </entry>
                                <entry>A default path for components</entry>
                                <entry>PATH</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Meaning </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Meaning </entry>
                                <entry>The interpretation or explanation field for a
                                    pattern/Semantics </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Model concept</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Model concept</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">DESCRIPTION; DESCRIPTION_ACCEPTABILITY;
                                        DESCRIPTION_CASE_SIGNIFICANCE; DESCRIPTION_SEMANTIC;
                                        DESCRIPTION_TYPE; DESCRIPTUM; DIALECT; DISPLAY_FIELDS;
                                        EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                        EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                        IDENTIFIER_SOURCE; INFERRED_NAVIGATION; IS_A; LANGUAGE;
                                        LANGUAGE_FOR_DESCRIPTION; LOGICAL_DEFINITION; MEANING;
                                        PHENOMENON; RELATIONSHIP_DESTINATION; RELATIONSHIP_ORIGIN;
                                        STATED_NAVIGATION; TEXT_FOR_DESCRIPTION;
                                    PURPOSE</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Module</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">PRIMORDIAL_MODULE</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Necessary set</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Necessary set </entry>
                                <entry>A set of relationships that is always true of a
                                    Concept.</entry>
                                <entry>EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                    EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Path</entry>
                                <entry>A set of assets under version control that can be managed
                                    distinctly from other assets. Paths “branch” from other paths
                                    when established, and can be “merged” with other paths as
                                    well.</entry>
                                <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">DEVELOPMENT_PATH; MASTER_PATH;
                                        PRIMORDIAL_PATH; SANDBOX_PATH</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Pattern</entry>
                                <entry>A Pattern is a set of display fields and values that can be
                                    asserted about a concept</entry>
                                <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">DESCRIPTION_PATTERN;
                                        GB_DIALECT_PATTERN; IDENTIFIER_PATTERN;
                                        INFERRED_NAVIGATION_PATTERN; STATED_NAVIGATION_PATTERN;
                                        US_DIALECT_PATTERN</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Phenomenon</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Phenomenon</entry>
                                <entry>A unique thought, fact, or circumstance</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Polish Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Preferred</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Preferred </entry>
                                <entry>Specifies that a description is preferred within a language
                                    or dialect. There will be one preferred description for each
                                    description type.</entry>
                                <entry>DESCRIPTION_ACCEPTABILITY</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Primordial module</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Primordial module</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>MODULE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Primordial path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Primordial path</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>PATH</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Primordial status</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Primordial </entry>
                                <entry>Concept used to represent a status for components that have
                                    not yet been released and exist in their most basic
                                    form.</entry>
                                <entry>STATUS_VALUE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Purpose</entry>
                                <entry>The reason for which a Tinkar value in a Pattern was created
                                    or for which it exist. </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Regular name description
                                        type</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Regular name desription type </entry>
                                <entry>There may be descriptions/synonyms marked as
                                    “regular.”</entry>
                                <entry>DESCRIPTION_TYPE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Relationship
                                    destination</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Relationship destination</entry>
                                <entry>Signifies path to child Concepts which are more specific than
                                    the Tinkar term</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Relationship origin</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Relationship origin</entry>
                                <entry>Signifies path to parent Concepts which are more general than
                                    the Tinkar term</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Role</entry>
                                <entry>Is an abstract representation of a high-level role for a
                                    therapeutic medicinal product; the Concepts are not intended to
                                    describe a detailed indication for therapeutic use nor imply
                                    that therapeutic use is appropriate in all clinical
                                    situations.</entry>
                                <entry>ROLE_GROUP; EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                    EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">ROLE_TYPE; ROLE_OPERATOR;
                                        ROLE_RESTRICTION</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role group</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Role group</entry>
                                <entry>An association between a set of attribute or axiom value
                                    pairs that causes them to be considered together within a
                                    Concept definition or postcoordinated expression.</entry>
                                <entry>EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                    EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">ROLE</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role operator</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Role operator </entry>
                                <entry>Concept that is used to describe universal vs existential
                                    restrictions.</entry>
                                <entry>ROLE</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">UNIVERSAL_RESTRICTION;
                                        EXISTENTIAL_RESTRICTION</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role restriction</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Role value</entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>ROLE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Role type</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Role type</entry>
                                <entry>Refers to a Concept that represents a particular kind of
                                    realtionship that can exist between two entities. It defines the
                                    specific function or responsibility that one entity plays in
                                    relation to another. </entry>
                                <entry>ROLE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Russian Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sandbox path</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Sandbox path</entry>
                                <entry>A path for components under testing.</entry>
                                <entry>PATH</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Spanish langauge</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Spanish language </entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Stated Navigation</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Stated Navigation</entry>
                                <entry>The origins and destinations for Concepts based on the
                                    reasoner generated stated terminological axioms </entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Stated Navigation
                                    Pattern</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Stated Navigation Pattern</entry>
                                <entry>A Pattern specifying the origins and destinations for
                                    Concepts based on the stated terminological axioms </entry>
                                <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Status value</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Status </entry>
                                <entry>The status of the STAMP Coordinate(Active, Cancelled,
                                    Inactive, Primordial)</entry>
                                <entry>ROOT_VERTEX</entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">ACTIVE_STATE; CANCELED_STATE;
                                        INACTIVE_STATE; PRIMORDIAL_STATE;
                                    WITHDRAWN_STATE</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">String</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>String</entry>
                                <entry>a sequence of characters, either as a literal constant or as
                                    a variable. Strings could be used to represent terms from code
                                    systems or URLs, textual definitions, etc.</entry>
                                <entry>DISPLAY_FIELDS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sufficient set</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Sufficient set </entry>
                                <entry>A set of relationships that differentiate a Concept and its
                                    subtypes from all other Concepts. A Concept that contains at
                                    least one set of necessary and sufficient conditions is
                                    considered defined.</entry>
                                <entry>EL_PLUS_PLUS_STATED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS;
                                    EL_PLUS_PLUS_INFERRED_TERMINOLOGICAL_AXIOMS</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Swedish Language</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>Value for the description language dialect</entry>
                                <entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Text for description</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Text</entry>
                                <entry>Captures the human readable text for a description in
                                    Komet</entry>
                                <entry>MODEL_CONCEPT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">United States of America English
                                        dialect</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>US English dialect </entry>
                                <entry>Particular form of language specific form of English
                                    language, particular to US</entry>
                                <entry>ENGLISH_DIALECT</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Universal
                                    Restriction</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Universal restriction</entry>
                                <entry> Universal restrictions constrain the relationships along a
                                    given property to Concepts that are members of a specific
                                    class.</entry>
                                <entry>ROLE_OPERATOR</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold"
                                        >UNIVERSALLY_UNIQUE_IDENTIFIER</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>UUID</entry>
                                <entry>A universally unique identifier that uniquely represents a
                                    Concept in Tinkar </entry>
                                <entry>IDENTIFIER_SOURCE</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">US Dialect Pattern </emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>US Dialect Pattern </entry>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry>PATTERN</entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Withdrawn state</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Withdrawn state</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept used to represent a status for
                                        components that are no longer active</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">STATUS_VALUE</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry/>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Archive</title>
        <para>From the OWL Expressions, a set of stated relationships or axioms are automatically
            created through a reasoner. An alternative to having the description logic string can be
            to simply create the stated definition axioms inside of a Tinkar application like Komet
            directly. Here are the Stated Definition Axioms for each example:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Example 1: SNOMED</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a “Sufficient Set”</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add an Is-A relationship to “Disease”:</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be “Finding Site”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be “Kidney Structure” </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Example 2: LOINC</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Create a “Necessary Set”</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add an Is-A relationship to "Observable Entity”</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be “System”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be “Ser”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be “Component”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be “Festuca elatior Ab.IgG”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be “Property”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be “ACnc ”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be “Scale”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be “Qn”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add a new Role Group</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Add a Role</para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Type would be “Time”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Role Value would be “Pt”</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
    </chapter>
    

</book>
