<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Use Cases</title>
    <section>
        <title>Use Case: Komet Demo</title>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Use Case: Komet Applications</title>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Use Case: Considerations for Real World Data Interoperability and Data Agility in
            Patient Journey to Diagnosis for Emerging Acute and Chronic Infectious Diseases</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction to the Emerging Acute and Chronic Infectious Diseases Use
                Case</title>
            <para>Increased generation of real-world data (RWD) and real-world evidence (RWE) from
                personal health devices, electronic heath records (EHR), and other sources has
                fueled a new wave of advanced analytics and has proven to be critical when
                evaluating emerging health trends. [1] Digital health devices, over-the-counter
                (OTC) diagnostic tests, and other technologies are important sources of RWD and can
                be used as decision support tools. However, interoperability issues including
                challenges with data transmission, storage, retrieval, and aggregation must be
                addressed to support safe and effective use of the data. RWE can drive important
                insights into public health and predict emerging diseases, pandemics such as
                SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19), and other population health trends. Timely access to
                interoperable data is critical when developing guidance and improving patient care
                and outcomes. </para>
            <para>Clinical workflows are highly cited as rich sources for analysis of clinical
                decision-making support and process improvement. Clinical process modeling and
                workflows can be used to understand a clinician’s reasoning, understanding, and use
                of patient data. Workflows capture the thought process behind decision making, help
                visualize the process, and can be considered as a decision tree. [2] Certain
                workflows can be used to understand the clinical data life cycle. In Vankipuram et
                al., the authors use a clinical workflow analytics framework using radio-frequency
                identification (RFID) to identify three phases of data flow: transmission, analysis,
                and transformation. [3] In these studies, the authors highlight the benefits and
                potential use of analyzing workflows to improve patient care or enhance clinical
                decision support tools. Other workflow analyses incorporate predictive modeling to
                analyze and predict most efficient operating models that drive effective
                interventions. [4] Advanced analytics including artificial intelligence and other
                technologies are being explored in workflows. [5] However, advanced analytical
                outcomes are fully dependent on the data feeding into the system. </para>
            <para>Business Process Modeling and Notation (BPMN) is a diagram technique used to
                represent a flowchart of activities and decision processes and is beneficial to
                healthcare organizations seeking to implement process improvements. BPMN is a tool
                organizations use to evaluate clinical decision support systems, model clinical
                treatment protocols, and easily relay complex processes. BPMN is often used to model
                organizational or task related processes, but its use can be broadened to understand
                systemic flows of information. [6-8] As Kassim et al. point out in their systematic
                review, most BPMN focuses on clinical decision support but stops short of modeling
                patient healthcare trajectories and, with that, health information. [9]</para>
            <para>Existing approaches of clinical process modeling analyze the data but fail to
                explore data considerations such as data capture and transmission. The need for
                interoperable data is evident. In previous health emergencies, important sources of
                data were identified too late, and the use of those data was further delayed by
                incompatibilities in interoperability. Preparing federal agencies and public health
                authorities with RWE tools will facilitate early identification of potential
                pandemics and diseases and allow timely and well-informed decision making. To reach
                this level of preparedness, it is critical to understand where potential data are
                generated, stored, and transmitted in a clinical workflow.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Aims for the Emerging Acute and Chronic Infectious Diseases Use Case</title>
            <para>In this body of work, we aim to demonstrate the importance of an interoperable
                data system and downstream analytical scenarios through a use case for Long COVID.
                We propose that the methods and findings are not solely applicable to a use case for
                Long COVID and are reproducible for any emerging acute and chronic infectious
                disease use case. This use case presents a Long COVID workflow highlighting a
                patient’s journey from first onset of COVID-19 symptoms through a Long COVID
                diagnosis and describes how data are captured, transmitted, and aggregated in a way
                that can be generalized to other emerging acute and chronic infectious diseases.
                Through understanding of data generation, transmission, and analysis we can identify
                important information and trends and establish an ideal future state for the use of
                RWE. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 1: Document a Current State Long COVID Workflow
                    Depicting Data Loss </emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 2: Establish the Future State of Patient Care
                </emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 3: Establish the Future State Data Workflow
                </emphasis></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Emerging Acute and Chronic Infectious Diseases Use Case Background</title>
            <para>The COVID-19 pandemic drastically impacted healthcare, laboratory operations,
                pharmaceuticals, and patient care delivery. While extensive resources have been
                allocated to studying COVID-19 in support of vaccine development, public health
                policies, and treatment, the long-term symptoms and impacts of COVID-19 are not well
                known. Long COVID is a poorly understood condition associated with lasting health
                problems that persist past the typical symptomatic period after an initial COVID-19
                infection. While Long COVID is typically marked by longitudinal fatigue, respiratory
                issues, and brain fog, there is a growing pool of symptoms and complications. Health
                conditions, duration, and even test results can vary across Long COVID cases,
                leading to an inability to quickly diagnose Long COVID. Identifying Long COVID is
                further complicated by a variety of inaccurate, lost, or suboptimal data collection
                and reporting. Due to these difficulties, there is no diagnostic test available for
                Long COVID, and care providers often reach a Long COVID diagnosis by ruling out
                other diseases or disorders with similar symptoms. [10-14]</para>
            <para>A lack of comprehensive research, information, and clinical decision support (CDS)
                impacts providers’ ability to accurately recognize and diagnose Long COVID. The US
                Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and the Systemic Harmonization and
                Interoperability Enhancement for Lab Data (SHIELD) collaborative must have access to
                a substantial amount of data from a variety of sources to support improvements in
                patient care for Long COVID and other emerging acute and chronic infectious
                diseases. SHIELD is a public-private collaboration focused on improving
                interoperability of in vitro diagnostic data between institutions. [15] Test data
                from COVID-positive and COVID-negative patients with a wide range of symptoms
                provide critical data that need to be captured and analyzed in support of these
                efforts. These data must be comprehensive and contain all necessary elements to
                support efficient querying and use in research and CDS.</para>
            <para>This Long COVID use case helps advance our understanding of the health data
                ecosystem and the necessary data capture and agility to ensure safe and effective
                patient care. This workflow broadly represents and can be applied to other emerging
                acute and chronic infectious diseases in that it highlights the data gaps and
                opportunities for use of RWE. We propose a future state workflow and proactive
                approach where data sets are analyzed and signals are detected before a condition is
                known, thereby yielding health information systems that are safe, effective, and
                interoperable. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Methods to Develop the Emerging Acute and Chronic Infectious Diseases Use
                Case</title>
            <section>
                <title>Aim 1: Document a Current State Long COVID Workflow Depicting Data Loss </title>
                <para>The team developed the generalized Long COVID workflow depicted in Figure 1
                    highlighting the steps a patient takes throughout their diagnostic journey with
                    accompanying data generated at each step. The team gathered foundational Long
                    COVID research to establish a comprehensive list of widely accepted and
                    important data elements and data entry points for the workflow. [10-13] A
                    template form was created to gather input from the team members on these data
                    elements including actors, descriptions, triggers, pre and post conditions,
                    assumptions, and data fields, and eight team members independently documented
                    considerations in the workflow. Team members had varying professional
                    backgrounds including MD, NP, RN, Informaticist, Terminologists, HL7 Interface
                    Engineers, Public Health, and Systems Engineering. The team met to discuss the
                    exercise and highlight differing approaches in the team’s documentation and
                    considerations. Common themes were extracted and used in Visio to develop an
                    initial draft of a generalized Long COVID use case workflow schematic that was
                    iterated upon based on subject matter expert and key stakeholder input. The
                    workflow follows an inpatient and outpatient path and identifies common steps in
                    a patient’s diagnostic journey along with associated data to highlight
                    opportunities for more accurate and comprehensive data collection. Several
                    important data elements were identified including patient symptoms, medical
                    history, laboratory tests and orders, vaccination history, demographics, and
                    prescriptions, and it was noted whether those data are currently collected or
                    lost. </para>
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
                <para>INSERT GENERALIZED CURRENT STATE LONG COVID WORKFLOW</para><?oxy_custom_end?>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Aim 2: Establish the Future State of Patient Care</title>
                <para>Once a standardized general Long COVID diagnostic workflow schematic was
                    developed, the team honed in on the outpatient scenario to capture the patient
                    journey in greater detail. The team chose to focus on an outpatient scenario as
                    there is a larger propensity for data loss when the patient is not under the
                    continuous monitoring of inpatient care. This new BPMN schematic closely
                    examined the parallel paths that a patient in an outpatient setting could follow
                    before arriving at a Long COVID diagnosis to support improved CDS, patient care,
                    and data collection and usage. This resulted in an approximate current state
                    patient workflow as well as an idealized future state patient workflow with a
                    supplementary data flow schematic. Note that while these scenarios used Long
                    COVID as an inspiration, the underlying principles can be applied to any similar
                    emerging acute, chronic and infectious disease.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Scenario 1: Current State Outpatient Long COVID
                        Workflow</emphasis></para>
                <para>Scenario 1 details an expanded view of the workflow as patients begin their
                    journey to a Long COVID diagnosis through parallel paths. Step 1 demonstrates
                    the different reasons that could prompt a patient to take a COVID-19 test such
                    as notification of exposure from the health department, phone proximity
                    tracking, routine testing at work, prerequisite testing for travel, or feeling
                    symptomatic. The parallel actions are listed for each step of the process in in
                    the workflow schematic below in Figure 2. In this current state, there are
                    several points at which data are produced but not collected and therefore
                    lost.</para>
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
                <para>INSERT SCENARIO 1 CURRENT STATE OUTPATIENT FLOW</para><?oxy_custom_end?>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Scenario 2: Future State Outpatient Long COVID
                        Workflow</emphasis></para>
                <para>Scenario 2 explores an idealized future state for the outpatient workflow
                    depicted in Figure 3 that aims to minimize data loss. It should be noted that
                    there are only subtle changes to the patient-centric workflow, but there are
                    several points at which data are collected and stored, which, in turn, will
                    enable more streamlined care and a more complete picture of health for the
                    individual patient and the larger population. The collection, storage, and
                    transmission of data are detailed in Aim 3.</para>
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
                <para>INSERT SCENARIO 2 FUTURE STATE OUTPATIENT FLOW</para><?oxy_custom_end?>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Aim 3: Establish the Future State Data Workflow</title>
                <para>Building upon the Future State Outpatient Long COVID Workflow, the team worked
                    with subject matter experts in public health reporting, laboratory data systems,
                    and health informatics to identify points in the patient care workflow where
                    data are captured, where data capture could be improved, and resources or
                    technologies that could support the improved data capture. The team then
                    developed a separate schematic (Figure 4) to showcase an idealized flow of those
                    data; the workflow is framed around an OTC COVID-19 test trigger and showcases
                    how data should be captured, transmitted, stored, and prepared for downstream
                    analytical and secondary use. </para>
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
                <para>INSERT IDEALIZED FUTURE STATE DATA FLOW</para><?oxy_custom_end?>
                <para>An important consideration when developing this workflow was the inclusion of
                    enablers. Enablers serve to drive the best future state collection and use of
                    the data that are generated in the future state patient care workflow starting
                    with empowering or incentivizing the patient to report OTC test results and
                    stretching to accurate reporting of point of care (POC) orders and results. The
                    team expanded upon what data are collected and where the data are stored,
                    leading to a detailed schematic of how data are aggregated, transmitted, and
                    ultimately used. </para>
                <para>Privacy Preserving Record Linkage (PPRL), a way to maintain patient privacy
                    while collecting protected patient data and preserving data meaning across data
                    sets, was included as an important step between data storage and aggregation and
                    final use by the federal government. [16] Following PPRL, a loop was included in
                    the data aggregation step “Data with Idealized Structure and Fully Defined
                    Terminology” to include an opportunity for feedback and continual improvement of
                    data collection practices and standards. This RWE and analytic-based feedback
                    also informs questionnaire creators as they deploy updated questionnaires back
                    to the original data collectors and serves as an opportunity to implement best
                    practices and suggestions for further exploration. These loops are included to
                    showcase how data insights can provide real-time feedback and identify
                    opportunities for continual process improvements. The future state data workflow
                    concludes with transformed, normalized, and de-identified data in repositories
                    ready for secondary use across a variety of systems depending on content and
                    purpose. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Results from the Emerging Acute and Chronic Infectious Diseases Use Case</title>
            <section>
                <title>Aim 1: Document a Current State Long COVID Workflow Depicting Data Loss </title>
                <para>The team developed Figure 1, a generalized workflow that outlines a patient’s
                    journey to a Long COVID diagnosis by aggregating common themes, data elements,
                    and components from the information that team members individually collected. In
                    the current state, critical data associated with OTC testing, patient symptoms,
                    symptom progression, and timelines are either lost or sub-optimally reported.
                    Accurate and standardized data reporting at all stages of a patient’s diagnosis
                    is needed to support improved patient care, research, and public health and
                    policy decision making.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Outpatient Path</emphasis></para>
                <para>A first instance of data loss occurs in the outpatient path when the patient
                    takes the first at-home OTC test; test results, symptoms at time of testing, and
                    timeline are uncaptured. However, lab orders and results are captured during
                    patient testing at the drive-up testing site and results are reported to the
                    “Community COVID-19 Reporting” database. Following the drive-up testing, there
                    is a 60-day window of missed opportunity for critical capture of symptoms and
                    at-home testing results, including timeline and progression data. During this
                    60-day period the patient experiences evolving symptoms and changes in activity
                    levels, routines, and diet. Data are only reported again when the patient visits
                    a primary care provider (PCP) for a follow-up visit, indicating the need for
                    gathering outpatient data generated by the patient. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Inpatient Path</emphasis></para>
                <para>The inpatient path indicates a better environment for data capture. Similar to
                    the outpatient workflow, initial OTC test results, symptoms, and timeline are
                    not captured as the patient does not report these data. However, the patient
                    enters an inpatient workflow environment where all data generated through the
                    PCP, Lab, and Emergency Room (ER) are documented in the patient’s EHR during a
                    period of continuous monitoring. In this inpatient scenario there is only one
                    point of data loss during a period of 30-days between testing negative and
                    returning for subsequent testing after experiencing continued symptoms. During
                    this period, data regarding activity levels, evolution of symptoms, and change
                    in routine, diet, and vitals are lost. </para>
                <para>The outpatient path eventually leads into the inpatient workflow as both
                    patients’ PCP consider a Long COVID diagnosis. This general workflow highlights
                    data loss in OTC testing or outpatient scenarios, and considerable loss of
                    uncaptured symptom and test results data. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Aim 2: Establish the Future State of Patient Care</title>
                <para>Once the generalized Long COVID use case was developed, the team explored a
                    more specific scenario that begins with a prompt for a patient to take an OTC
                    COVID-19 test. Current and standardized data points were identified in the
                    representative patient flow and categorized as captured or uncaptured data. The
                    workflow highlighted the major steps over the course of a patient’s Long COVID
                    diagnostic journey, including potential variations in results or outcomes at
                    certain steps.</para>
                <para>The workflow begins with one of five steps that lead to the patient pursuing
                    an at-home, OTC COVID-19 test and exploring home treatment/quarantine decisions
                    without clinical input or EHR data capture. Uncaptured data generated during
                    these steps in the diagnostic journey include exposure methods and related data,
                    symptom diary options, patient background, OTC POC test sales and supply data,
                    results from the OTC POC test, and more. </para>
                <para>Step eight, when the patient looks to confirm the results of their OTC test,
                    is when the process reaches the first point of clinical input as the patient
                    takes one of four potential Lab PCR tests. In the current state, data preceding
                    step eight would be lost or unutilized. Data generated at this step include
                    registration, intake information, continuation of symptoms, lab orders, and
                    results. Standardized data include patient demographics, insurance information,
                    updated lab order information (device and test kit IDs), and EHR standard data
                    elements, depending on the location of the test (e.g., pharmacy, urgent care,
                    PCP, ER). </para>
                <para>The workflow continues with data collection from both POC and OTC sources,
                    aiming to collect as much as possible along the way. It should also be noted
                    that there will be bidirectional data flow within this ideal future state. For
                    example, a physician will have access to patient data collected throughout their
                    journey to support their clinical decision making and, ultimately, diagnosis.
                    Aim 3 explains how data will be transformed and utilized for specific
                    purposes.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Aim 3: Establish the Future State Data Workflow</title>
                <para>Using the outpatient Long COVID patient care workflow, the specific steps
                    where data are or should be captured were identified and collated into a table.
                    Subject matter experts then identified opportunities for improved data capture
                    through various resources, technologies, and methods. Table 1 is an example of
                    four data capture points from the larger table that identifies specific steps in
                    the outpatient Long COVID workflow, if and how data are currently captured at
                    those steps, new data that need to be collected, and methods for collecting
                    those data. The specific data collection points are denoted with a data icon in
                    the outpatient Long COVID patient care workflow and similar data collection
                    steps are grouped by a box with a dashed line. This process was repeated
                    throughout the workflow for each data capture point.</para>
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
                <para>INSERT FUTURE STATE DATA COLLECTION TABLE</para><?oxy_custom_end?>
                <para>The data collection groups were then transposed and used as the starting
                    points for the idealized future state data workflow depicted in Figure 4. This
                    workflow outlines the idealized flow of data through the five key data
                    dimensions listed in chronological order:</para>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Enablers</emphasis>: Enablers are key processes,
                    steps, or components that must be achieved to improve the quality and
                    standardization of data collection steps. The future state data workflow begins
                    with overarching enablers, such as intermediaries and data platforms to support
                    data transmissions, and then dives into more specific requirements for each of
                    the data collection methods like implementing functional barcode/QR code systems
                    on OTC test boxes.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">How Data are Collected</emphasis>: The workflow
                    then highlights the various data collection tools and resources that can be used
                    to collect critical patient health data.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">What Data are Collected</emphasis>: The workflow
                    then explores the type of data that are collected. Depending on the associated
                    step in the future state outpatient workflow, the various data collection
                    methods could capture retail data, test data, patient symptoms, ask at order
                    entry (AOE) questions, and much more.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">Where Data are Stored</emphasis>: Once the type of
                    data that are collected is identified, the workflow outlines the storage systems
                    and databases that originally house the data.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="underline">How Data are Aggregated and Transmitted</emphasis>:
                    After data flow out of the initial data store and through a PPRL, the data will
                    undergo a statement transformation process and terminology representation
                    process that is informed by knowledge management reference implementation and
                    produces data with idealized structure and terminology. These data then continue
                    through Analysis Normal Form (ANF) storage and rules execution and applies
                    transmission standards such as FHIR. Data are then finally ready to be
                    transmitted to other healthcare systems such as research repositories or EHRs.
                    Data with idealized structure and terminology can also follow an alternate path
                    and take part in feedback loops that inform questionnaire development for data
                    acquisition from patients and providers or can be used as real-world evidence to
                    inform improvements to the initial data collection methods.</para>
                <para>While the data workflow uses a COVID-19 test trigger, the purchase of an OTC
                    COVID-19 test, the administration and use of an OTC COVID-19 test, and
                    administration of a confirmatory laboratory PCR test, this process can be
                    expanded to more data collection steps along a Long COVID diagnosis or even
                    expanded to other emerging acute and chronic infectious diseases. This data
                    workflow shows how data will need to move within and between EHRs, laboratory
                    information systems (LIS), federal databases, website and application data
                    stores, and other healthcare related systems and how RWE can be used as a
                    feedback mechanism to support continual process and data collection
                    improvements.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Emerging Acute and Chronic Infectious Diseases Use Case Discussion</title>
            <para>In today’s healthcare ecosystem and expanding digital and personal health markets,
                large amounts of patient data are generated but uncaptured. This body of work aims
                to highlight some of the gaps in data collection and proposes potential
                opportunities to use existing technologies and resources to improve the quality and
                interoperability of data that are collected from previously uncaptured sources. A
                generalized Long COVID and more granular workflows were developed as a use case to
                highlight specific instances of data loss and opportunities to improve collection of
                data across a variety of emerging acute and chronic infectious diseases that is
                critical to patient care, such as at home test results. Long COVID, a relatively new
                and poorly characterized condition, acts as a use case to demonstrate how capturing
                this additional data would allow providers, researchers, and many others involved in
                the healthcare system to make better informed patient care decisions and develop
                evidence-based indicators for a Long COVID diagnosis. Improving data
                interoperability will improve an organization’s ability to ingest data in real-time
                and develop materials such as questionnaires or symptom trackers to deploy to the
                field. Targeted and dynamic data collection methods will give organizations better
                insight into the most pertinent questions that need to be answered for a variety of
                emerging conditions and diseases.</para>
            <para>Our analysis of the Long COVID workflow uncovered several sources of RWD where
                extra effort should be made to gather and represent relevant data. RWD, including
                patient reported symptoms, are an opportunity to gather information that could lead
                to earlier identification of diseases. When considering the expanding market for OTC
                testing for many chronic and infectious diseases, it is evident the amount of
                critical data that are lost from the system and unavailable for further analyses.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Future Considerations for the Emerging Acute and Chronic Infectious Diseases Use
                Case</title>
            <para>The Long COVID data workflow outlines idealized data stemming from a COVID-19 OTC
                test trigger, the purchase and use of a COVID-19 OTC test, and the administration of
                a confirmatory laboratory PCR test. These are all key data collection points in the
                Future State Long COVID patient workflow but do not comprehensively represent how
                data could flow in an idealized state. The team will continue to incorporate the
                remaining data collection steps and data groupings from the patient workflow to
                elucidate how various data storage systems house, transform, and transmit data as
                well as the enablers needed to improve and standardize the associated data
                collection. This continued work will be included in a future iteration of this work.
                While this work currently centers around a Long COVID diagnosis, the themes and
                insights will be used to inform data aggregation and secondary use for other
                emerging acute and chronic infectious diseases that will ultimately provide their
                own feedback and insights to further improve data collection.</para>
            <para>Advanced analytical capability of monitoring and responding to data trends in real
                time goes beyond detecting emerging diseases and can extend to fast tracking device
                and diagnostic tool approvals. Liquid Biopsy (LBx) is a promising new diagnostic
                tool for screening and detecting cancers, however, traditional clinical trials
                require too many resources and cannot evaluate the breadth of emerging LBx assays.
                Aggregated patient data are needed along with timely data from EHRs, LIS, tumor
                registries, and other data repositories for appropriate evaluation. Many different
                RWD elements and classes are required to establish the sensitivity and specificity
                of a LBx, including data on a range of cancer negative/positive patients, lab
                results, pre/post cancer testing, past medical and family histories, medication
                history, environmental exposure, germline sequences, imaging studies, and
                demographics. Further understanding the sources of data can help inform future data
                flows similar to the Long COVID flow to create normalized, interoperable, and
                dynamic data repositories. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References (as of 7/7/23)</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>FDA. Real World Evidence [Internet]. U.S. Food and Drug Administration.
                        2022. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/science-research/science-and-research-special-topics/real-world-evidence"
                            >https://www.fda.gov/science-research/science-and-research-special-topics/real-world-evidence</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cook RJ, Durning SJ. Clinical Process Modeling. Academic Medicine. 2019
                        Apr;1.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Vankipuram A, Traub S, Patel VL. A method for the analysis and
                        visualization of clinical workflow in dynamic environments. Journal of
                        Biomedical Informatics. 2018 Mar;79:20–31.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Crowley C, Guitron S, Son J, Pianykh OS. Modeling workflows: Identifying
                        the most predictive features in healthcare operational processes. Vellido A,
                        editor. PLOS ONE. 2020 Jun 11;15(6):e0233810.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Griewing S, Lingenfelder M, Wagner U, Gremke N. Use Case Evaluation and
                        Digital Workflow of Breast Cancer Care by Artificial Intelligence and
                        Blockchain Technology Application. Healthcare. 2022 Oct
                        20;10(10):2100.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>de Bruin JS, Adlassnig K-P, Leitich H, Rappelsberger A. Separating
                        Business Logic from Medical Knowledge in Digital Clinical Workflows Using
                        Business Process Model and Notation and Arden Syntax. Studies in Health
                        Technology and Informatics [Internet]. 2018 [cited 2023 Mar 15];248:17–24.
                        Available from: <link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29726414/"
                            >https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29726414/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Natsiavas P, Stavropoulos TG, Pliatsios A, Karanikas H, Gavriilidis GI,
                        Dimitriadis VK, et al. Using Business Process Management Notation to Model
                        Therapeutic Prescription Protocols: The PrescIT Approach. Studies in Health
                        Technology and Informatics. 2021 May 27;</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ruiz F, Garcia F, Calahorra L, Llorente C, Gonçalves L, Daniel C, et al.
                        Business process modeling in healthcare. Studies in Health Technology and
                        Informatics [Internet]. 2012 [cited 2023 Mar 15];179:75–87. Available from:
                            <link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22925789/"
                            >https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22925789/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kassim SA, Gartner J-B, Labbé L, Landa P, Paquet C, Bergeron F, et al.
                        Benefits and limitations of business process model notation in modelling
                        patient healthcare trajectory: a scoping review protocol. BMJ Open. 2022
                        May;12(5):e060357.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hedin K, van der Velden AW, Hansen MP, Moberg AB, Balan A, Bruno P, et al.
                        Initial symptoms and three months follow-up after acute COVID-19 in
                        outpatients: An international prospective cohort study. The European Journal
                        of General Practice [Internet]. 2023 Jan 19 [cited 2023 Mar 9];2154074.
                        Available from: <link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36655704/"
                            >https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36655704/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Tran V-T, Porcher R, Pane I, Ravaud P. Course of post COVID-19 disease
                        symptoms over time in the ComPaRe long COVID prospective e-cohort. Nature
                        Communications. 2022 Apr 5;13(1).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Davis HE, McCorkell L, Vogel JM, Topol EJ. Long COVID: major findings,
                        mechanisms and recommendations. Nature Reviews Microbiology [Internet]. 2023
                        Jan 13;1–14. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41579-022-00846-2"
                            >https://www.nature.com/articles/s41579-022-00846-2</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Malden DE, Tartof SY, Ackerson BK, Hong V, Skarbinski J, Yau V, et al.
                        Natural Language Processing for Improved Characterization of COVID-19
                        Symptoms: Observational Study of 350,000 Patients in a Large Integrated
                        Health Care System. JMIR Public Health and Surveillance [Internet]. 2022 Dec
                        30 [cited 2023 Mar 9];8(12):e41529. Available from:<link
                            xlink:href="https://publichealth.jmir.org/2022/12/e41529"
                            >https://publichealth.jmir.org/2022/12/e41529</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>CDC. Long COVID or Post-COVID Conditions [Internet]. Centers for Disease
                        Control and Prevention. 2021. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/long-term-effects/index.html"
                            >https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/long-term-effects/index.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cholan RA, Pappas G, Rehwoldt G, Sills AK, Korte ED, Appleton IK, et al.
                        Encoding laboratory testing data: case studies of the national
                        implementation of HHS requirements and related standards in five
                        laboratories. Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association
                        [Internet]. 2022 May 25 [cited 2023 Mar 16];29(8):1372–80. Available from:
                        https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article/29/8/1372/6592172#365931904</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>PPRL | N3C [Internet]. covid.cd2h.org. [cited 2023 Mar 9]. Available from:
                        https://covid.cd2h.org/PPRL</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>

