<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">

    <title>Next Steps</title>
    <para>Tinkar is a logical model and therefore may be implemented using relevant implementable
        models and technology. This section will focus on the use of Tinkar alongside preexisting
        HL7 exchange standards. In practice, the Tinkar logical model can be used to create
        practical implementation guidance in the future (e.g., implementation guides, profiles,
        value sets), and can be applied to design change management solutions.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Tinkar Serialization Data</title>
        <para>Tinkar will include a serialization format that will serialize any or all the
            information stored in a Tinkar implementation. This serialization format will allow
            third parties to read data created by a Tinkar compliant implementation. A serialized
            Tinkar file can also be used to transfer information between different Tinkar
            implementations. This will ensure that no Tinkar data is lost. </para>
        <para>C# and Java code implementations of the Tinkar Data Model will be made available to
            integrators, allowing third parties to more easily use Tinkar.</para>
        <para>Specifically, third party implementers can use Java or C# to:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Read Tinkar data into memory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Manipulate and modify Tinkar data using Tinkar data structures.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Write Tinkar data out to a serialized file.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Tinkar interfacing with FHIR</title>
        <para>Tinkar data can be used to create Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR)
            compliant data. Tinkar data can be used to generate FHIR data. Only a subset of the
            Tinkar data model would be converted to FHIR. Roundtripping of data between Tinkar and
            FHIR back and forth is likely to result in Tinkar data loss.</para>
        <para>Tinkar data items lost in FHIR conversion:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>STAMP data: Loss of the STAMP data means that the ability to look at
                    terminology at a specific point in time is lost. The FHIR data is a snapshot at
                    a fixed point in time.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Semantic data: FHIR data does not contain a concept similar to Tinkar’s
                    semantic relationships. </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>There are two main areas in which Tinkar and FHIR are expected to interface, as
            described in the subsequent sections: “Dynamic FHIR Terminology Servers” and “Static
            FHIR CodeSystem and ValueSet Resources.”</para>
        <section>
            <title>Dynamic FHIR Terminology Servers</title>
            <para>FHIR terminology servers are designed to provide knowledge artifacts in real time
                to support clinical system operations. A system may request $expand on a ValueSet,
                for instance, to populate a drop-down list in a user interface, or $validate-code to
                confirm content in an interface conforming to a profile; a request for $subsumes on
                a CodeSystem or on a ConceptMap can be used to translate codes when transforming
                native records to a standard format, and so forth.</para>
            <para>FHIR queries against the FHIR terminology server could use Tinkar originated
                terminology data as well as other non-Tinkar generated terminology to fulfill the
                requests.</para>
            <para>The serialization file described above would be one way to import data from a
                Tinkar system to a FHIR terminology server. Implementers for each FHIR Terminology
                Server would have to write code specific to their implementation to import Tinkar
                data into their own implementation dependent data storage.</para>
            <para>The Tinkar C# and Java libraries could be used by the FHIR Server Implementors to
                help support that import process.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Static FHIR CodeSystem and ValueSet Resources</title>
            <para>FHIR CodeSystem and ValueSet records are designed to provide knowledge artifacts
                to support clinical system operations. Terminology data contained in FHIR CodeSystem
                and ValueSet resources are fixed at the time that the resource instances are
                generated.</para>
            <para>It is expected that some automated means of creating FHIR ValueSet and CodeSystem
                records from Tinkar will be developed. The automated system could import data from a
                Tinkar system using the serialization format described above, and output desired
                CodeSystem and ValueSet instances. Modifications to the Tinkar data would require
                regeneration of the FHIR artifacts and subsequent transmission to interested users
                of those resource instances.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Tinkar interfacing with HL7 UTG, THO, HTA</title>
        <para>The three HL7 processes for maintaining and distributing HL7 terminology content are
            UTG, THO, HTA. Our understanding of these HL7 Areas: </para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Unified Terminology Governance (UTG)</emphasis>: A
                        process with associated tooling to support the process strictly for
                        governance of HL7 terminological content. UTG is the maintenance process to
                        keep it up to date and manage change. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">HL7 Terminological Content (THO)</emphasis>: HL7
                        Terminological Content refers to <emphasis role="underline"
                            >t</emphasis>erminology.<emphasis role="underline"
                            >h</emphasis>L7.<emphasis role="underline">o</emphasis>rg (THO) which is
                        the domain address of the entry point for the published content. HL7
                        terminology or THO refers to an enormous corpus of coded content that varies
                        in quality and that has been developed in HL7 for about 30 years.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">HL7 Terminology Authority (HTA)</emphasis>: The
                        HTA’s primary purpose is to deal memorandum of understanding and publication
                        interfaces with non-HL7 publishers and maintainers of terminological
                        content. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>The aim of these HL7 groups, to provide standardized HL7 terminology in a consistent
            format, is consistent with the goal of Tinkar.</para>
        <para>If HL7 so desired, Tinkar could be used as the format by which all HL7 terminology is
            exported. It is believed that current HL7 content can be converted to Tinkar with no
            loss. Further work would need to be done to verify that if HL7 was interested in that
            path.</para>
        <para>Conversion of HL7 common terminology data to Tinkar would allow:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use of tools like KOMET to import, export, maintain and validate HL7
                    terminology data</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use of Tinkar serialization format for serialization and distribution
                    format</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use of Tinkar and third-party tooling to convert Tinkar serialized data to
                    FHIR records and import to FHIR terminology servers</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>


</chapter>
