<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1" xml:id="appendix">
    <title>Related Works</title>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Campbell KE. Distributed Development of a Logic-based Controlled Medical
                Terminology. Stanford University. June 1997. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Campbell KE, Das AK, Musen MA. A logical foundation for representation of clinical
                data. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 1994 May-Jun;1(3):218-32. doi:
                10.1136/jamia.1994.95236154. PMID: 7719805; PMCID: PMC116201.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Spackman KA, Campbell KE, Côté RA. SNOMED RT: a reference terminology for health
                care. Proc AMIA Annu Fall Symp. 1997:640-4. PMID: 9357704; PMCID: PMC2233423.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Campbell KE, Cohn SP, Chute CG, Shortliffe EH, Rennels G. Scalable methodologies
                for distributed development of logic-based convergent medical terminology. Methods
                Inf Med. 1998 Nov;37(4-5):426-39. PMID: 9865041.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Bakken S, Campbell KE, Cimino JJ, Huff SM, Hammond WE. Toward vocabulary domain
                specifications for health level 7-coded data elements. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2000
                Jul-Aug;7(4):333-42. doi: 10.1136/jamia.2000.0070333. PMID: 10887162; PMCID:
                PMC61438.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Campbell KE, Oliver DE, Shortliffe EH. The Unified Medical Language System: toward
                a collaborative approach for solving terminologic problems. J Am Med Inform Assoc.
                1998 Jan-Feb;5(1):12-6. doi: 10.1136/jamia.1998.0050012. PMID: 9452982; PMCID:
                PMC61272.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Campbell KE, Giannangelo K. Language barrier. Getting past the classifications and
                terminologies roadblock. J AHIMA. 2007 Feb;78(2):44-6, 48. PMID: 17366992.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Campbell KE, Musen MA. Representation of clinical data using SNOMED III and
                conceptual graphs. Proc Annu Symp Comput Appl Med Care. 1992:354-8. PMID: 1482897;
                PMCID: PMC2248067.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Chute CG, Cohn SP, Campbell KE, Oliver DE, Campbell JR. The content coverage of
                clinical classifications. For The Computer-Based Patient Record Institute's Work
                Group on Codes &amp; Structures. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 1996 May-Jun;3(3):224-33.
                doi: 10.1136/jamia.1996.96310636. PMID: 8723613; PMCID: PMC116304.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Bakken S, Parker J, Konicek D, Campbell KE. An evaluation of ICNP intervention
                axes as terminology model components. Proc AMIA Symp. 2000:42-6. PMID: 11079841;
                PMCID: PMC2244103.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Spackman KA, Reynoso G. Examining SNOMED from the perspective of Formal
                Ontological Principles: Some Preliminary Analysis and Observations. Proc. KR-MED,
                2004: 72-80.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
</appendix>
