<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Business Requirements</title>
    <para>This section details specific business requirements for a Tinkar logical model.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Clinical Requirements</title>
        <para>The ultimate goal of this effort is to <emphasis role="underline"
                linkend="requirement_1">support the coordination of safe, effective medicine
                (Requirement 1)</emphasis>. This goal requires <emphasis role="underline"
                linkend="requirement_2">quality information in the patient record (Requirement
                2)</emphasis>, wherever it comes from, and the increasingly distributed nature of
            care that requires <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_3">commonly
                understood data standards (Requirement 3)</emphasis> to ensure mutual comprehension
            across the care team and over time. There are four outlined clinical use cases:</para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="1">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Record Patient Data</emphasis></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>A care provider, already authenticated and authorized to the
                                system and using the appropriate context to ensure the system
                                records the data for the correct patient, adds or modifies
                                information in the patient record. This may include signs, symptoms,
                                impressions, diagnoses, orders, notes, or other assets.</para>
                            <para>This operation may initiate workflow processes or automated
                                processes such as clinical decision support suggestions.</para>
                            <para>For structured data using standard terminologies, the <emphasis
                                    role="underline" linkend="requirement_4">terms available are
                                    appropriate (Requirement 4)</emphasis> for the clinical context,
                                for the role (i.e., terms may differ for different kinds of users),
                                and for the data context (e.g., data entry fields may not support
                                inactive or deprecated terms that would be allowed in search or
                                analytical contexts).</para>
                            <para>If the available terminology does not support the provider’s
                                needs, the provider may assert a need for a new term.</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Propose Terminology Change</emphasis></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>If a provider attempts to enter a term that is not supported by
                                the enterprise terminology, the <emphasis role="underline"
                                    linkend="requirement_5">effort will be captured as a proposed
                                    term (Requirement 5).</emphasis>
                            </para>
                            <para>Systems may capture this information unobtrusively as text, or
                                prompt further information from the clinician to assist the
                                authoring process. The system will convey at least the text and the
                                identity of the clinician to the terminologist.</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Review Patient Data</emphasis></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>A provider, already authenticated and authorized to the system and
                                using the appropriate context to ensure the system records the data
                                for the correct patient, finds and reviews information in the
                                patient record. </para>
                            <para>For structured data using standard terminologies, the terms
                                available are appropriate for the clinical context, for the role
                                (i.e., terms may differ for different kinds of users), and for the
                                data context (i.e., data entry fields may not support inactive or
                                deprecated terms that would be allowed in search or analytical
                                contexts).</para>
                            <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_6">Changes to the
                                    terminology that could affect record interpretation will be
                                    indicated (Requirement 6)</emphasis>, along with a way to
                                identify the change and its effect.</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Review Knowledge Base Changes
                                            Relevant to Record</emphasis></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>If the system identifies a relevant change, the provider may
                                request further information. </para>
                            <para>This will include the ability to <emphasis role="underline"
                                    linkend="requirement_7">see available values and CDS results for
                                    specific dates and contexts (Requirement 7)</emphasis>,
                                including those under which the data was recorded or specific
                                decisions were made.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para> </para>
        <para> </para>
        <para> </para>
        <para> </para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic"> Clinical Use Cases</emphasis></para>
        <para>The key capability for a clinician should be <emphasis role="underline"
                linkend="requirement_8">to record and review data quickly and accurately
                (Requirement 8)</emphasis>, taking advantage of up-to-date classifications and
            decision support rules. This should be accomplished by knowing when a change in the
            knowledge base might affect a record. The change management capability that supports
            these operations should be as unobtrusive as possible to patients and care providers,
            and always readily available.</para>
        <para>These operations depend on the availability not only of currently accurate terminology
            assets, but also <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_7">assets from prior
                points in time (Requirement 7)</emphasis>. These may include assets as defined or refined by different
                stakeholders with different sets of assumptions. For
            instance, whether a disorder meets a criterion defined by a standard terminology, a
            payor, a professional society, or a locally chartered board of specialists.</para>
        <para>To support these needs, the Enterprise Terminology that supports the clinical systems
            must <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_9">manage change systematically
                (Requirement 9)</emphasis>, and it must do so for both internally-managed and
            externally-sourced assets. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Asset Curation Requirements</title>
        <para>Curation of these assets requires detailed change data. The evolution and maturation
            of knowledge happens at different times and places. Keeping standards and relationships
            to standards current is a complex undertaking. A health system may subscribe to dozens
            of standard and commercial terminologies, each of which may publish scheduled updates
            several times a year, and any of which may push out an emergency update at any time. All
            these assets have different designs, so ensuring continued cohesion is expensive and
            time-consuming, and the necessary transformations introduce risk. Systematic management
            of change requires granular representation of the assets and associated asset
            changes.</para>
        <para>There are best-practice capabilities in knowledge asset maintenance. The following is
            proposed for clinical data standards:</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_10">Unique object identification (Requirement 10)</emphasis>: Every
                        object under version control must have a unique identifier, and the
                        identifier must remain unchanged as the object is modified and different
                        versions of it are created and saved. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_11">Version history
                            retention (Requirement 11)</emphasis>: Each version of an object must be
                        persisted as the object changes over time, along with metadata indicating
                        its version identifier, time of creation, creating author, and branch of the
                        version control system on which it was created. Further, every version of
                        each object must remain available for retrieval and inspection.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_12">Version comparison (Requirement 12)</emphasis>: It must be easy
                        to compare two versions of the same object and identify all differences
                        between them. Among other things, this capability is important to determine
                        whether updates to a sub-artifact have changed its semantics in a way that
                        may affect the behavior of one or more of its parent artifacts. Ready
                        comparison is also important when merging two or more concurrent development
                        efforts involving the same knowledge artifacts.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_13">Branching capabilities (Requirement 13)</emphasis>: It must be
                        possible to create a virtual copy of the entire version-control
                        configuration, or a defined subset, in a new “path,” such that changes made
                        to objects in this branch do not appear in the original configuration. This
                        capability allows individual knowledge engineers to make and test changes to
                        knowledge artifacts without affecting the work of other knowledge engineers
                        or the integrity of knowledge artifacts currently in production. This
                        facility is critical to the orderly and safe management of a clinical
                        decision support system.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_14">Merging capabilities (Requirement 14)</emphasis>: It must be
                        possible to incorporate all the changes made on one branch of the
                        version-control repository into another branch, such that any conflicts
                        between different versions of the same objects are detected and resolved.
                        This capability is important to enable work done by multiple knowledge
                        engineers concurrently to be combined and incorporated into the main branch
                        of the repository. The merging capability is also important to allow
                        knowledge engineers to update their local branches of the repository with
                        changes that may have been made by others to the main branch, thus ensuring
                        that changes will remain compatible with the latest version of the
                        system.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>These core properties support authoring and maintenance operations: at a high level,
            this means <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_15">modifying the enterprise
                terminologies (Requirement 15)</emphasis>, <emphasis role="underline"
                linkend="requirement_16">importing standard terminologies (Requirement
                16)</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_17">publishing
                the enterprise terminologies (Requirement 17)</emphasis> to the client clinical
            systems. The standard terminology publisher has the same needs around modification and
            publishing as the enterprise, and some standards import other standards as well (e.g.,
            MedRT, which publishes relationships among other standards). </para>
        <para>We distinguish between the Enterprise Terminologist and the Standards Development
            Organization (SDO) Terminologist. The Enterprise Terminologist is responsible for
            ensuring that the terminology resources provided to clinical systems are current and
            accurate. This involves managing the consumption of external terminologies as well as
            maintenance of assets defined within the enterprise. The SDO Terminologist is
            responsible for ensuring that the terminology resources provided to other terminology
            systems are current and accurate. This may involve managing the consumption of external
            terminologies as well as maintenance of assets defined within the SDO.</para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="1">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Modify Enterprise Terminology</emphasis></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>A user adds, modifies, or deactivates content in the terminology
                                assets of the enterprise, including assets provided to clinical
                                systems as well as management data used only within the knowledge
                                base.</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Publish Enterprise Terminology</emphasis></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>A user manages the publication process that supports the automated
                                provision of terminology content to clinical systems.</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Import Standard Terminology</emphasis></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>A user incorporates a new standard terminology or new version of a
                                standard terminology into the enterprise terminology. During this
                                process, functionality supports the assessment and management of
                                impacts on existing enterprise assets.</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Publish Standard Terminology</emphasis></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>A user manages the publication process that supports the automated
                                provision of terminology content to client terminology
                                servers.</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Modify Standard Terminology</emphasis></para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>A user adds, modifies, or deactivates content in the terminology
                                assets of the standard, including assets provided to client
                                terminology systems as well as management data used only within the
                                knowledge base (e.g., changing SNOMED CT® relationships, inserting a
                                concept in between two existing concepts). <emphasis>Note that a
                                    standard can only be modified by the standard owner</emphasis>.
                                A client enterprise may add to or modify the content in an
                                “overlay,” but those changes are part of the local enterprise
                                assets. The client enterprise cannot actually modify the
                                standard.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Asset Curation Use Cases</emphasis></para>
        <para>Today, clinical systems consume terminologies, but the interfaces are point-to-point.
            To assert or assess new information, the tools must already understand all relevant
            interface models. Since an external organization may modify that model at any time, the
            ability to consume external assets involves ongoing manual efforts to understand or
            confirm the model and the design of transformations to support consumption. This is
            potentially expensive and risky.</para>
        <para>We propose a “data-driven” architecture to support self-describing terminology assets.
            All changes can be programmatically managed with a globally consistent design.
            Management may involve human review, but it can leverage pattern-based recognition of
            specific change types for automated handling, leaving a smaller number of cases that
            require human judgment. This information design will support a common representation of
            all terminologies. There are two key requirements for this design:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_11">A complete record of all changes, including relevant change context information (Requirement 11)</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_18">A single syntax to support the representation of all terminology assets, known and future (Requirement 18)</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The context information of the first requirement includes the following:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_19">Status</emphasis> of
                    the asset: whether it should be considered active or inactive in the context of
                    these other attributes <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_19"
                        >(Requirement 19)</emphasis>. For systems that do not support status, the
                    default will be “active.”</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_20">Time</emphasis> of the
                    change, specified with a time zone and at an appropriate precision <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_20">(Requirement
                    20)</emphasis>. For systems that do not provide a time, the default will be the release
                    time.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_21">Author</emphasis> of
                    the creation or change, unambiguously identified <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_21">(Requirement 21)</emphasis>. For systems
                    that do not provide an author, a default author will be created for the
                    system.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The domain or organizational name of the larger asset within which the
                    component is meaningful, such as code system or edition <emphasis
                        role="underline" linkend="requirement_22">(a.k.a., Module) (Requirement
                    22)</emphasis>. For systems that do not provide a module, a default module will be created
                    for the system.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The production branch of that organization, e.g., for distributed development,
                    testing, staging, or production <emphasis role="underline"
                        linkend="requirement_23">(a.k.a., Path) (Requirement 23)</emphasis>. For systems that
                    do not provide a path, a default path will be created for the system.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>These elements together are referred to by the acronym “<emphasis role="bold"
                >STAMP</emphasis>.” Every new assertion, whether a new asset or a change to an
            existing asset, must have a STAMP to determine when it is to be used. The STAMP
            properties support the ability to apply terminology assets for specific purposes. For
            example:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>“Path” can be used to test provisional content without physically swapping out
                    systems. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>“Modules” are used to organize content for maintenance and publication
                    purposes. Modules are the domain or organizational name of the larger asset
                    within which the component is meaningful, such as code system or edition.
                    Modularity for terminologies should follow a similar design to modularity in
                    software engineering. Deciding what belongs in certain modules or extensions
                    within certain terminologies is a difficult subject that is out of scope for
                    this document, but having support for the ability to create modules, recognize
                    redundancy, and merge or retire concepts are important requirements that must be
                    supported. <link
                        linkend="bib13">[12]</link> <link
                            linkend="bib14">[13]</link> <link
                                linkend="bib15">[14]</link>  </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>“Time” supports the ability to apply CDS rules as they would have looked in
                    the past.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>A further requirement is that not only must the architecture support these properties,
            but that <emphasis role="underline">it must require</emphasis> the properties for all
            assets under curation. Without consistent application of this rule, the foundational
            capability of detailed version management is more difficult. </para>
        <para>Additionally, for an asset to support a record of changes, each <emphasis
                role="underline" linkend="requirement_10">asset must itself be identifiable
                (Requirement 10)</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>The “single syntax” requirement is harder to satisfy. One approach would be to define
            a syntax that addresses the data elements of all known terminologies. This would be a
            heavy specification, that would be difficult to maintain, and could fail to capture new
            elements as terminologies are added in the future.</para>
        <para>The other approach is to use a “self-describing” or “meta-modeling” approach, where
            the syntax defines not only the content but also what the content means. “Rigid” or
            “brittle” specifications determine in advance where information belongs: a database may
            use column names to suggest what belongs in a column, but there is no way to determine
            whether the name is a good one, or whether an instance value meets the criterion implied
            by the name. But flexible specifications support data definition. XML (a subset of SGML)
            provides a way to specify types of data and structural (not semantic) relationships. RDF
            goes one step further by making the relationship between an element and its containing
            class an explicit part of every triplet. If this relationship is specified in a
            controlled terminology, then assertions can be tested for validity. For example, if an
            RDF Schema Specification (RDFS) asserts that the finding site of a lesion must be an
            anatomical feature, then assertions about actual lesions can be tested for valid finding
            sites. Furthermore, this logic specifies a “range” in the same syntactic structure as
            the instance assertion: changes to the knowledge base do not affect the syntactical
            representation of the knowledge. Systems that adopt this approach will require effort to
            take advantage of new features of terminologies, without having to rebuild their
            infrastructure when changes are made.</para>
        <para>Having change data in discrete tagged change sets will allow the software to hide most
            of the complexity of version management from the human managers, allowing them to focus
            on significant decisions.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Configuration Requirements</title>
        <para>A granular self-describing model will support any statement that can be made using
            concepts in a subject-predicate-object structure, and its compositional aspect permits
            compound predicates. It is difficult to imagine a proposition that cannot be supported.
            This power, however, means that there are multiple ways to support any specific kind of
            statement that a terminology knowledge base must support. This section addresses best
            practices for these cases.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Operations</title>
            <para><emphasis role="underline">Import</emphasis>: A user may identify content from
                another system and write it into the Terminology Repository. When this happens, the
                new content will be recorded in the common, self-describing format. When a set of
                content is imported, rules asserted by the source steward or the Terminology
                Repository steward may be used to assert structural equivalence in the repository
                (i.e., different source concepts may be represented as alternate representations of
                the same root concept). During importation of subsequent versions of a system,
                changes to assets on which other enterprise assets depend must be identified and
                managed as directed by documented policies. The import operation will usually
                identify sets of such changes which require prioritization to prevent redundant
                processing.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_24">Search (Requirement 24)</emphasis>: A user may use lexical or concept-based
                parameters to search for a set of matching assets.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_25">View (Requirement 25)</emphasis>: A user may view an asset, the view
                consisting of related information associated in visually appropriate ways. This view
                may omit information not appropriate to the user’s context. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_12">Compare (Requirement
                    12)</emphasis>: A user may view related assets, including versions of component,
                in a form designed to support analytical comparison (e.g., side-by-side
                display).</para>
            <para><emphasis role="underline">Authoring/Maintenance</emphasis>: A user may modify existing
                content or add new content. To preserve prior states, all modifications are recorded
                as new versions of content: prior versions will remain unchanged. Any time a change
                is made, the system will identify dependent assets and rules for handling these
                changes.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>An <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_26">addition
                            (Requirement 26)</emphasis> is a new version with a new asset UUID
                        (universally unique identifier). Patterns may assert constraints for
                        additions, which may be specific to context (Modules, Paths, Languages,
                        etc.). </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>An <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_27">inactivation (Requirement 27)</emphasis> is a new version of an existing asset with status set to
                        “inactive.” Patterns may assert rules for deletions, which may be specific
                        to context.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_28">change (Requirement 28)</emphasis> is a new version of an existing asset with the new value(s),
                        distinguishable by STAMP value. A change may involve only a STAMP value. For
                        example, deactivation, or import of a concept to a new module or
                        path.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_29">Classify (Requirement 29)</emphasis>: A user may select a logical profile and
                classifier and use classification logic to test equivalence and subsumption of
                identified assets, or to generate a set of inferred relationships from a set of
                stated relationships. An inferred set may be persisted.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="underline" linkend="requirement_30">Publish (Requirement 30)</emphasis>: A user may promote content into a
                “publication” path and produce a transmissible payload of content that can be
                consumed by other repositories. This promotion is a change and may require
                resolution of constraints on membership in that path.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Patterns for Representing Various Assets</title>
            <para>The data architecture must support patterns for the representation of many kinds
                of assets. A minimal list includes the following:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="bold">term</emphasis> must have: </para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A string representation</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A language, possibly including refinements </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>An indicator of case sensitivity </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A type used to represent whether a term is a synonym, fully
                                qualified name (for example: SNOMED CT® Fully Specified Name or
                                LOINC® Long Common Name), definition, etc.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="bold">concept</emphasis> must have: </para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>At least one term</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>At least one parent, except for root concepts or terminologies
                                that are not hierarchical</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A <emphasis role="bold">logical definition</emphasis> must have:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>A definitional status</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">STAMP values must include</emphasis>:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>“Active” and “inactive” status concepts</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>At least one “default” author</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>At least one “root” module</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Paths supporting “development” and “publication”</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>An <emphasis role="bold">inferred classification</emphasis> must
                        indicate:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The classifier used for its generation</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The logic profile used for its generation</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The stated asset(s)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">module dependency</emphasis> graph:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Identifies the root module</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Lists all other modules, indicating dependency</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Must be acyclical</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>Many other patterns may be present. Implementations are expected to
                support:</para>
            <orderedlist continuation='continues'>
                <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Any assembly of relationships</emphasis> associating one concept with
                        another which must have:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>At least one default rule (constraint) for handling changes (e.g.,
                                whether assets dependent on changed assets can be automatically
                                handled or require intervention) </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Any assembly of relationships</emphasis> may include components that are themselves semantics</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Value sets</emphasis> may include:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Rule-based member inclusions</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Enumerated members</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>System-specific <emphasis role="bold">import rules</emphasis>:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>System equivalences for Tinkar attribute and other infrastructure
                                concepts</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Specified exclusions of logical assertions to support
                                equivalence-on-import inferences irrespective of administrative
                                metadata</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Maps</emphasis>:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Relationships for equivalence assertions</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Relationships for subsumption assertions</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Relationships for other functions (e.g., CDC Reportable Condition
                                Mapping Table)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Constraints</emphasis> on asset patterns,
                        including:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Logical composition constraints on concepts (e.g., the SNOMED CT®
                                concept model)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Syntactic compositional constraints on strings (e.g., MIME types,
                                ISO languages, or Unified Code for Units of Measure (UCUM)
                                units)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Pattern constraints, e.g., presence of exactly one name classified
                                as “fully specified,” or names in specified languages</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Rules that may govern modifications to other assets (e.g.,
                                incremental addition of effort estimates based on known problematic
                                terms).</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist></listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>One other feature is the set of concepts that the application will use to
                determine how to present the data to the user. A key dimension is the STAMP
                information defined above. In addition, three other “coordinates” are required for
                managing the presentation:</para>
            <orderedlist continuation='continues'>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Language</emphasis>: A user may assert a required or
                        preferred language, or a set of ranked language priorities. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Logic</emphasis>: A user may select the parameters
                        for logical classification.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Navigation</emphasis>: A user may select the
                        parameters for presentation of the logical classification </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>Like other concepts, these can be represented by the core data architecture. The
                application implementing the Tinkar specification must be able to identify those
                concepts appropriate for these uses.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Constraints</title>
            <para>
                    Constraints are required to:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Ensure that the appropriate level of detail for standard
                                terminologies are represented within Tinkar</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Create terminology extensions that conform to the requirements of
                                the standard(s) the extension is based on</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Perform general quality assurance</para>
                        </listitem>
                 </orderedlist>
                <para>For example, constraints would be used to represent standard terminology
                artifacts, like the SNOMED CT® Machine Readable Concept Model. Additionally,
                constraints could be used to ensure that the terminologies represented within a
                Tinkar implementation are completely and consistently queried and displayed. </para>
                <para>These same constraints can be used to create new content within a Tinkar
                    implementation to specify the minimally viable data that would be required. For
                        example:</para>
                        <orderedlist numeration="arabic" continuation="continues">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>All concepts must have at least one Fully Qualified Name within at
                        least one Language or Dialect</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>All concepts must have at least one Name specified as Preferred
                        within at least one Language or Dialect</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>All concepts must have at least one parent, unless it is a root
                        concept</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                    <para>Constraints can be applied (or not applied) based on various criteria to
                    perform Quality Assurance on content that is represented within a Tinkar
                    implementation. For example:<orderedlist numeration="arabic"
                        continuation="continues">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>SNOMED CT® FullySpecifiedName hierarchy tags are applied based on
                            where a concept exists in a hierarchy</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Relationships between concepts have domain (based on hierarchy)
                                and range (the hierarchy(s) of values that a relationship
                                takes)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Modeling templates can be specified to ensure that new content
                            that is created under a certain node in a hierarchy uses similar wording
                            and relationships</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist></para>
                    <para>Since some Quality Assurance Constraints do not always indicate an error,
                an Allow List could also be represented as a Semantic to record concepts that are
                allowed to not conform to a constraint. Constraints would be represented using
                semantics as they are self describing and can support multiple different
                representations for constraints (SNOMED CT® Expression Constraint Language, Drools,
                etc.). Representing Constraints as a Semantic also ensures STAMP. STAMP is versioned
                over time, capturing author information and allowing for tests and progress over
                different modules and paths.</para>
                    <para>Implementing Constraints would depend upon how the Constraints are written
                and formatted. For example, implementers could utilize a Rete algorithm through
                something like Drools to implement Constraints.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Minimally Required Content</title>
            <para>A Tinkar implementation must be furnished with the following content:<orderedlist>
                <listitem><para>One root concept</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>One module dependency graph</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Infrastructure concepts a.k.a Tinkar Model Concepts to support the core patterns listed above</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Import rules to support import of standard terminologies, including:</para>
                    <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
                            <listitem><para>Equivalences to support semantic integration of terminologies (e.g., that a LOINC® “system”
                                    instantiates the same relationship concept as the SNOMED CT®
                                    “inheres in” attribute)</para></listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Exclusions to support removal of non-semantic properties from
                                    classification (e.g., RxNorm Translated CDs)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                </orderedlist></para>
            <para>Definitions for Tinkar Model Concepts are located in <link
                    linkend="tinkar_model_concept_appenidix">Appendix C.</link></para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <?hard-linebreak?>
    <section role="landscape">
        <title>List of Requirements</title>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="6">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col3" colwidth="4*"/>
                <colspec colname="newCol3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="newCol4" colnum="4" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="newCol5" colnum="5" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <colspec colname="newCol6" colnum="6" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">ID</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Requirement</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Level</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Clinical System</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Terminology Management</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Information Design</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_1" xreflabel="1">1</entry>
                        <entry>Support the practice and coordination of safe, effective medicine </entry>
                        <entry>Need</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x </entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_2" xreflabel="2">2</entry>
                        <entry>Provide quality information in the patient record</entry>
                        <entry>Need</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_3" xreflabel="3">3</entry>
                        <entry>Represent information in commonly understood data standards </entry>
                        <entry>Feature</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_4" xreflabel="4">4</entry>
                        <entry>Provide terms appropriate to the context</entry>
                        <entry>Feature</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_5" xreflabel="5">5</entry>
                        <entry>Capture terminology suggestions from point of care</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center"/>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_6" xreflabel="6">6</entry>
                        <entry>Indicate data for which changes to the terminology could affect
                            record interpretation </entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_7" xreflabel="7">7</entry>
                        <entry>View available terms and decision support recommendations for
                            specified dates and contexts</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_8" xreflabel="8">8</entry>
                        <entry>Support rapid and accurate recording and review of record data </entry>
                        <entry>Need</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center"/>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_9" xreflabel="9">9</entry>
                        <entry>Manage change systematically</entry>
                        <entry>Feature</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_10" xreflabel="10">10</entry>
                        <entry>Identify assets uniquely</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_11" xreflabel="11">11</entry>
                        <entry>Retain all prior versions</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_12" xreflabel="12">12</entry>
                        <entry>Support comparison of versions</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_13" xreflabel="13">13</entry>
                        <entry>Support branching of sets of assets for independent
                            development</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_14" xreflabel="14">14</entry>
                        <entry>Support controlled merging of branches by identifying and addressing
                            conflicts with defined rules</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_15" xreflabel="15">15</entry>
                        <entry>Modify enterprise terminology by creating, modifying, or deactivating
                            assets and relationships</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_16" xreflabel="16">16</entry>
                        <entry>Import standard terminologies, including merging capability for
                            assets referring to prior versions of the standard</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_17" xreflabel="17">17</entry>
                        <entry>Publish enterprise terminologies, including application and
                            resolution of constraints specific to the publication path</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_18" xreflabel="18">18</entry>
                        <entry>A self-describing method for representing terminology assets from
                            diverse and mutable models</entry>
                        <entry>Feature</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_19" xreflabel="19">19</entry>
                        <entry>Represent the status of the asset in a context</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_20" xreflabel="20">20</entry>
                        <entry>Represent the time at which a change is recorded</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                        <entry align="center">x</entry>

                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        
        
         <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="6">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col3" colwidth="4*"/>
                <colspec colname="newCol3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="newCol4" colnum="4" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="newCol5" colnum="5" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <colspec colname="newCol6" colnum="6" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">ID</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Requirement</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Level</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Clinical System</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Terminology Management</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Information Design</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_21" xreflabel="21">21</entry>
                        <entry>Represent the author of a change</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_22" xreflabel="22">22</entry>
                        <entry>Represent the system or sub-system of an asset</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_23" xreflabel="23">23</entry>
                        <entry>Represent the path or branch of an asset version</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_24" xreflabel="24">24</entry>
                        <entry>Support search using lexical or logical criteria</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_25" xreflabel="25">25</entry>
                        <entry>Support detailed view of assets and diverse properties, filtering
                            content not relevant to the chosen context</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_26" xreflabel="26">26</entry>
                        <entry>Add terminology assets, including concepts, terms, relationships,
                            definitions, value sets, maps, and others</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_27" xreflabel="27">27</entry>
                        <entry>Deactivate assets, preserving their original form</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_28" xreflabel="28">28</entry>
                        <entry>Modify assets, preserving their original form</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_29" xreflabel="=29">29</entry>
                        <entry>Classify assets using identified tools and logical profiles in chosen
                            contexts, with the option to persist the inferred assets</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry xml:id="requirement_30" xreflabel="30">30</entry>
                        <entry>Process a set of content for publication, including identification
                            and resolution of unresolved constraints</entry>
                        <entry>Function</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                        <entry align="center">x</entry>
                        <entry align="center"/>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        
        
    </section>
</chapter>
