<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
     <title>Terminology Knowledge</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction to Concepts and Codes</title>
        <para>Terminology systems are increasingly critical components for achieving
            interoperability across applications in the healthcare domain. The role of standard
            terminologies in achieving interoperability for the purposes of advancing patient care
            is well documented. Ideally, these clinical terminology standards intend to provide
            rules to allow for the exchange, integration, and management of electronic clinical
            information. The federal government recognizes the benefit of standard terminologies and
            promotes their development and use. The
                <?oxy_comment_start author="tocrow" timestamp="20240624T130607-0400" comment="Cite"?><emphasis
                role="italic">Federal Health IT Strategic Plan
            2015-2020</emphasis><?oxy_comment_end?> set a strategy to encourage consistent
            terminology standards implementation in Electronic Health Records (EHRs) and encourage
            use through federal payment policies. </para>
        <para>Standards are obtained from a variety of efforts, cover different domains of clinical
            and nonclinical content relevant to the EHR, and serve various purposes. Currently, no
            single terminology or classification system contains everything that is needed for the
            medical record. </para>
        <para>Terminology systems typically consist of the following elements: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Coded Concepts – the discrete units of knowledge managed within the
                    terminology. They typically consist of numeric codes and textual preferred
                    names, synonyms, and descriptions. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Concept Hierarchies – the logical organization of concepts into parent-child
                    and ancestor-descendant relationships that express the semantics of
                    generalization and specialization. The hierarchical organization of a
                    terminology may be explicitly expressed through stored parent-child and
                    ancestor-descendant links, or it may be implicitly expressed through the logical
                    definitions of individual concepts that a computer can use to infer parent-child
                    and ancestor-descendant relationships. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Value Sets – named lists of individual concepts that represent more abstract
                    categories useful in decision-support logic.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>New applications and new medical knowledge constantly call for expansion and
            enhancement of existing terminologies. However, since terminology systems are often
            non-static, incomplete and under specified, inconsistencies may be introduced. </para>
        <para>While many of these challenges are related to terminology evolution, others may be
            related to the design of the standard clinical terminologies themselves. Cimino notably
            described the challenges of concept orientation, completeness, correctness, currency,
            granularity, and redundancy when designing re-usable medical terminologies. Today a
            menagerie of inconsistent and overlapping terminology models hinders efforts that try to
            store and analyze encoded clinical data. The scope of content covered in terminologies
            varies from focusing on a very specific domain to covering multiple domains.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What is Logical Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes (LOINC®)?</title>
        <para>Bodenreider et al. provide an overview of LOINC®:</para>
        <para><emphasis>LOINC® is a clinical terminology for identifying health measurements,
                observations, and documents. LOINC® was initiated in 1994 by the Regenstrief
                Institute, a non-profit medical research organization associated with Indiana
                University. By 1994, many electronic systems were sending clinical information as
                discrete results using messaging standards such as Health Level Seven (HL7) or ASTM
                1238 (American Society for Testing and Materials). Inside these messages,
                laboratories and clinical systems used local, idiosyncratic names and codes to
                identify which test was being reported. This practice was problematic for data
                exchange and aggregation because of the large resources it takes to map codes
                between every participating system.</emphasis></para>
        <para><emphasis>To solve this problem, Regenstrief organized the LOINC® Committee to develop
                a common terminology for laboratory and clinical observations. Existing
                terminologies were not granular enough, focused on coding for billing rather than
                clinical results delivery, or did not fit with the messaging models being used.
                Because such a standard did not exist, the LOINC® Committee embarked on creating a
                terminology with [an] appropriate level of granularity for defining the names of
                observations used in laboratory and clinical information systems. Since its
                creation, LOINC® has continued to be developed and published by the Regenstrief
                Institute as a freely available global standard with a set of implementation tools.
                Today, LOINC® is used by a diverse global community that propels its continuous
                development.</emphasis></para>
        <para><emphasis>LOINC's® primary role is to provide identifiers and names for observations.
                Here, observation [is used] as a generic term for health data represented in a
                particular way. In different domains, these might be called tests, variables, or
                data elements. Within and among health IT systems, observations are communicated
                with a structure that has two key structural elements. The first element identifies
                what the observation is, e.g., diastolic blood pressure, hematocrit, tobacco smoking
                status. The second element carries the result value of the observation, e.g., 80
                (mmHg), 40 (%), or “current everyday smoker”. When used together, these two elements
                carry the instance of a specific test result for a given patient. A common pairing
                is to use LOINC® as the standard code for the observation, and Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms® (SNOMED CT®) as the
                standard code for the observation value, when needed. This approach is endorsed by
                the developers of both terminologies and fits their design
            purpose.</emphasis></para>
        <para><emphasis>Some mistakenly believe that LOINC® is only for laboratory tests. It is true
                that the first release of LOINC® in May 1995 contained only terms for laboratory
                testing, but by December of 1996, LOINC® had already added about 1,500 clinical
                measurement terms (vital signs, ECG measures, etc). Now, more than 20 years and 60
                releases later, LOINC® has grown significantly in other domains, including
                radiology, standardized survey instruments and patient-reported outcomes measures,
                clinical documents, nursing management data, and nursing assessments. The LOINC®
                Committee itself is now composed of three major composite committees: Laboratory,
                Clinical, and Radiology. </emphasis>[1]</para>
        <section>
            <title>LOINC® Current State</title>
            <para>Regenstrief continues to update LOINC® and publish twice-yearly releases. New
                concepts are added to LOINC® based on submissions from end users. The current
                version contains more than 99,000 terms covering the full scope of laboratory
                testing (chemistry, microbiology, molecular pathology, …etc.) and a broad range of
                clinical measurements (e.g., vital signs, ECG, patient-reported outcomes, …etc.). In
                addition to distributing the terminology, Regenstrief makes available at no cost a
                variety of supporting tools and resources, including the Regenstrief LOINC® Mapping
                Assistant (RELMA®) and online search application.</para>
            <para>LOINC® uses a semantic data model containing six major and up to four minor
                attributes to create fully-specified names for concepts. The major attributes of the
                LOINC® name are:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Component (e.g., what is measured, evaluated, or observed)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Kind of property (e.g., mass, substance, catalytic activity)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Time aspect (e.g., 24-hour collection)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>System type (e.g., context or specimen type within which the observation
                        was made)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Type of scale (e.g., ordinal, nominal, narrative)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Type of method (e.g., procedure used to make the measurement or
                        observation).</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>The atomic elements that make up each LOINC® term name are called “Parts” and are
                also assigned identifiers. The combination of attribute values produce term names
                that are [intended to be] detailed enough to distinguish among similar observations.
                Of the six attributes, only the method is optional and used only when necessary to
                distinguish among clinical important differences. </para>
            <para>“A fully specified test result or clinical observation can be described formally
                with the following syntax: &lt;Analyte/component>:&lt;kind of property of
                observation or measurement>:&lt;time aspect>:&lt;system
                (sample)>:&lt;scale>:-&lt;method>.” [2]</para>
            <para>Over time, LOINC® has not only grown in size, but also developed additional data
                structures and content around its main codes for individual observations. The LOINC®
                release contains a basic hierarchy that organizes LOINC® codes into a set of is-a
                relationships. LOINC® now has a detailed model for representing enumerated
                collections of observations, such as laboratory panels (complete blood count),
                assessment instruments (e.g., PHQ-9), data sets (National Trauma Data Standard), and
                forms (e.g., U.S. Standard Birth Certificate). This content is published in a
                special release artifact called the LOINC® Database, with the current version
                (August 2022) containing more than 99,000 terms. LOINC® also has a detailed model
                for connecting observation terms to structured answer lists. These answer lists can
                be defined by extension or intension and linked to observation terms with different
                types (e.g., example, preferred, normative). This content is published in the LOINC®
                Answer List File, with the current version (August 2022) containing links between
                25,640 unique LOINC® terms and 4,341 unique answer lists composed of coded LOINC®
                Answers, and including mappings to other terminologies such as SNOMED CT® where they
                exist. LOINC® now also publishes the atomic elements (called Parts) that make up
                each LOINC® term name. The LOINC® Part File includes the Part identifiers and names,
                links between Parts and LOINC® terms, and mappings from LOINC® Parts to other
                terminologies such as SNOMED CT® and RxNorm where they exist.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>LOINC® Collaboration</title>
            <para>The following <emphasis role="italic">italicized excerpts</emphasis> provide an
                overview of Regenstrief’s relationship with the health community in the development
                of LOINC®. Non italicized text reflects updates and discussion to reflect the
                current state. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Regenstrief is committed to working with developers of
                    health data standards that are complementary to LOINC®, including syntax
                    standards for data exchange and other terminology standards. Regenstrief and HL7
                    have a long-standing collaboration; a few joint work highlights include clinical
                    genomics guides, claims attachments specifications, and approaches for
                    representing vocabulary standards in Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources
                    (FHIR) terminology services. Regenstrief Institute made core LOINC® content
                    available via a FHIR API as part of its normal release process beginning Summer
                    2018.</emphasis></para>
            <para>In April 2022, a LOINC® Terminology Service using the FHIR Standard was launched
                with an API that provides a means for users to access LOINC® content across multiple
                versions programmatically.]</para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Regenstrief and the Institute of Electrical and
                    Electronics Engineers (IEEE) Standards Association, developer of the 11073™
                    standards, are collaborating to enhance the interoperability of traditional
                    medical devices and personal health devices. Regenstrief is an active member of
                    the Health Standards Collaborative (HSC) which provides an executive forum for
                    senior leadership of the U.S. healthcare standards development community to
                    improve interoperability. In 2017, Regenstrief worked with the In Vitro
                    Diagnostic (IVD) Industry Connectivity Consortium (IICC) on a specification for
                    publishing vendor IVD tests associated with a set of LOINC® codes that identify
                    the distinct observations produced by the test.</emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">In the context of the specifications of the U.S.
                    Meaningful Use incentive program, LOINC® is the primary choice for specifying
                    attributes, and SNOMED CT® the system of use for the relevant attribute values.
                    In other words, LOINC® is used to specify the question (e.g., 29308-4: “what is
                    the diagnosis?”), and SNOMED CT® to specify the answer (e.g., 3723001:
                    “Arthritis”). Adoption of this principle by both the Regenstrief Institute and
                    SNOMED International has formed the basis for the cooperation agreement. In
                    2013, Regenstrief and SNOMED International formed a long-term collaborative
                    relationship to link the rich clinical semantics of SNOMED CT® to LOINC®, which
                    provides extensive coverage of laboratory tests and clinical measurements.
                </emphasis>[1]</para>
            <para>While the initial partnership and memorandum of understanding signed between
                SNOMED CT® and LOINC® developers paved the way
                for development teams to facilitate interoperability and minimize duplication of
                effort, the collaborative relationship did not accomplish a complete integration of
                the two disparate terminologies. Further integration has been proposed to leverage
                SNOMED CT®’s model for the representation of LOINC® building blocks and for a more
                consistent representation of clinical and laboratory observations in SNOMED CT®.
                Furthermore, the use of description logics for the representation of LOINC® was not
                accomplished under this initial partnership in 2013 and only SNOMED CT® currently
                uses this formalism. LOINC® still uses its distinct formalisms and tools for its
                representation, has its own release cycles and versioning mechanisms, which makes
                seamless integration with SNOMED CT® non trivial, if possible at all. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What is
            <?oxy_comment_start author="tocrow" timestamp="20240624T153502-0400" comment="spell out?"?>SNOMED
            CT®<?oxy_comment_end?>?</title>
        <para>Bodenreider et al. provide an overview of SNOMED International: </para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Since the inception of the Systematized Nomenclature of
                Pathology (SNOP) in 1965, the various versions of SNOMED have developed both in
                terms of content and underlying representation. Development of content is clearly
                illustrated by the number of elements in the various systems. SNOP comprised “about
                15,000 distinct medical objects, processes, and concepts”. It developed further into
                SNOMED-2, and later SNOMED International, which contained 150,000 concepts in the
                mid-1990s. Its successor, SNOMED Reference Terminology (SNOMED RT), contained over
                120,000 active concepts. The initial version of SNOMED CT®, the merger of SNOMED RT®
                and the UK-based Clinical Terms Version 3, released January 2002, consisted of
                278,000 active concepts, a number that has grown to 350,000+ in the January 2022
                release of SNOMED CT®. The representation has gone through phases of increasing
                formal rigor. The initial SNOP and SNOMED versions were multi-axial systems that
                enabled post-coordination. Whereas SNOP started as a 4-axis system, SNOMED
                International had expanded to using 12 axes: anatomy (topography), morphology
                (pathologic structure), normal and abnormal functions, symptoms and signs of
                disease, chemicals, drugs, enzymes and other body proteins, living organisms,
                physical agents, spatial relationships, occupations, social contexts,
                diseases/diagnoses and procedures. SNOMED RT® abandoned the use of self-standing
                axes that could be combined into composite codes in favor of a description logic
                formalism called Ontylog, based on the Knowledge Representation System Specification
                (KRSS) syntax and the K-REP system. Following contemporary naming conventions for
                description logics, the set of constructors used corresponds to the
                </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">ℰℒ ++ language. SNOMED CT® has continued to use
                this description logic as its underlying representation. The evolution of the
                representation of “arthritis” through the history of
                <?oxy_comment_start author="naylee" timestamp="20231130T113252-0600" comment="SNOMED here is fine since it&apos;s referring to the general history since its inception in 1965."?>SNOMED<?oxy_comment_end?>
                provides an illustration of editorial changes over time, with examples from
                SNOMED-2, SNOMED International, and the current version of SNOMED CT®.</emphasis>
            [1]</para>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED CT® Current State</title>
            <para>Regarding the current state, Bodenreider, et al., go on to say:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Since the first release of SNOMED CT® in January 2003,
                    updated versions have been released twice a year. Maintenance can lead to a
                    decrease of the number of elements, e.g., in January 2010 when, among others,
                    the veterinary content was removed from the International Release.
                </emphasis>[1]</para>
            <para>The July 2022 release contains 356,817 active concepts, 1,202,379 active
                relationships and 1,286,456 active descriptions. The largest categories of concepts
                in SNOMED CT® are disorders (23%), procedures (16%), body structures (11%), clinical
                findings other than disorders (10%), and organisms (9%). In SNOMED CT® parlance,
                descriptions are labels that describe the concepts, not textual definitions of the
                concept, of which SNOMED CT® contains 9762. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">A significant design criterion for SNOMED CT® is to keep
                    concept expressions simple enough to be broadly usable by clinicians, while
                    maintaining faithful representation of concept meaning. Validity of concept
                    expressions is determined by adherence to the concept model underlying SNOMED
                    CT®. This concept model specifies which types of relationship are allowed for
                    which concepts, and what the allowed values are. For example, the concept model
                    specifies that “Method” is an allowed attribute relationship for “Procedure”
                    concepts, for which the value should be a type of “Action”. The January 2018
                    release uses 82 relationship types, almost twice the number of the initial 42
                    relationship types. Since July 2017, the concept model is available in
                    machine-readable form, and distributed as separate tables which are part of the
                    semi-annual releases. Other tables provide mappings to several versions of the
                    International Classification of Diseases (ICD9-CM, ICD-10 and ICD-O). The
                    current release format, called Release Format 2 (RF2), supports versioning,
                    providing access to any previous release of SNOMED CT®.</emphasis></para>
            <para>While SNOMED CT® has made much progress in their use of description logics, and
                have also provided a tool on github, snomed-owl-toolkit, to facilitate the
                conversion and classification process, the official distribution of OWL refsets has
                yet to be seen. It seems one reason is the lack of current clinical systems to
                utilize them at this time. [3-4]</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED CT® Collaborations</title>
            <para>Here’s an excerpt of what Bodreider et al. have to say about Collaboration
                Initiatives:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">SNOMED CT® is not developing in isolation, but
                    increasingly collaborating and harmonizing with other relevant standards in the
                    area of structured and standardized storage and exchange of biomedical data.
                    This includes mapping, as well as binding of information model and terminology.
                    Mappings are maintained between SNOMED CT® and a number of terminology systems.
                    These include the World Health Organization (WHO) classifications (e.g.,
                    versions ICD-10 and ICD-O of the International Classification of Diseases), as
                    well as the International Classification of Primary Care (ICPC-2), the
                    International Classification for Nursing Practice (ICNP), and LOINC®. The latter
                    is especially important in the context of the specifications of the U.S.
                    Meaningful Use incentive program, in which LOINC® is the primary choice for
                    specifying attributes, and SNOMED CT® the system of use for the relevant
                    attribute values. In other words, LOINC® is used to specify the question (e.g.,
                    29308-4: “what is the diagnosis?”), and SNOMED CT® to specify the answer (e.g.,
                    3723001: “Arthritis”). Adoption of this principle by both the Regenstrief
                    Institute and SNOMED International has formed the basis for a cooperation
                    agreement in 2013.</emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">SNOMED CT® also has collaborations for specific domains.
                    In the context of rare diseases, collaboration with Orphanet leads to
                    harmonization of content between SNOMED CT® and ORDO, the Orphanet ontology of
                    rare diseases. Medical device terminology is addressed in collaboration with the
                    Global Medical Device Nomenclature Agency (GMDNA). Finally, Kaiser Permanente’s
                    Convergent Medical Terminology (CMT) provides concepts and descriptions to be
                    considered for inclusion. Moreover, SNOMED CT® forms the backbone for the
                    development of national extensions by member countries of SNOMED International.
                    National extensions typically contain concepts that are important in a given
                    country, but not in scope for the international release of SNOMED CT®. Other
                    extensions, such as the veterinary extension, contain content specific to a
                    given community of practice.</emphasis>[1]</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What is RxNorm?</title>
        <para>RxNorm is a terminology for human clinical drugs in the U.S., representing drug
            properties such as ingredient, strength, and dose form, maintained by the National
            Library of Medicine (NLM) and distributed via the Unified Medical Language System
            (UMLS).</para>
        <para>RxNorm provides normalized clinical drug names and relationships between those names
            and common drug vocabularies for the purpose of easing the exchange of clinical drug
            information between systems that use different drug vocabularies. Every concept in
            RxNorm is given a unique Concept Unique Identifiers (RxCUIs). The names and codes from
            the common drug vocabularies are then linked to that RxCUI.</para>
        <para><inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/RxNorm.svg" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para>Here’s an excerpt of Bodenreider et al. overview of RxNorm:</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">At the dawn of the twenty-first century, there was no standard
                terminology for drugs in the U.S.. While many companies provide information about
                drugs for use in clinical information systems (e.g., to support clinical decision),
                each drug knowledge base defines its own codes and names for medications, making it
                difficult to exchange information across clinical information systems and to
                retrieve information from different systems. For example, the same transdermal patch
                delivering 0.583 milligrams of nicotine per hour for 24 hours (e.g., to help with
                smoking cessation) is referred to with the following codes and names in three of the
                major drug knowledge bases: • 2707 nicotine 14 mg/24 hr transdermal film, extended
                release • 102712 Nicotine 14 MG/24 HR Transdermal Patch, Extended Release • 016426
                NICOTINE 14 mg/24 hour T R A N S D E R M P A T C H , TRANSDERMAL 24 HOURS In
                addition to capitalization differences, there is a lack of standardization in naming
                dose forms (transdermal film vs. transdermal patch) and units (24 hr vs. 24 hour),
                making it difficult to parse names from multiple systems. RxNorm was created to
                address the lack of standardization in drug names, and to make drug terminologies
                interoperable by integrating them into a reference system. Since the 1990s, the NLM
                has released the UMLS, a terminology integration system in which names and codes
                from all major biomedical terminologies are integrated, and equivalent terms across
                vocabularies are identified. RxNorm can be thought of as a specialized version of
                the UMLS. While both UMLS and RxNorm are built upon existing vocabularies, one major
                difference between the two is that UMLS generally does not create names for
                biomedical entities. In contrast, RxNorm creates a “normal form” for every drug
                entity it integrates. In RxNorm parlance, normal forms are standardized terms for
                drug entities. For example, the normal form for the nicotine patch discussed above
                is “24 HR Nicotine 0.583 MG/HR Transdermal System”, to which RxNorm permanently
                assigns the concept unique identifier 198029. Unlike the UMLS, RxNorm also defines a
                rich network of named relationships among the various types of drug entities it
                integrates (e.g., ingredient, brand name, generic drug product, branded drug
                product). The main use cases RxNorm was designed to support include electronic
                prescribing, drug information exchange, and mapping across drug vocabularies (e.g.,
                for medication reconciliation purposes). Standard names and codes for drugs were
                also expected to facilitate the development of standard clinical decision support
                rules involving medications. RxNorm started in 2002. It was first released through
                the UMLS and has been published as an independent terminology with monthly releases
                since November 2004, and weekly updates since 2008 to reflect drugs recently
                marketed in the U.S. market. The number of sources integrated in RxNorm has grown
                from 5 to 13.</emphasis>[1]</para>
        <section>
            <title>RxNorm Current State</title>
            <para>Bodenreider et al. go on to talk about the current state:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Status: RxNorm currently integrates terminology
                    information from most drug knowledge base vendors (e.g., First DataBank, Multum,
                    Micromedex, Gold Standard), as well as the drug component of standard
                    terminologies (e.g., SNOMED CT®, MeSH). RxNorm also integrates sources from
                    several public entities. More recently, RxNorm has also integrated international
                    drug resources, such as the Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) Classification
                    System and DrugBank, a drug resource used in many research projects.
                </emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Organization: The RxNorm drug model distinguishes between
                    generic and branded drug entities and identifies three major definitional
                    elements for drug products, namely ingredient, strength, and dose form, along
                    with two additional elements, quantity factor and qualitative distinction. The
                    major types of drug entities include ingredient (e.g., Azithromycin), brand name
                    (e.g., Zithromax), clinical drug (e.g., Azithromycin 250 MG Oral Tablet), and
                    branded drug (e.g., Zithromax 250 MG Oral Tablet). Generic and branded packs are
                    collections of clinical and branded drugs, respectively (e.g., Z-PAK, a branded
                    pack of 6 tablets of 250 milligrams of azithromycin). While drugs are sold
                    mostly pre-packaged in some countries (e.g., individual tablets in blister
                    packs), packs are available for a minority of drugs in the U.S. In addition to
                    the six major drug entities, RxNorm provides entities for navigational purposes.
                    Clinical and branded drug components associate ingredient (or brand name) and
                    strength information, and clinical and branded dose forms associate ingredient
                    (or brand name) and dose form information.</emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">The various types of drug entities in RxNorm are organized
                    into a graph that can be easily traversed, enabling users to navigate among
                    types of entities (e.g., to find the branded drugs associated with a given
                    ingredient). While its main organization principles have remained centered on
                    the ingredient-strength-dose form triad, RxNorm has added definitional features
                    to accommodate distinctions, such as duration for extended release forms and
                    transdermal systems (e.g., the quantity factor “24 HR” in “24 HR Nicotine 0.583
                    MG/HR Transdermal System”) and size of unit of presentation for injectable
                    medications (e.g., the quantity factor “40 ML” in “40 ML Ciprofloxacin 10 MG/ML
                    Injection”), as well as qualitative elements for specific drugs (e.g., the
                    qualitative distinction “Sugar-Free” in “Sugar-Free Cholestyramine Resin 4000 MG
                    Powder for Oral Suspension”). A drug product in RxNorm is fully defined by its
                    set of ingredient, strength, dose form, quantity factor, and qualitative
                    distinction values. Types of ingredients include multi-ingredients (e.g.,
                    Sulfamethoxazole / Trimethoprim) and “precise ingredients” (e.g., Atorvastatin
                    calcium, Morphine Sulfate), generally denoting, salts, esters, and complexes of
                    base substances. As illustrated in the examples above, RxNorm normal forms
                    reflect the definitional features of drug entities. Additionally, RxNorm
                    explicitly links drug entities to these features, which supports efficient
                    processing. For example, the generic nicotine patch “24 HR Nicotine 0.583 MG/HR
                    Transdermal System” is linked to its ingredient (Nicotine), strength (0.583
                    MG/HR), dose form (Transdermal System), and quantity factor (“24 HR”).
                </emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">The scope of RxNorm is different from that of drug
                    knowledge bases. RxNorm focuses on drug names and codes. In other words,
                    clinical information (e.g., indications, drug classes, and drug-drug
                    interactions) and administrative information (e.g., drug pricing) are out of
                    scope for RxNorm. Although it integrates international sources (e.g., ATC,
                    DrugBank), RxNorm focuses on drug products marketed in the U.S. Finally,
                    non-therapeutic radiopharmaceuticals, bulk powders, contrast media, food,
                    dietary supplements, and medical devices, such as bandages and crutches, are all
                    out of scope for RxNorm. In addition to the codes from drug terminologies and
                    knowledge bases, RxNorm integrates codes from the US Food and Drug
                    Aministration's (FDA) National Drug Code (NDC) Directory, which serve as product
                    identifiers for drugs in billing transactions, and contains links to Structured
                    Product Labels (i.e., package inserts) submitted by drug manufacturers to the
                    FDA..</emphasis>[1]</para>
            <para>The September 2022 edition of RxNorm includes 13856 (base) ingredients, 5065 brand
                names, 17226 semantic clinical drugs, 9424 semantic branded drugs, 474 generic
                packs, and 543 branded backs. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">With each monthly update, the RxNorm content is kept
                    current and in sync with drugs available on the U.S. market, i.e., new drug
                    products are added and drug products no longer available are retired. RxNorm
                    identifiers are never reused and can be safely used as permanent identifiers for
                    drugs in clinical data warehouses and prescription datasets. However, any given
                    release of RxNorm only contains detailed information about active drug products
                    in that release.</emphasis></para>
            <para>In 2019 Medication - Reference Terminology (MED-RT) replaced National Drug File -
                Reference Terminology (NDF-RT). [5] RxNorm is available as a resource in the HL7
                FHIR website. While it is currently in Standard for Trial Use (STU), it has been
                advancing through the HL7 Ballot Levels to expose the RxNorm content as medication
                resources. [6]</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>RxNorm Collaborations</title>
            <para>In regards to RxNorm collaborations, Bodenreider, et al. has this to say:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">In the development of RxNorm content, NLM has worked in
                    close collaboration with the vendors of drug knowledge bases, with federal
                    partners, and with representatives of the pharmacy services industry represented
                    by the National Council for Prescription Drug Program (NCPDP). Similarly, the
                    development of RxNav and the RxNorm API have greatly benefited from the feedback
                    provided by their user community. For the past five years, NLM has held an
                    annual DailyMed/RxNorm Jamboree Workshop to bring together the RxNorm
                    stakeholders. To extend the usefulness of RxNorm despite its limited scope, NLM
                    has also initiated partnerships with providers of clinical information that can
                    be linked to RxNorm. For example, NLM has developed companion APIs to link
                    RxNorm drugs to various drug classification systems and to publicly available
                    sources of drug-drug interaction information. Drug classes for RxNorm drugs can
                    also be explored through the RxClass application.</emphasis></para>
            <para>The table below is a comparison of terminologies on how well they meet Cimino’s
                Desiderata. [7] The Desiderata is a list of attributes needed for a standard
                terminology to meet the needs of its users. SNOMED CT® is the only terminology that
                meets all the requirements as described by Cimino. However, as noted above, SNOMED
                CT® has proprietary elements that limits its usefulness for interoperability.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Met Criteria of LOINC®, SNOMED CT® and RxNorm to Cimino’s Desiderata</title>
                    <tgroup cols="4">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Tenant</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept Orientation</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>None</entry>
                                <entry>Complete</entry>
                                <entry>Complete</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept Permanence</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Complete</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Partial</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Non-Semantic Concept
                                        Identifier</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Complete</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Polyhierarchical</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>None</entry>
                                <entry>Complete</entry>
                                <entry>Complete</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Formal Definitions</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>None</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Partial</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Classification</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>None</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Multiple
                                    Granularities</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>None</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Multiple Consistent
                                    Views</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>None</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Representation of
                                    Context</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>None</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Complete</para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Unified Medical Language System (UMLS)</title>
        <para>The NLM integrates terms and codes from over 150 source vocabularies by concept,
            attribute, and meaning in a set of files and software called the UMLS. The UMLS brings
            together many health and biomedical vocabularies and standards to enable
            interoperability between computer systems.</para>
        <para>The UMLS is used to enhance or develop applications such as electronic health records,
            classification tools, dictionaries and language translators. The UMLS has been used to
            link health information, medical terms, drug names, and billing codes across different
            computer systems. Additionally, the UMLS has been used to aid in search engine
            retrieval, data mining, public health statistics reporting, and terminology
            research.</para>
        <para>The UMLS has three tools:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Metathesaurus</emphasis>: Terms and codes from many
                    vocabularies, including Current Procedural Terminology (CPT®), ICD-10-CM,
                    LOINC®, MeSH®, RxNorm, and SNOMED CT®</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Semantic Network</emphasis>: Broad categories (semantic
                    types) and their relationships (semantic relations)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">SPECIALIST Lexicon and Lexical Tools</emphasis>: Natural
                    language processing tools</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The Semantic Network and Lexical Tools are used to produce the Metathesaurus. The
            steps to produce the Metathesaurus involve:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Processing the terms and codes from source terminologies using the Lexical
                    Tools</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Grouping synonymous terms into UMLS concepts</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Categorizing concepts by semantic types using the Semantic Network</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Incorporating relationships and attributes provided by source
                    terminologies</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Releasing the data in a common format called the Rich Release Format
                    (RRF)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>These tools, while helpful, have gaps. Raje et al. highlighted issues with
            completeness, correctness, and redundancy when they found gaps in the UMLS
            Metathesaurus’ coverage of disease concepts.
                <citation><?oxy_comment_start author="tocrow" timestamp="20240624T152747-0400" comment="Cite"?>Raje<?oxy_comment_end?></citation>
            The UMLS does not necessarily look at semantic equivalence of concepts across or within
            terminologies, rather focuses on lexical equivalence. A good example of this is how the
            UMLS has represented content from SNOMED CT® in the pharmaceutical product and substance
            hierarchies. SNOMED CT® has separate concepts to represent the substance that makes up a
            pharmaceutical product, for example acetaminophen, and a higher level concept in the
            pharmaceutical product hierarchy that is used to group products together (all products
            that contain acetaminophen). In the UMLS these concepts are grouped together under a
            single UMLS Concept Unique Identifier (CUI).</para>
        <para>These issues related to integrating clinical content have a direct impact on patient
            safety and point to the need to be able to consistently represent and encode clinical
            data and observations. Therefore, quality assurance is an indispensable part of the
            terminology management lifecycle. A central limitation of integrating controlled medical
            terminologies is that they often lack any formal model to denote the relationships among
            constituent data elements. </para>
        <para>Recently, however, development teams for SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, and RxNorm have partnered
            to promote interoperability. Developers can now leverage SNOMED CT®’s representation
            model for the building blocks of LOINC®, and a new drug model in SNOMED CT® facilitates
            extensions and consistency to RxNorm. Bodenreider et al. wrote about the recent
            collaboration: “while this evolution leads to greater compatibility and
            interoperability, integration of SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, and RxNorm still requires mappings
            among the three terminologies. Moreover, these three terminologies use different
            formalisms and tools for their representation, have their own release cycles and
            versioning mechanisms, which makes their seamless integration non trivial, if at all
            possible.” </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Value Set Authority Center (VSAC)</title>
    
        <para>The NLM, also, in collaboration with the Office of the National Coordinator for Health
            Information Technology and Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, hosts the Value
            Set Authority Center (VSAC). The VSAC aims to provide lists of values, codes, and names
            (i.e., value sets) from standard clinical terminologies to represent clinical concepts.
            Similarly, Winnenburg et al. highlighted duplicate value sets in the VSAC, and showed
            that 19% of value sets in 2011 contained invalid codes.
                <citation><?oxy_comment_start author="tocrow" timestamp="20240624T153159-0400" comment="Cite"?>Winnenburg<?oxy_comment_end?></citation>
            In subsequent work, they highlighted issues related to granularity by evaluating over
            1,000 value sets and found that value sets varied vastly in size with some only
            containing one code, while other value sets included over 20,000 codes.
                <citation><?oxy_comment_start author="tocrow" timestamp="20240624T153204-0400" comment="Cite"?>Winnenburg2<?oxy_comment_end?></citation>
            Similarly, Bahr et al. showed issues with concept orientation by analyzing medication
            value sets and found extraneous and missing ingredients in both the value sets and drug
                classes.<citation><?oxy_comment_start author="tocrow" timestamp="20240624T153212-0400" comment="Cite"?>Bahr<?oxy_comment_end?></citation>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Observational Medical Outcomes Partnership (OMOP)</title>
        <para>Observational Health Data Sciences and Informatics (OHDSI) created OMOP Common Data
            Model (CDM) to inform the appropriate use of observational healthcare databases for
            studying the effects of medical products. ATHENA is used to harmonize disparate coding
            systems—with minimal information loss—to a standardized vocabulary. The Standard
            Vocabulary is a foundational tool that enables transparent and consistent content across
            disparate observational databases, and serves to support the OHDSI research community in
            conducting efficient and reproducible observational research.</para>
        <para>OHDSI categorizes source terminology concepts in three ways:<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Standard Concept:</emphasis> "official" concepts
                    used to represent unique clinical entities in the CDM.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Classification Concept:</emphasis> have a
                    hierarchical relationship to Standard Concepts and can be used to query for
                    Standard Concepts using the records of the CONCEPT_ANCESTOR table. However,
                    they cannot appear in the Data Tables.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Source Concept:</emphasis> all remaining Concepts
                    that are not Standard or Classification Concepts </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>OHDSI's Standard Vocabulary relies heavily on mapping non-standard concepts to the
            Standard Concepts.  </para>
    </section>
    <xi:include href="Book%20SOLOR%20Terminology.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    <section>
        <title>Language</title>
        <para>Language is used to describe identified components. While the initial focus of
            Integrated Knowledge Management (IKM) will be to use the English language versions from
            the foundational coding systems, support for other languages will be included as a part
            of future iterations.</para>
        <section>
        <title>Language Layer Concerns</title>
        <section xml:id="section_ed272173-6351-49e9-8503-abffd8bc18bb">
            <title>Language</title>
            <para>SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, and RxNorm as well as other coding systems have various ways
                of representing language. </para>
            <para>Descriptions in SNOMED CT® include one Fully Specified Name and at least one
                synonym for each language. The Preferred and Acceptable Synonyms per language are
                then specified in a Language Reference Set. Any additional synonyms, other than the
                preferred, that are relevant for a language would be identifed as acceptable.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Description and RefSet Values for Myocardial infarction</title>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Description Term</entry>
                            <entry>Description Type</entry>
                            <entry>Refset(s)</entry>
                            <entry>Refset Acceptability</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Myocardial infarction (disorder)</entry>
                            <entry>Fully Specified Name</entry>
                            <entry>United States (US) and Great Britain (GB) Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Myocardial infarction</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Infarction of heart</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Cardiac infarction</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Heart attack</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>MI - myocardial infarction</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Myocardial infarct</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>RxNorm identifies language in the RXNCONSO file in the STR field. The language of
                the name is specified in the LAT field and the source the name comes from is
                represented in the STT field. The names in the RXNCONSO are not unique as the same
                name can come from multiple sources.</para>
            <para>
                <table>
                    <title>RxNorm Strings Associated With "100 ML Acetaminophen 10 MG/ML
                        Injection"</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Property</entry>
                                <entry>STR</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Prescribable Synonym</entry>
                                <entry>acetaminophen 1000 MG in 100 ML Injection</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>RxNorm Name</entry>
                                <entry>100 ML Acetaminophen 10 MG/ML Injection</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>RxNorm Synonym</entry>
                                <entry>acetaminophen 1000 MG per 100 ML Injection</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>RxNorm Synonym</entry>
                                <entry>100 ML APAP 10 MG/ML Injection</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para>LOINC® has names spread across multiple fields with the Fully Specified Name
                constructed as a concatenation of the six parts. It also contains a Long Common Name
                and a Short Name. The screenshot from Komet below exemplifies the 6 LOINC® parts:
                Component, Method, Property, Scale, System, and Timing. </para>
            <para>
                <table>
                    <title>LOINC® Representation of "Glucose [Presence] in Urine by Test strip --4.5
                        hours post 75 g glucose PO"</title>
                    <tgroup cols="6">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>COMPONENT</entry>
                                <entry>PROPERTY</entry>
                                <entry>TIME_ASPCT</entry>
                                <entry>SYSTEM</entry>
                                <entry>SCALE_TYP</entry>
                                <entry>METHOD_TYP</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Glucose^4.5H post 75 g glucose PO</entry>
                                <entry>PrThr</entry>
                                <entry>Pt</entry>
                                <entry>Urine</entry>
                                <entry>Ord</entry>
                                <entry>Test strip</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190610T132017-0600" comment="In the PDF, this example is cutoff and you can&apos;t see the full middle panel section and you can only see the first letter of each of the 6 components.  Needs fixing."?>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/LOINC_komet.png" scale="20"/><?oxy_comment_end?>
                    </imageobject>
                </inlinemediaobject></para>
            <para>Descriptions within a coding system can span multiple languages. For example,
                &quot;deja vu&quot; exists in both the French and English languages as it is the
                description used to describe the memory finding.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_2f530c57-07b6-4abf-9399-db11515f1977">
            <title>Dialect</title>
            <para>Merriam-Webster's Dictionary defines a dialect as &quot;a regional variety of
                language distinguished by features of vocabulary, grammar, and pronunciation from
                other regional varieties and constituting together with them a single
                language&quot;. Two common differences between dialects deal with spelling variants
                and phrases that have alternate meanings. An example of a spelling variant would be
                &quot;Anesthetic&quot; in the US dialect versus &quot;Anaesthetic&quot; in the
                British dialect. The same word in one dialect can mean have a different meaning in
                another, for example
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T153845-0700" comment="Is there a reason that quotes weren&apos;t used with this, like they were in the prior example?" flag="done"?>&quot;napkin&quot;<?oxy_comment_end?>
                in the US is used to describe a piece of cloth or paper used to wipe the hands and
                mouth at a table while in the United Kingdom it is used to describe a diaper. </para>
            <table>
                <title>Description and RefSet Values for Epidural anesthesia</title>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Description Term</entry>
                            <entry>Description Type</entry>
                            <entry>Refset(s)</entry>
                            <entry>Refset Acceptability</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Epidural anesthesia (procedure)</entry>
                            <entry>Fully Specified Name</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialects</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Epidural anesthesia</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Peridural anesthesia</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Local anesthetic epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>LA - Local anesthetic epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Epidural anaesthesia</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Preferred</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Peridural anaesthesia</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Local anaesthetic epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>LA - Local anaesthetic epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Epidural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Extradural block</entry>
                            <entry>Synonym</entry>
                            <entry>US and GB Dialect</entry>
                            <entry>Acceptable</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="section_7a5f5087-2a21-4b5e-8993-53fd045b53ff">
        <title>Cross Cutting Concerns</title>
        <section xml:id="section_ce7e4daf-e50d-4ada-93c7-305f036ce86d">
            <title>Understandability, Reproducibility, and Utility</title>
            <para>The language used to describe a component must be concordant with the underlying
                semantics of the object being identified. Therefore, there needs to be guidelines in
                place to ensure only correct terms are associated with an object in Solor.</para>
            <para>Having a consistent naming convention defined will assist with textual queries to identify duplicates when concepts are primitive and not able to be fully defined using relationships within Solor. Having a consistent way of representing Fully Specified Names will alleviate the issue of users creating duplicate concepts like &quot;Disorder of immune function&quot; and &quot;Immune function disorder&quot;.</para>
            <para>Consistent naming is also important to support effective retrieval. For example,
                the SNOMED CT® concept 386560004 |Glasgow coma score finding (finding)| has 13
                children all with the string Glasgow coma scale instead of Glasgow coma score. </para>
            <para>Another common issue is to add a synonym to a concept that is more specific than
                the concept itself. A concept should only have synonyms that accurately represent a
                concept and not any of its children. If a synonym has a more specific meaning, a new
                concept should be created.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="section_c3d7371d-1785-4e89-b280-9b4a53cd3665">
            <title>Language
                <?oxy_comment_start author="steph" timestamp="20190305T154146-0700" comment="This section should be revised so it can be read as in the prior sections.  Here&apos;s it&apos;s just a list of what appear to be definitions.  You at least need some introductory paragraph that explains what you have listed here. " flag="done"?>Query<?oxy_comment_end?>
                Requirements</title>
            <para>For a search engine to retrieve meaningful results, it must be able to understand
                common usages of everyday jargon, similar to how synonyms are used to help broaden
                the way to express the same word. This section describes several strategies used to
                help with a query.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Word variants</emphasis> – Similar to synonyms, word
                variants are used to express the same word. While synonyms are explicitly created as
                a term to describe a concept (for example, SNOMED CT®'s "Heart attack" and
                "Myocardial infarction"), word variants are utilized during searching to assist in
                finding the correct concept, rather than explicitly creating the term. Hypothetical
                example - if "kidney failure" is a term created for a concept, a word variant of
                'renal' could be created for 'kidney'. Instead of explicitly creating a separate
                term of "renal failure", this word variant could be utilized during searching to
                find all concepts that have the explicit term of "kidney failure" when a user enters
                "renal failure" by replacing "renal" with "kidney". This would create the burden of
                creating all possible variant terms for a given word.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Misspellings</emphasis> – Certain terms are more commonly
                misspelled when searching over healthcare descriptions. The ability for a search
                mechanism to recognize them and to search over both the correct and incorrect
                spellings will help to identify the correct concept. For example, perineal vs
                peroneal and aphagia vs aphasia. </para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Word order</emphasis> – Terms can be combined in different ways
                to mean the same synonym. The ability to search over a term in varying order of
                phrases is important. For example, Disorder of the eye vs Eye disorder.</para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Components query</emphasis> – The importance of this searching
                strategy comes into play when a certain focus is desired for the search result. For
                example, in LOINC®, there may be circumstances where a certain axis is desired for
                the search. Similarly, a certain hierarchy may be desired when searching in SNOMED
                CT®. For example, "cold" is a synonym of common cold (a disorder) in SNOMED CT®, and
                also exists as "cold sensation quality" (a qualifier value). By allowing users to
                limit the search criteria (disorder vs. qualifier), the most appropriate query
                result will be returned to the user.</para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Active and inactive</emphasis> – Concepts and terms will come
                in and out of use over time. This is often indicated by an active/inactive
                designation. In order to properly return concepts/terms that are active, query
                parameters must contain a parameter to designate if the query result should/should
                not return active and inactive concepts or terms.</para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Regular Expressions</emphasis> - Regular expression or regex is
                a sequence of characters that defines a search pattern. This pattern would allow a
                user to retrieve results based on a certain pattern. For example "a|b*" would return
                all "a", "b" and other b's that fits the pattern such as "bb", "bbb", "bab", etc.
                Since the depth and breadth of regular expression is beyond the scope of this
                document, various syntaxes, usage and explanation can be found in many resources
                such as <link xlink:href="https://regexr.com/"/>.</para>
        	<para><emphasis role="bold">Grouping Results by hierarchy</emphasis> - This search
                requirement can be thought of as a complement to "components query". After casting a
                wide net, results could be a bag of various terms (common cold vs. feeling cold)
                that may be cumbersome for users to sift through if it is not organized in an
                orderly fashion. Therefore, if results are placed together in a logical grouping, it
                would assist the user in finding the appropriate query result. For example, in
                SNOMED CT®, it may be worthwhile to group results by hierarchy (disorder vs.
                procedures) to allow a user to look for a result in a desired domain or in RxNorm
                where all Ingredient results are grouped separately from Semantic Clinical Drug
                results.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Definitional</title>
        <para>We, as humans, are able to express individual concepts and expand on just the name of
            the concept, because we are able to associate certain characteristics to individual
            concepts to further describe itself, as well as establishing connections or
            relationships between concepts. Once concepts have a meaning beyond just a name, and
            have relationships to other meaningful concepts, then reasoning can occur. </para>
        <para>While the purpose of Language is to provide necessary vocabulary to express various
            domains of medicine, the purpose of the Definitions are to expand on just a name to go
            with an idea - single concepts with a name by itself adds no value. In other words, a
            system must be capable of capturing not just the words of the concept, but also provide
            a mechanism to express characteristics of that concept (it has the color white [assuming
            color and white are already defined]) and relationships between concepts (it is a
            beta-blocker). Additionally, once relationships of meaningful concepts are established,
            reasoning can occur (beta-blocker is used to treat high blood pressure, therefore, it
            treats high blood pressure).</para>
        <para>Once a system is able to 'digest' the meaning of concepts, it can begin to utilize
            logic to conduct reasoning. In the field of computer science, the study of Description
            Logic is to represent the domain, then using these concepts to specify properties of
            objects and individuals occuring in the domain. Additionally, another feature of
            Description Logic is the capability to conduct reasoning on represented knowledge. The
            goal of this section is to first provide a primer to those who may not be fully immersed
            in the study of description logic, then an introduction to Solor designs to allow for a
            robust representation and relationships of concepts, followed by topics or concerns from
            Solor developers and contributors that necessitate a discussion on why these concerns
            could affect a system to conduct reasoning properly or successfully. </para>
    </section>
    <xi:include href="../definitional_primer.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    <xi:include href="../definitional_solorDesign.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    <xi:include href="../definitional_topicsOfConcern.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    <section>
        <title>Terminology Principles and Best Practices</title>
        <para>This section contains an overview of principles and best practices for terminology
            design and representation. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Understandable, Reproducible, Useful (URU)</title>
            <para>There are core evolutionary design principles called “Understandable,
                Reproducible, and Useful,” (URU) upon which SNOMED CT® development is still based.
                [8-9] These criteria describe an approach for improving data quality and increasing
                data integrity and agility: </para>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Understandable: the content can be processed by health IT
                                systems and understood by most healthcare providers without
                                reference to private or inaccessible information; </emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Reproducible: multiple users or systems apply the data to the
                            same situations and source data with an equivalent result;
                            and</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">Useful: data is fit-for-purpose – it has practical
                            value for data analysis in support of health information exchange,
                            research, and public health that requires information aggregated across
                            health IT systems. </emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <?oxy_comment_start author="tocrow" timestamp="20240624T154213-0400" comment="I think duplicative of book terminology intro"?>
            <title>The Desiderata for Controlled Medical Vocabularies in the 21st
                Century<?oxy_comment_end?></title>
            <para>Jim Cimino developed a series of tenants that are essential for a strong
                terminology model
                [7]:<?oxy_comment_start author="naylee" timestamp="20231129T142446-0600" comment="Bullets used and punctuated per Oxford Stye Guide"?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Concept Orientation</emphasis> – terms should be
                        exact in meaning and non-ambiguous </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Concept Permanence</emphasis> – once a concept is
                        created, its meaning will never be changed </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Non-Semantic Concept Identifier</emphasis> – every
                        concept must have a unique identifier </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Polyhierarchy</emphasis> – hierarchical arrangements
                        are necessary in medical vocabularies. “There seems to be almost universal
                        agreement that controlled medical vocabularies should have hierarchical
                        arrangements… There is some disagreement, however, as to whether concepts
                        should be classified according to a single taxonomy (strict hierarchy) or if
                        multiple classifications (polyhierarchy) can be allowed. Most available
                        standard vocabularies are strict hierarchies.”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Formal Definitions </emphasis>– “These definitions
                        are expressed as some collection of relationships to other concepts in the
                        vocabulary”</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Every Concept has a Classification</emphasis> -
                        reject “not elsewhere classified” </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Multiple Granularities</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Multiple Consistent Views</emphasis> – fine-grained
                        concepts should be able to be collapsed into more coarse-grained concepts
                        and appear as synonyms; and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Representation of Context - </emphasis>Beyond
                        medical concepts: representing context.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Knowledge Representation and Description Logic</title>
            <para>A report in the 2016 Yearbook of Medical Informatics defines terminology as “a
                system of concepts with assigned identifiers and human language terms, typically
                involving some kind of semantic hierarchy. Some systems may support the assignment
                of multiple terms, or synonyms, to a given concept; these may include terms in
                multiple natural languages, such as English or Dutch.” [10] This definition implies
                that knowledge representation for a terminology system may not always be based on a
                strict defining hierarchy. The advantage, or disadvantage, of such an approach is
                that the terminology, such as LOINC® for instance, might appear to be rather
                intuitive and human-readable and comprehensible. However, when delving into complex
                use cases, a lack of formal defining structure may reveal that it is difficult to
                understand the precise meaning of the terminological representations and that use of
                a system such as LOINC® may differ widely amongst humans. Further exacerbating
                potential variability is the heterogeneous behavior of tools implemented to reason
                with terminological structures. [11] </para>
            <para>The field of Knowledge Representation and “Description Logics” was developed out
                of the attempt to formally define “intuitive representations” with a formal
                semantics to establish a common ground for human and tool interoperability.
                Knowledge representation involves the design of formalisms for expressing knowledge
                about a particular domain and focuses on representing and characterizing classes of
                objects and relationships between them. </para>
            <para>An ideal state terminology that relies on description logics may invoke more
                formal semantic relationships between and among concepts. Use of a Description
                Logics reasoner can help in overcoming important drawbacks of multi-axial systems
                and other non-standard, distinct formalisms: (1) the capability of detecting
                semantic equivalence of syntactically different expressions, and (2) the automated
                classification of concepts in a hierarchy. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED CT® Design Criteria</title>
            <para>Bodenreider et al. provide an overview of SNOMED Design Criteria:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">The representation of SNOMED has gone through phases of
                    increasing formal rigor. The initial SNOP and SNOMED versions were multi-axial
                    systems that enabled post-coordination. Whereas SNOP started as a 4-axis system,
                    SNOMED International had expanded to using 12 axes. SNOMED RT® abandoned the use
                    of self-standing axes that could be combined into composite codes in favor of a
                    description logic formalism called Ontylog, based on the Knowledge
                    Representation System Specification (KRSS) syntax and the K-REP system.
                    Following contemporary naming conventions for description logics, the set of
                    constructors used corresponds to the EL ++ language. SNOMED CT® has continued to
                    use this description logic as its underlying representation.</emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">A significant design criterion for SNOMED is to keep
                    concept expressions simple enough to be broadly usable by clinicians, while
                    maintaining faithful representation of concept meaning. Validity of concept
                    expressions is determined by adherence to the concept model underlying SNOMED
                    CT®. This concept model specifies which types of relationship are allowed for
                    which concepts, and what the allowed values are. For example, the concept model
                    specifies that “Method” is an allowed attribute relationship for “Procedure”
                    concepts, for which the value should be a type of “Action”. The January 2018
                    release uses 82 relationship types, almost twice the number of the initial 42
                    relationship types. Since July 2017, the concept model is available in
                    machine-readable form, and distributed as separate tables which are part of the
                    semi-annual releases. Other tables provide mappings to several versions of the
                    International Classification of Diseases (ICD-9-CM, ICD-10 and ICD-O). The
                    current release format, called Release Format 2 (RF2), supports versioning,
                    providing access to any previous release of SNOMED CT®.</emphasis> [1]</para>
            <para>While SNOMED CT® has committed to an application of formal methods and rigor to
                its knowledge representation, others have explicitly rejected the value of
                description logic and chose not to provide a defining taxonomy or fully define
                LOINC® parts.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Comparing LOINC®, SNOMED CT® and RxNorm to Cimino’s Desiderata</title>
        <para>Despite the guiding principles for terminology design and representation summarized
            above, “LOINC® does not fulfill the definition of a computable medical terminology as
            articulated by Cimino et al., that being one based in concept orientation, concept
            definition, and polyhierarchy. These characteristics enable the logical inference
            between concepts, parts, and part elements.” [12] LOINC® is a well-maintained
            terminology – there is a deprecation process and has concept permanence where codes
            aren’t reused – but they do not establish the basic parameters of hierarchy and
            polyhierarchy. And, they are violating the tenants of Cimino’s Desiderata.</para>
        <table>
                <title>Correspondence of LOINC® to Cimino’s Desiderata</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Tenant</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">LOINC®</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept Orientation</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>No</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept Permanence</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Yes</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Non-Semantic Concept
                                Identifier</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>Yes</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Polyhierarchy</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>No</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Formal Definitions</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>No</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Classification</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>No – they have a miscellaneous code</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Multiple Granularities</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>No</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Multiple Consistent
                                Views</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>No</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Representation of
                                Context</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>No, but they have Narrative Summary</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        <section>
            <title>Comparison of SNOMED CT® to Cimino’s Desiderata</title>
            <para>SNOMED CT® is the terminology of our current awareness most closely aligns with
                the Desiderata. As stated elsewhere, it uses Description Logics for computability
                and facilitates the use of reasoners to determine equivalence among various
                syntactic representations. The primary downsides are 1). Some proprietary concepts
                and 2). Lengthy concept submissions process for consideration into either the
                National or International editions. This lack of agility, efficiency and speed is
                apparent in crisis situations such as COVID-19 pandemic. Otherwise, it has proven to
                be robust and has a large global community to assist with its development and
                vetting.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Correspondence of SNOMED CT® to Cimino’s Desiderata</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Tenant</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">SNOMED CT®</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept Orientation</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept Permanence</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Non-Semantic Concept
                                        Identifier</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Polyhierarchy</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Formal Definitions</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Classification</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Multiple
                                    Granularities</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Multiple Consistent
                                    Views</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Representation of
                                    Context</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </section>
        <section>
            <title>Comparison of RxNorm to Cimino’s Desiderata</title>
            <para>While RxNorm meets most of the Desiderata’s requirements, there are a few that are
                not met. Of particular importance is the lack of Description Logics. Use of a
                Description Logics reasoner can help in overcoming important drawbacks of
                multi-axial systems: (1) the capability of detecting semantic equivalence of
                syntactically different expressions, and (2) the automated classification of
                concepts in a hierarchy. RxNorm has another issue of not being a global standard as
                its development and main use is in the U.S. where it is a nationally recognized
                standard, i.e. Meaningful Use. </para>
            <para>However, recent work by Bona et al. have been developing a Drug Ontology product
                (DrOn), based on RxNorm and Chemical Entities of Biological Interest Ontology, which
                is a modular and extensible ontology of drug products, their ingredients and
                biological activity to enable comparative effectiveness and allow researchers to
                query National Drug Codes (NDCs) in multiple ways. Bone et al. go on to say the
                following:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">We have implemented a full accounting of national drug
                    codes and RxNorm unique concept identifiers as information content entities, and
                    of the processes involved in managing their creation and changes. This includes
                    an OWL file that implements and defines the classes necessary to model these
                    entities. A separate file contains an instance-level prototype in OWL that
                    demonstrates the feasibility of this approach to representing NDCs and the
                    RxCUIs and the processes of managing them by retrieving and representing several
                    individual NDCs, both active and inactive, and the RxCUIs to which they are
                    connected. We also demonstrate how historic information about these identifiers
                    in DrOn can be easily retrieved using a simple SPARQL Protocol and RDF Query
                    Language (SPARQL).</emphasis>[13]</para>
            <para>This development may have a significant impact on improving knowledge management
                as well as the ability to utilize Description Logics reasoners with its attendant
                benefits.</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Correspondence of RxNorm to Cimino’s Desiderata</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Tenant</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">RxNorm</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept Orientation</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Concept Permanence</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>No – remapping, changing atoms, splitting, etc.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Non-Semantic Concept
                                        Identifier</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Polyhierarchy</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Formal Definitions</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>No – [Ingredients] [Strength] [Dose] enough?</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Classification</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Multiple
                                    Granularities</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Multiple Consistent
                                    Views</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Representation of
                                    Context</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Yes</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Current Opportunities for SNOMED CT®, LOINC® and RxNorm to Integrate, Enhance and
            Extend</title>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED CT® Existing Limitations</title>
            <section>
                <title>Licensing Conditions</title>
                <para>There are also licensing conditions to SNOMED CT® that historically prevented
                    its use as a common format for LOINC®. [14] This issue needs to be addressed for
                    building on SNOMED CT®'s foundation. Nonetheless, SNOMED CT®'s commitment to
                    develop and expand their use of description logics formalism as called out by
                    Tinkar efforts as well as their alignment with the Desiderata as described by
                    Cimino, et at, is a step in the right direction.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Submission Process Time</title>
                <para>While SNOMED CT® has a process for handling new concept requests and
                    submissions, it is lengthy and not amenable to rapidly changing conditions as
                    seen with COVID-19. While workarounds can be done, what is needed is a formal,
                    standardized, and agile process to accommodate quickly changing
                    conditions/situations. The ability to share and aggregate data nationally, if
                    not internationally, is paramount.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Compositional Complexity </title>
                <para>While SNOMED CT® uses explicit, elaborate axioms to clarify meaning, its
                    complex representation (compositional grammar) limits its broad adoption. [15]
                    The learning curve to appropriately learn, author, and represent concepts using
                    SNOMED CT®'s compositional grammar (for post-coordinated expressions) and
                    constraint language is steep, resulting in few who want to spend the resources
                    to learn. In addition, even for those who learn it, it takes substantial
                    experience to develop the expertise to understand and demonstrate concept
                    redundancy in a consistent and correct manner.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Inconsistent Representation</title>
                <para>There are multiple ways to represent SNOMED CT® concepts, leading to
                    inconsistent representation (i.e., lack of equivalence), ambiguity, and patient
                    harm from low data quality. SNOMED CT® is still up for constant refinement
                    especially for improving and standardizing concept representation, which makes
                    it difficult for the user to determine equivalence, both within and across
                    terminologies.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Interpretive Comments</title>
                <para>Interpretive comments are meant to enrich measurement results. One specific
                    example is a statement of measurement uncertainty, which is required by some
                    metrological guidelines. Measurement uncertainty is invaluable in the correct
                    interpretation of measurement results. [15] Because interpretive comments can be
                    of crucial importance in patient care, it is critical to expand SNOMED CT® to
                    thoroughly capture these concepts.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>LOINC® Existing Limitations</title>
            <section>
                <title>Inconsistent Selection of Codes for the Same Test</title>
                <para>Without concepts of polyhierarchy, concept orientation, and concept
                    definition, there is additional pressure on technicians and other stakeholders
                    to correctly specify the correct LOINC® code: “When the terminology model is
                    ultimately weak, it forces more onto the [statement] model”. [15] “A challenge
                    that remains to be solved is the binding of statement model and terminology.
                    There is often no clear demarcation between what is represented in the statement
                    model and what is represented in the terminology.” [9] </para>
                <para>Consequently, laboratory technicians may select a LOINC® code with an
                    incorrect part (i.e., the incorrect specimen or analyte) due to LOINC®’s
                    multiaxial hierarchy, resulting in difficulties for data aggregation and
                    understanding across both different technicians and institution. [12] It has
                    been reported that choosing different ‘properties’ (i.e., parts) was the most
                    frequent reason that different coding choices were made. [16] In a “study about
                    correctness of LOINC® mapping, choosing different ‘Method’, ‘Scale’ and
                    ‘Property’ attributes was the most common reason for different coding choices
                    among three large institutions. For example, in the ‘Method’ axis, some
                    institutions usually use a code that specifies the method (when available),
                    whereas other institutions always choose terms that are “methodless”. Another
                    example, is that in the ‘Scale/Property’ axes, LOINC® uses two distinct styles
                    (Prid:Nar VS. Prid:Nom) for reporting the interpretation of laboratory tests
                    (e.g. CFTR gene mutation analysis). The Narrative (Nar) scale is for free text
                    results (sentences, paragraphs, sections), whereas the Nominal (Nom) scale is
                    used for representing coded values, as when selecting an organism found on
                    culture from a coded list of bacteria. The differences between these types are
                    often subtle and require understanding the reporting system. Steindel et al.
                    also concluded that for some purposes, such as finding any code that could be
                    used to indicate the presence of a particular disease, rolling up LOINC® codes
                    and ignoring some LOINC® axes (e.g. method, scale, or property) can be
                    beneficial.” [16]</para>
                <para>There is not much management in terms of education in what codes are used for,
                    and medical technicians often do not have the LOINC® level of knowledge for
                    encoding that is necessarily expected. [17] The results in the following example
                    offer insight into how different codes may be selected for the same test from
                    different laboratories. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Case Study 1: Cardiac Marker and Coagulation Laboratory
                        Proficiency Tests [12]</emphasis></para>
                <para>Depending on the lab, technicians may choose different LOINC® codes for the
                    same test. The College of American Pathologists (CAP) surveyed 90 lab
                    participants on “practice setting, instrument(s) and test method(s), and LOINC®
                    code selection and usage in the laboratory and electronic health records” for 10
                    commonly ordered tests. 19.6% of codes reported were incorrect, with the highest
                    error rates “observed in the property (27 of 275, 9.8%), system (27 of 275,
                    9.8%), and component (22 of 275, 8.0%) LOINC® axes. Errors in LOINC® code
                    selection included selection of the incorrect component (e.g., activated
                    clotting time instead of activated partial thromboplastin time); selection of
                    panels that can never be used to obtain an individual analyte (e.g., prothrombin
                    time panel instead of international normalized ratio); and selection of an
                    incorrect specimen type.” </para>
                <figure xml:id="BreakdownofLOINCCodesProvidedbyEachLaboratory">
                    <title>Breakdown of LOINC® Codes Provided by Each Laboratory</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/Breakdown%20of%20LOINC%C2%AE%20Codes%20Provided%20by%20Each%20Laboratory%20.svg" align="center" scale ="30"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>For an Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) test, labs reported five
                    different LOINC® codes that could be selected. Results differed due to different
                    selections for the following axes:<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Component – One lab reported using the code 3184-9 for an aPTT
                                test, which used a component “activated clotting time” instead of
                                “coagulation surface induced”</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>System – Between the different labs, some codes selected had the
                                system as control blood (Bld^Control), platelet-poor plasma (PPP),
                                or whole blood (Bld).</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
                <para>For a Prothrombin Time (PT) test, labs reported three different LOINC® codes
                    that could be selected. Results differed due to some labs incorrectly selecting
                    panels or the wrong system. For a D-Dimer test, results differed to differences
                    in component, property, system, and method.</para>
                <para>As referenced in the table "Correspondence of SNOMED CT® to Ciminos
                    Desiderata", many of the errors occurred from different selections in system,
                    where the system could be whole blood or platelet form plasma. “For the
                    analyzers used by the laboratories in this survey, coagulation tests such as
                    APTT and International Normalized Ratio (INR) are performed on PPP and are never
                    performed on whole blood, so the selection of a code that indicates the system
                    as PPP would more accurately represent the test performed as opposed to a code
                    that lists the system as blood (Bld). Superficially, an end-user may think that
                    “Bld” is a nonspecific answer for a collected blood specimen. However, LOINC®
                    has defined the system part term Bld as whole blood as indicated in section 2.5
                    of the LOINC® User's Guide V2.65.”</para>
                <para>LOINC® is an international standard which means that there are terms that only
                    apply to foreign assays but are still available for use by laboratories in the
                    U.S. This results in concepts such as “Whole Blood” that mean something
                    different than intended. End-users commonly use this concept when they intend to
                    represent “platelet form plasma”; this results in highly prevalent errors in
                    CoAg testing because the LOINC® concept for “Whole Blood” is perceived to be a
                    general term when it is not. [15]</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Issues with Granularity and Specificity</title>
                <para>A study assessing LOINC® consistency at three different institutions found
                    “inconsistency across institutions regarding specificity of mappings as they
                    relate to methods. It appears that sometimes mappers link the method specific
                    codes to a more general LOINC® code, and at other times they link to a method
                    specific LOINC® code. This causes inconsistency in mappings across
                    institutions.” [17]</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Case Study 2: Comparison of LOINC® Codes between IVD
                        Manufacturers and Medical Center Laboratories [20]</emphasis></para>
                <para>In an assessment of LOINC® interoperability between diagnostic test
                    manufacturers and five medical center laboratories, there were mismatches
                    related to granularity identified such as discrepancies between choosing:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A methodless LOINC® code (e.g., 1920-8, Aspartate
                            aminotransferase(AST),) instead of specific code including the method
                            (e.g., 30239-8, Aspartate aminotransferase [Enzymatic activity/volume]
                            in Serum or Plasma by With P-5’-P)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A Quantitative LOINC® code (e.g., 70143-4, Cannobinoid screen) versus
                            qualitative LOINC® code (e.g., 8172-9, Cannabinoids) by the manufacturer
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Different units of measure: mass/volume (e.g., 3094-0, Urea nitrogen
                            [Mass/volume] in Serum or Plasma) versus moles/volume (e.g., 1493-7,
                            Urea nitrogen [Moles/volume] in Serum or Plasma) [18]</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Variation in Results for Different Devices</title>
                <para>In addition to variation between how labs classify certain tests, there can
                    also be variation in test results from manufacturers. </para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Case Study 3: D-Dimer Test Results from Different
                        In-Vitro Diagnostic (IVD) Devices [15]</emphasis></para>
                <para><xref linkend="DDimerTestResultsfromDifferentDevices"/> represents data results for D-Dimer tests that are all
                    represented by the same LOINC® code. However, upon closer notice, the means
                    between the different devices are significantly different. This raises concern
                    amongst comparing data across institutions that use different devices. </para>
                <figure xml:id="DDimerTestResultsfromDifferentDevices">
                    <title>D-Dimer Test Results from Different Devices</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/D-Dimer%20Test%20Results%20from%20Different%20Devices.svg" align="center" scale="50"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para>The aforementioned CAP study surveying laboratories found that for a D-Dimer
                    test, results differed to differences in component, property, system, and
                    method. [12] Therefore, there is not only variation in test results from
                    different devices and D-Dimer results, but there is also additional variation in
                    the ability to encode the same test from a single device. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Manual Mapping Between Institutions</title>
                <para>Due to the described inconsistencies between institutions, there is additional
                    manpower required to determine comparable LOINC® codes. At many institutions,
                    there are designated teams of doctors who must manually review submitted data to
                    their institution to ensure that codes can accurately be compared between
                    existing data in their system. [15] This process results in a cumbersome
                    workflow process that involves personnel who must compare LOINC® codes, assess
                    the validity of codes, and submit reviewal processes for codes that must be
                    corrected.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Case Study 4: Bone-Marrow Transplant Research Study
                        [15]</emphasis></para>
                <para>An academic medical center in Texas is conducting a bone-marrow transplant
                    research center study, in order to build an interface that will allow users to
                    automatically submit data to the hospital. However, upon review, there are
                    issues where the LOINC® codes do not match correctly.</para>
                <figure xml:id="LOINCCodesUsedatTwoDifferentInstitutionsfortheSameTests">
                    <title>LOINC® Codes Used at Two Different
                        Institutions for the Same Tests</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <?oxy_comment_start author="naylee" timestamp="20231129T174431-0600" comment="(R) is missing in the LOINC in the table (two places in the top heading row) "?>
                            <imagedata
                                fileref="../images/LOINC%20Codes%20Used%20at%20Two%20Different%20Institutions%20for%20the%20Same%20Tests.svg" scale="40"/><?oxy_comment_end?>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                <para><xref linkend="LOINCCodesUsedatTwoDifferentInstitutionsfortheSameTests"/> provides insight into the difficulties doctors and technicians face
                    in ensuring data mapped between systems are the same. Without high confidence in
                    data, these issues can lead to impacts on real-world evidence
                    capabilities.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>LOINC® Should Define Relations (Using Description Logic)</title>
                <para>LOINC® should define the relations between codes and combinations of codes
                    that allow users to infer equivalence if their meanings in data instance
                    representation are interoperable. That is, if the combination of two codes has
                    the same meaning as a single code (a difference in the use of pre- or
                    post-coordination), relationships should exist between the codes that support
                    the assertion of equivalence. Use of a Description Logics reasoner can help in
                    overcoming important drawbacks of multi-axial systems: (1) the capability of
                    detecting semantic equivalence of syntactically different expressions, and (2)
                    the automated classification of concepts in a hierarchy. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Current LOINC® Efforts to Improve Interoperability</title>
            <section>
                <title>LOINC®-to-IVD (LIVD) Manufacturer Specifications</title>
                <para>The LOINC® to IVD (LIVD) Mapping Specification is required by the United
                    States Department of Health and Human Services for SARS-CoV-2 reporting and
                    harmonizes how IVD test information is represented using LOINC®. The LIVD file
                    format is currently led by IVD Industry Connectivity Consortium (IICC), and the
                    JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) representation is a project at HL7. </para>
                <para>To quantify the magnitude of problems that the lab data ecosystem faces,
                    Cholan et al. describes a pilot evaluation with five healthcare systems that
                    found LOINC® data maintained only 59% integrity as it moved from laboratory
                    analyzer to laboratory information system. [20] Efforts to promote
                    interoperability using LOINC® and related standards will require a more
                    comprehensive effort and continuing evaluation and quality control.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Current LOINC® Improvements and Extensions of the Existing Hierarchy</title>
            <section>
                <title>Quality Assurance in LOINC® Using Description Logic</title>
                <para>Although LOINC® has not officially adopted Description Logic and formal
                    knowledge representation languages, the U.S. National Library of Medicine
                    applied Description Logic to the quality assurance of LOINC® (based on the 2013
                    collaborative agreement) and used it as a basis for auditing LOINC®. [19] This
                    study helps demonstrate the usefulness of Description Logic for terminologies by
                    producing the following findings: </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>427 sets of logically equivalent LOINC® codes</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>676 sets of logically equivalent LOINC® parts</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>239 consistencies in LOINC® multi axial hierarchy</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Automated classification of LOINC® and SNOMED CT® increased
                            connectivity by an additional 9000 LOINC® codes</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Overall, these results suggest decent quality maintenance for LOINC® as these
                    counts are relatively small considering the 450k+ concepts in LOINC® as part of
                    this study. However, the key takeaway from this body of work is that LOINC®
                    could benefit from the application of Description Logic by allowing for
                    automated classification and equivalence detection. [19]</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>LOINC® Document Ontology</title>
                <para>The LOINC® Document Ontology is a special set of LOINC® codes that are built
                    on a framework for naming and classifying the key attributes of clinical
                    documents. The codes intend to provide consistent semantics for documents
                    exchanged between systems for many uses. The LOINC® Document Ontology represents
                    the five key attributes of clinical documents that intend to be understood
                    across systems.<?oxy_comment_start author="naylee" timestamp="20231129T180500-0600" comment="Bullets here need no punctuation because it&apos;s just a list of items. No period needed. 1st rule on page 11 on the Oxford Style Guide"?><itemizedlist><?oxy_comment_end?>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><emphasis role="bold">Subject Matter Domain</emphasis> e.g.,
                                Cardiology, Pediatric Cardiology, Physical Therapy</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Role </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">e.g.,
                                Physician, Nurse, Case Manager, Therapist, Patient</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Setting </emphasis><emphasis role="italic">e.g.,
                                Hospital, Outpatient, Emergency Department</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Type of Service </emphasis><emphasis
                                role="italic">e.g., Consultation, History and Physical, Discharge
                                Summary</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis role="bold">Kind of Document </emphasis><emphasis
                                role="italic">e.g., Note, Letter, Consent</emphasis></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>A semi structured interview conducted by consultants to government agencies
                    and pathology experts produced a finding that the “LOINC® document ontology
                    appears to be irrelevant to move things – not many people use it. It was a first
                    attempt to apply some relationships between LOINC®'s concepts that formally
                    don’t exist now, but it’s in a domain with low impact. [20]</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>LOINC® Hierarchy Browser</title>
                <para>LOINC’s® website currently hosts ‘The Hierarchy Browser’ tool which allows
                    users to view various hierarchies located in LOINC®. Much of this functionality
                    was previously only available in the RELMA® application. [22] While a good
                    starting point towards formal knowledge representation, the current hierarchies
                    are limited, and still do not provide full definitions for LOINC® parts.
                    Furthermore, the use of the hierarchies and LOINC® parts are very restricted
                    under the LOINC® Copyright Notice and License. [22]</para>
                <figure xml:id="RepresentationofASTinTheLOINCHierarchyBrowserTool">
                    <title>Representation of AST in The LOINC® Hierarchy Browser Tool</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="../images/Representation%20of%20AST%20in%20The%20LOINC%20Hierarchy%20Browser%20Tool.svg" align="center" scale="30"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                </section>
            <section>
                <title>Nebraska Lexicon</title>
                <para>The following excerpt provides background on the Nebraska Lexicon, a project
                    focused on the harmonization between LOINC® and SNOMED CT®:</para>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">Since February 2004, University of Nebraska Medical
                        Center (Nebraska Medicine) has maintained an extension namespace (extension
                        identifier 1000004 registered with International Health Terminology
                        Standards Development Organization (IHTSDO)) to support clinical terminology
                        development required for electronic health record (EHR) deployment at its
                        hospital and clinics. Content developed for this namespace has been driven
                        pragmatically by recording requirements reported by Nebraska clinicians in
                        the course of their daily work. This content has been deployed in records
                        over three generations of EHRs including the Public Health Automated Medical
                        Information System (PHAMIS), IDX-GE and now is in use in
                    Epic®…</emphasis></para>
                <para><emphasis role="italic">…</emphasis><emphasis role="italic">In 2014, the
                        Observables project of the IHTSDO and Regenstrief Institute published a
                        draft convergent concept model for harmonization of content between LOINC®
                        and SNOMED CT®. In January 2017, the project published a set of SNOMED CT®
                        formatted expressions that define the meaning of ~13000 laboratory LOINC®
                        observables employing the harmonized concept model. An expanded technology
                        preview of ~20,000 concepts has been released by the IHTSDO but is not
                        included in this publication. UNMC has converted the earlier expression set
                        into SNOMED CT® formatted extension concepts employing LOINC® long names as
                        the SNOMED CT® fully specified name and assigning class supertypes within
                        the Observable entity hierarchy in SNOMED CT®. ‘Grouper’ concepts have been
                        modeled and deployed within the Observable entity hierarchy in order to
                        enhance clinical navigation and to support common query use cases in
                        laboratory medicine and pathology. Anatomic and molecular pathology
                        observables defined by semantic analysis of the CAP Annotated Cancer
                        Protocols explained in 3.3 are included. Some pre-existing SNOMED CT®
                        Observable entity content has been fully defined using the harmonized
                        concept model with permission of the IHTSDO. Grouper concepts have been
                        included to organize the ontology and support common query use cases
                        proposed by CAP. All content was run through the description logic
                        classifier and both ‘stated’ and ‘inferred’ relationships are included in
                        this release. This “Observables ontology” for laboratory medicine and
                        pathology is being published for evaluation and comment by the informatics
                        community.</emphasis> [23]</para>
                <para>The Nebraska Lexicon is a pragmatic example of harmonizing terminologies into
                    a single concept model and melding LOINC® and SNOMED CT® together. The content
                    is published with permission of the CAP. A common terminology data model that
                    expands beyond just LOINC® and SNOMED®, but that could also represent additional
                    terminologies such as RxNorm, CVX, etc. (i.e., HL7’s Terminology Knowledge
                    Architecture) would allow users to integrate content and changes more seamlessly
                    and reduce duplicative work</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Quality Control</title>
                <para>Current quality control of LOINC® is limited or not known. While the
                    aforementioned Quality Assurance study proved that use of Description Logic is
                    promising and beneficial for terminologies such as LOINC®, these types of
                    quality assurance methods are not widely used. </para>
                <para>The only published quality metrics from Regenstrief about LOINC® include
                    published stats about their submission queue describing how long it takes to
                    create a LOINC® term (e.g., 182 days to turn around a revision). [24]</para>
                <para>Regenstrief relies on an occasional survey (either once per year or once every
                    few years) from ONC to the laboratory community to assess how labs are using
                    LOINC®, what are the barriers, etc.; however, the survey is very LOINC®-centric
                    and not so much about the quality of the terminology standard itself. </para>
                <para>LOINC® is user-driven, so all submissions are coming from the community. This
                    is beneficial in that there is transparency and openness to the curation of
                    content. However, the current curation is inadequate, and there is no systemic
                    approach to ensure no overlap between terms. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Educational Workshops</title>
                <para>There are paid workshops users can attend in association with LOINC® meetings.
                    These workshops tell users how to go about using LOINC® codes and how to use
                    RELMA®. In a semi-structured interview with participants from the public and
                    private sectors, it was stated that “the helpfulness and usefulness of these
                    educational workshops may be in question by some stakeholders in the
                    community.”</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Future Policy and Direction for LOINC®</title>
            <section>
                <title>Improved Education</title>
                <para>Improving education through established certification programs, improved
                    structure in the community, and more training are potential next steps.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Robust Quality Control</title>
                <para>LOINC® may need more pruning of extraneous terms and duplicate terms. There is
                    also potential room for refining the different levels of granularity of
                    terms.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>RxNorm Existing Limitations</title>
            <section>
                <title>Lack of Description Logics</title>
                <para>RxNorm lack of Description Logics formalism use, as proposed by SOLOR, limits
                    its ability to use logic reasoners for inferencing. This limits RxNorms ability
                    to find new patterns, relationships and identification of equivalence.
                    [1]</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Concerns Over Concept Permanence</title>
                <para>While RxNorm CUIs are never reused as per best practice, the possibility
                    exists that RxNorm atoms can change with the potential to change the definition.
                    Furthermore, RxNorm CUIs that are no longer in
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="naylee" timestamp="20231130T093437-0600" comment="A name of archive, not an abbreviation. Leave as it is. "?>RXNCONSO<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    are moved to a cumulative archive called RXNATOMARCHIVE.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Formal Concept Definition</title>
                <para>While RxNorm has ‘defined ingredients’, historically it has lacked the
                    computational ability to define concepts by relationships, thereby allowing
                    inferencing. [26] However, recent efforts by Bona et al. have successfully
                    created an OWL file to implement and define the classes necessary to model
                    RxNorm and NDC concepts. [13]</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Future Harmonization of Standards</title>
            <para>In the U.S., SNOMED CT® and RxNorm are harmonized but LOINC® has not joined the
                harmonization. There have been some partnerships and independently funded programs
                to help make LOINC® more compatible and useful within the ecosystem of controlled
                medical terminologies that converge on a model of meaning that can be shared.
                Further integration has been proposed but will require additional resources to bring
                these terminologies closer together. However, the collaboration between SNOMED CT®
                and LOINC® has been renewed. Create a LOINC® extension of SNOMED CT® to leverage the
                strengths of both has been the popular notion. This notion has been particularly
                attractive for the SNOMED CT®'s polyhierarchal structure and inferencing
                capabilities. This concept leads to embrace a greater compatibility and
                interoperability, integration of SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, and RxNorm, while noting
                different formalisms and tools for their representation in these technologies. [26]
                Various terminologies have different semantics, models, release cycles, and
                versioning mechanisms. [1] While there is recognition that terminologies are not
                standardized at the exchange level, there is no consensus about harmonized next
                steps to solve the challenges.</para>
            <para><?oxy_comment_start author="naylee" timestamp="20231130T111550-0600" comment="Removed &quot;Efforts such as SHIELD (Systemic Harmonization and Interoperability Enhancement for Laboratory Data) sponsored in part by the U.S. FDA sets strategies to transform the current U.S. laboratory ecosystem into an interoperable system, including the goals of harmonizing industry coding standards such as LOINC® to create a reference knowledge base where any user of laboratory data can obtain more information about the performed test in question.&quot; "?>Today<?oxy_comment_end?>,
                we recognize many popular movements in both private and public sectors to set
                strategies to transform many aspects of laboratory ecosystem into an interoperable
                system. We strive to achieve the goal of unifying industry coding standards, such as
                LOINC®, to create a reference knowledge base where any user of laboratory data can
                obtain more information about the performed test in question. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Terminology Knowledge Example</title>
        <para>In this section, we will be discussing a use case using questionnaires and
            responses.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Terminology Knowledge Problem Statement</title>
            <para>As a real-world use case, we focused on improving the diagnosis of emerging acute
                chronic infectious diseases, initially focusing on Long COVID as an example. There
                are numerous areas within clinical workflows for COVID-19 exposure and Long COVID
                diagnosis that are open to improvements that will ultimately help provide safe and
                effective patient care. There is a need to determine clear prioritization principles
                around focus areas for data capture within these COVID-19 workflows. To date, Long
                COVID has been primarily a diagnosis of exclusion, meaning that it is often only
                diagnosed after all other conditions are eliminated as a possible cause of symptoms.
                Clinicians need to make quick decisions based on objective and subjective
                observations to determine if a patient has signs and symptoms compatible with Long
                COVID and whether the patient should be admitted to the hospital. Clinicians are
                encouraged to leverage technology, virtual visits, and other Health Information
                Technology (IT)-generated clinical data to assist with decision making and
                information sharing. Unfortunately, electronic clinical data is plagued by data
                quality challenges, including variation in how data elements are encoded by
                terminology standards, and stored in clinical information models. These challenges
                can cause inefficiencies in how clinical data elements are identified, retrieved,
                analyzed, and operationalized into workflows at the point-of-care. </para>
            <para>In the current workflows for COVID-19 and Long COVID, clinicians are encouraged to
                rely on electronic clinical data to determine which patients should be prioritized
                for being tested, hospitalized, and/or isolated. Failure to include or exclude
                patients’ screening, testing, and treatment could lead to life-threatening
                situations for patients and could impact the overall trajectory of the outbreak at a
                population-level. Overall, the ability to measure and improve healthcare outcomes
                relies on consistent, high-quality electronic data that is aggregated from a variety
                of Health IT systems across numerous medical centers and healthcare facilities.
                Clinicians need to be able to easily access and fully trust the electronic data they
                are using to make determinations at the point-of-care, key components of High
                Reliability Organizations and Learning Health Systems. </para>
            <para>Using ANF as a standardized statement model to streamline analysis could
                potentially lead to improved and earlier Long COVID diagnoses. This body of work
                aims to focus on workflow areas of data as it is captured for Long COVID – perhaps
                iPad data entry, EHR collection of signs and symptoms, emergency warning signs,
                patient-reported data, etc. – to understand how the collection of data elements in a
                consistent and high-quality manner, and the subsequent data analysis, fit into the
                overall goal of achieving coordinated, national and highly-reliable care.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Terminology Knowledge Demonstration Objectives</title>
            <para>The objective of this work is to document data collection methods and statement
                model standards to demonstrate the importance of an interoperable data system and
                downstream analytical scenarios through a use case for Long COVID as an example of
                an emerging acute chronic infectious disease. We aim to highlight how Analysis
                Normal Form (ANF) can be used to standardize the representation of equivalent
                concepts associated with data capture, storage and aggregation within the Long COVID
                workflow. This work utilized four main aims to demonstrate how ANF-thinking could
                improve use case outcomes and reduce the clinical burden on data consumers during
                data collection and aggregation:</para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 1: Review Workflow Schematic for Emerging Acute
                    Chronic Infectious Diseases, specifically focused on Data Capture Elements and
                    Long COVID Value Sets</emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 2: Draft Potential Questionnaires to Standardize Use
                    Case Data Acquisition </emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 3: Outline Variability in Statement
                    Representations</emphasis></para>
            <para><emphasis role="italic">Aim 4: Demonstrate ANF Ability to Standardize Terminology
                    and Capture Critical Data</emphasis></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Terminology Knowledge Methods</title>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 1: Review Workflow Schematic for Emerging Acute Chronic Infectious
                    Diseases, specifically focused on Data Capture Elements and Long COVID Value
                    Sets</emphasis>. In support of Task 3.2.1, our team documented a generalized
                workflow and use case schematic for a patient’s journey from COVID-19 exposure to
                Long COVID diagnosis. We focused on decision points related to data capture of signs
                and symptoms related to COVID-19 and outlined key terminology and clinical
                information modeling considerations within the workflow artifacts that were
                developed. </para>
            <para>The team then gathered and reviewed value sets from the National Institute of
                Health’s (NIH) NLM Value Set Authority Center (VSAC) to identify common concepts and
                data elements that would need to be captured to support a Long COVID diagnosis. Each
                team member was assigned a value set and identified common and well documented
                concepts from their respective set, including signs and symptoms, laboratory tests,
                laboratory test results, potential and confirmed exposure, and suspected and
                confirmed infection. The concepts were organized by value set and documented in a
                table.</para>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 2: Draft Potential Questionnaires to Standardize Use Case Data
                    Acquisition</emphasis>. Long COVID is a poorly understood condition where
                patients experience COVID-19 symptoms long past the expected symptomatic period and
                whose symptoms, test results, and timelines can vary drastically between patients.
                The team developed sample questionnaires based on the VSAC value sets to collect
                additional data that patients or providers could enter into a Clinical Input Form or
                questionnaire. Traditional, current-state questionnaires were developed for the Long
                COVID use case to demonstrate how users may struggle to identify the optimal
                selections to document certain symptoms and may result in inconsistent and/or
                duplicative clinical data. The team then worked to develop an improved questionnaire
                that removes redundant and vague concepts and forces more granular and detailed
                selections to highlight ways to enhance the quality, accuracy, and interoperability
                of collected data.</para>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 3: Outline Variability in Statement Representations</emphasis>.
                Current terminology standards vary in the way they represent and code many data
                points that can be acquired through patient questionnaires. Critical information
                regarding severity, site, associated concepts, and data elements can be spread
                across the respective fields, incorporated directly into the concept code, or a
                combination of the two. The table aims to highlight the need for a normalized way to
                represent concepts to prevent loss of critical data and meaning as it is transformed
                and transmitted within and between systems. Improving the data collection, encoding,
                and storage of both present and absent concepts is essential in the effort to
                achieve lossless and interoperable data.</para>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 4: Demonstrate ANF Ability to Standardize Terminology and Capture
                    Critical Data</emphasis>. This paper ultimately aims to improve the acquisition,
                storage, and use of data across a variety of clinical situations, with the Long
                COVID use case as an example. We propose ANF as the tool to standardize and
                normalize the way critical data concepts from patient questionnaires are represented
                before transmitting to other systems for secondary use. The same concepts that were
                shown to have varying representations across terminology standards were modeled
                using a tabular ANF representation to demonstrate how ANF captures the same or more
                detail as other standards and normalizes the formatting of equivalent concepts
                across terminologies. The ANF table captures key data elements for the concept of
                loss of sense of smell since onset of COVID-19 symptoms. The concept ID, author, and
                topic are clearly documented along with timing of onset and recording. Not only is
                the concept itself represented in a normalized way that captures all pertinent
                values and details, but other normalized concepts, like linking to the beginning of
                symptom onset can be linked as associated clinical statements that add additional
                value and context.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Terminology Knowledge Example Results</title>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 1: Review Workflow Schematic for Emerging Acute Chronic Infectious
                    Diseases, specifically focused on Data Capture Elements and Long COVID Value
                    Sets. </emphasis>The team downloaded and reviewed the COVID-19 VSAC value sets
                outlined in the table below. The team used these value sets to extract an initial
                list of generalized clinical concepts associated with a COVID-19 diagnosis that
                could potentially contribute to a Long COVID diagnosis. [27]</para>
                <table>
                    <title>VSAC Value Sets</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Value Set Name</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>Steward</entry>
                                <entry>Value Set OID</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Potential Signs and
                                        Symptoms</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>CareEvolution</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1223.22</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Nonspecific Respiratory Viral
                                        Infection</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>CareEvolution</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1223.25</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">C19HCC SARSCoV2
                                    Exposure</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>MITRE</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1032.120</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Potential
                                    Exposure</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>CareEvolution</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1223.18</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Suspected
                                    Infection</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>CareEvolution</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1223.6</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">LIVD SARS CoV2 Test
                                    Codes</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>ONC</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1114.9</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold">LIVD SARS CoV2 Test Result
                                        Codes</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>ONC</entry>
                                <entry>2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1114.10</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 2: Draft Potential Questionnaires to Standardize Use Case Data
                    Acquisition</emphasis>. An initial questionnaire was developed for the
                generalized concepts extracted from the COVID-19 VSAC value sets that poses a simple
                yes or no question for each of the concepts that could potentially aid in a Long
                COVID diagnosis. This chapter focuses on potential questionnaires for ‘Signs and
                Symptoms’ and ‘Non-Specific Respiratory Diagnoses’, outlined in <xref
                    linkend="HypotheticalSignsandSymptomsQuestionnaires"/> and <xref
                    linkend="HypotheticalNonSpecificRespiratoryDiagnosesQuestionnaire"/>
                respectively. [2]</para>
            <figure xml:id="HypotheticalSignsandSymptomsQuestionnaires">
                <title>Hypothetical Signs and Symptoms Questionnaires</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Hypothetical%20Signs%20and%20Symptoms%20Questionnaires.svg" align="center" scale="50"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>While the initial version of the questionnaire on the left can collect important
                information and data, the format was improved in the version on the right to reduce
                redundancy, improve clarity, and collect more accurate and granular detail. The
                improved questionnaire forces patients or physicians completing the survey to select
                more granular symptoms and reduces ambiguity. Rather than allowing for individuals
                to select ‘cough’ and ‘dry cough’ or ‘productive cough’, the improved questionnaire
                forces a more accurate selection of either ‘dry cough’ or ‘productive cough’ to
                reduce redundant data. Additionally, the improved questionnaire utilizes
                user-friendly definitions like rapid breathing rather than highly technical
                terminology like ‘tachypnea’ to reduce duplicative symptoms and support accurate
                data collection from a wider audience. The value sets and questionnaires will need
                to be updated as symptoms are more comprehensively understood, and as new symptoms
                are identified. </para>
            <para>The team developed additional questionnaires for non-specific respiratory
                diagnoses below in <xref linkend="HypotheticalNonSpecificRespiratoryDiagnosesQuestionnaire"/>. The diagnoses questionnaires continue to improve data
                quality by reducing duplicative selections and improving granularity by forcing an
                Upper or Lower ‘Viral Respiratory Tract Infection’ rather than allowing the
                selection of both Upper or Lower Viral Respiratory Tract Infection and “Viral
                Respiratory Tract Infection’. These additional questionnaires demonstrate how
                improvements can be made to data collection across a variety of areas associated
                with patient care and can be applied to other emerging acute and chronic infectious
                diseases.</para>
            <figure xml:id="HypotheticalNonSpecificRespiratoryDiagnosesQuestionnaire">
                <title>Hypothetical Non-Specific Respiratory Diagnoses
                    Questionnaire</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/Hypothetical%20Non-Specific%20Respiratory%20Diagnoses%20Questionnaire.svg" align="center" scale="50"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 3: Outline Variability in Statement Representations</emphasis>.
                Building upon the concepts found in the VSAC value sets, the team developed tabular
                representations of certain symptoms to display the variability in the way concepts
                could be represented and coded. <xref linkend="HypotheticalNonSpecificRespiratoryDiagnosesQuestionnaire"/> depicts the symptom of ‘Fever Greater Than
                100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills’ across three example terminology standards as well as
                the null value of a normal body temperature. After reviewing the table, one could
                conclude that the first three examples are semantically the same. Each describe a
                condition of fever greater than 100.4 Fahrenheit, but critical information is spread
                out across the severity, site, and code fields depending on how the respective
                terminology standard represents the condition. This variability leads to sub-optimal
                data capture that can hinder data querying, data use, and the ability to identify
                semantically equivalent concepts.</para>
                <table>
                    <title>Variability in Representation of Fever</title>
                    <tgroup cols="5">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                        <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
                        <colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry> </entry>
                                <entry><link
                                    xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present.html#root"
                                        ><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Symptoms Present
                                        Example</emphasis></link><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                                        role="underline"> 1</emphasis></emphasis></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                    xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present.html#root"
                                        ><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Symptoms Present Example
                                        2</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                    xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present.html#root"
                                        ><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Symptoms Present Example
                                        3</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                    xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present.html#root"
                                        ><emphasis role="bold">COVID19 Symptoms
                                    Absent</emphasis></link></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <para><link
                                            xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition"
                                                ><emphasis role="bold"
                                        >Condition</emphasis></link></para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Fever Greater Than 100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills
                                    Present</entry>
                                <entry>Fever Greater Than 100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills
                                    Present</entry>
                                <entry>Fever Greater Than 100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills
                                    Present</entry>
                                <entry>Body Temperature Within Normal Range</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry><link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <link
                                        xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.id"
                                            ><emphasis role="bold">…...</emphasis></link></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline"
                                            >Severity</emphasis></emphasis></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <para>Null </para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Greater than 100.4 Fahrenheit</entry>
                                <entry>Greater than 100.4 Fahrenheit</entry>
                                <entry>Between 97.6 and 99.6 Fahrenheit</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <para><link
                                            xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.code"
                                                ><emphasis role="bold">Code</emphasis></link></para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Fever Greater Than 100.4 Fahrenheit with Chills
                                    (finding)</entry>
                                <entry>Fever with Chills (finding)</entry>
                                <entry>Fever with Chills (finding)</entry>
                                <entry>Regular Body Temperature (finding)</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <para><link
                                            xlink:href="https://covid-19-ig.logicahealth.org/StructureDefinition-covid19-symptoms-present-definitions.html#Condition.bodySite"
                                                ><emphasis role="bold">Site</emphasis></link></para>
                                    <para> </para>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>Null </entry>
                                <entry>Null </entry>
                                <entry>Mouth/Tongue</entry>
                                <entry>Null </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            <para><emphasis>Aim 4: Demonstrate ANF Ability to Standardize Terminology and Capture
                    Critical Data</emphasis>. The team demonstrated the value of ANF by developing a
                tabular ANF representation for loss of sense of smell since onset of COVID-19
                symptoms. ANF provides a singular, normalized way to represent concepts from
                different terminology standards by restricting various data elements to certain
                fields, like the severity of a particular symptom in the results section.
                Standardizing how data elements are reported facilitates the identification of
                equivalent terminology and improves the quality and interoperability of data. In the
                example below, ANF captures all the pertinent information including the symptom
                itself, option for the severity or numerical value of an observation, and the method
                of the observation, as well as additional information like the timeframe when a
                symptom first occurred. This additional information is an associated term that adds
                value and context to a measurement. </para>
            <para>While documenting symptoms that are marked as present on the improved
                questionnaire in a normalized format is essential, it is also important to represent
                signs and symptoms that are absent in a patient. Corresponding present and absent
                concepts for a certain symptom do not always exist across terminology standards, but
                ANF is able to represent the absence of a symptom using a numerical countable
                quantity, ensuring relevant and pertinent information is not lost.</para>
                 <table>
                    <title>ANF Standardized Representation of Anosmia and Associated Term Narrative 1</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Narrative 1: <emphasis
                                        role="bold">Loss of Sense of Smell</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                                    <para>id: <emphasis role="bold"
                                            >XXXXXXXX-XXXX-XXXX-XXXX-XXXXXXXXXXXX</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>time: <emphasis role="bold">1:17pm 2023-02-14
                                            T09:20:00.00+01:00</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>subjectOfRecordId: <emphasis role="bold"
                                            >Participant</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>author: <emphasis role="bold">Healthcare
                                            Professional</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>subjectOfInformation: <emphasis role="bold">Subject of
                                            Record</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>type: <emphasis role="bold">Performance</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>topic: <emphasis role="bold">Loss of Sense of
                                            Smell</emphasis></para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry morerows="7">Circumstance</entry>
                                <entry>PerformanceCircumstance</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>status: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[Complete]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>result: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[1,1]</emphasis></para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>resolution: 
                                                      <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>semantic: 
                                                      <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>healthRisk: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>participant: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[Participant]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>referenceRange 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>timing: 
                                            <emphasis role="bold">12:40pm 2023-02-14
                                                T09:20:00.00+01:00</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>purpose: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Associations:</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                                    <para>associatedStatement: </para>
                                    <para>[UUID] (Table: Associated Clinical Statement 1)</para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <title>ANF Standardized Representation of Anosmia and Associated Term Narrative 2</title>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Narrative 2: <emphasis
                                        role="bold">Since Onset of COVID-19
                                    Symptoms</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                                    <para>id: <emphasis role="bold">[UUID] Associated Clinical
                                            Statement 1</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>time: <emphasis role="bold">1:17pm 20123-02-14
                                            T09:20:00.00+01:00</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>subjectOfRecordId: <emphasis role="bold"
                                            >Participant</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>author: <emphasis role="bold">Healthcare
                                            professional</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>subjectOfInformation: <emphasis role="bold">Subject of
                                            record</emphasis></para>
                                    <para>type: <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic"
                                                >Observation Procedure</emphasis></emphasis></para>
                                    <para>topic: <emphasis role="bold">Since onset of COVID
                                            symptoms</emphasis></para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry morerows="7">Circumstance</entry>
                                <entry>PerformanceCircumstance</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>status: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[Complete]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>result:
                                                <emphasis role="bold"> [1,1]</emphasis></para>
                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>resolution: 
                                                      <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                                <listitem>
                                                  <para>semantic: 
                                                      <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                                </listitem>
                                            </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>healthRisk: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>participant: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[Participant]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>referenceRange: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>timing: 
                                            <emphasis role="bold">1:17pm 20123-02-14
                                                T09:20:00.00+01:00</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>purpose: 
                                                <emphasis role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">Associations:</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">associatedStatement: <emphasis
                                        role="bold">[N/A]</emphasis></entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Recommendations to Address Terminology Issues</title>
            <para>This section aims to highlight some of the current shortcomings with the way data
                is collected and represented. We propose the following recommendations for data
                collection via patient questionnaires to reduce duplicative and vague data
                collection, facilitate secondary data usage, and improve data
                interoperability:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Restrict data entry and collection with pre-populated patient
                        questionnaires based on established concepts from the appropriate value sets
                        to standardize data collection. This will work when questionnaire designers
                        and data consumers know the data that they are trying to capture. In the
                        context of a condition where the signs and symptoms are less well defined,
                        or have not yet been defined, this methodology may inhibit knowledge
                        discovery and should be supported by integrated knowledge management
                        constructs that facilitate data agility and regular updates to value sets.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Use detailed concepts to force granular selections that reduce ambiguity
                        or the need for duplicative data in pre-populated patient
                        questionnaires.</para>
                    <para>Questionnaires should not allow the selection of just ‘<emphasis
                            role="italic">Cough’</emphasis> and should prompt patients or providers
                        to select if it is a ‘<emphasis role="italic">Productive Cough</emphasis>’
                        or ‘<emphasis role="italic">Dry Cough</emphasis>’. </para>
                    <para>Questionnaires should not allow the selection of ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                            >Viral Respiratory Infection</emphasis>’ and should prompt patients or
                        providers to select a body site or location like ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                            >Upper Viral Respiratory Infection</emphasis>’ or ‘<emphasis
                            role="italic">Lower Viral Respiratory Infection</emphasis>’.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Group concepts by critical information like ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                            >Confirmed</emphasis>’ and ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                        >Potential</emphasis>’ exposure to prevent accidental selection of
                        inaccurate responses. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Add patient friendly terminology, like ‘<emphasis role="italic">Rapid
                            Breathing</emphasis>’, to value sets and questionnaires to facilitate
                        the collection of critical patient health data from a wider audience rather
                        than highly technical terms such as ‘<emphasis role="italic"
                            >Tachypnea</emphasis>’.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>These recommendations can and should be applied across all data collection
                questionnaires, not just the ‘Signs and Symptoms’ and ‘Non-Specific Respiratory
                Diagnosis’ questionnaires represented in this chapter. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Technologies that Support ANF </title>
            <para>While standardizing data collection methods is a critical step towards data
                interoperability and ANF data transformations, there are still common sources of
                errors associated with normalizing clinical data. Errors normalizing terminology
                content, terminology semantics, and poorly defined interactions between the input
                and presentation of clinical data are three key problems that still need to be
                addressed. Several transformation languages and architectures exist for expressing
                and executing transformation logic to address the issues above and to normalize
                specific instances of clinical data into ANF. Users can choose a language that is
                best tailored for the format of the data source, while transformation quality and
                accuracy is left to the transformation author. Below is a list of four
                transformation languages and the associated benefits and limitations. While each
                option has its own limitations and cost, the ability to address or minimize common
                normalization errors justifies their use.
                [27]<?oxy_comment_start author="naylee" timestamp="20231130T110056-0600" comment="The table below needs to define QVT = Query/View/Transformation in the first colum of the table. "?></para><?oxy_comment_end?>
            <table>
                <title>Benefits and Limitations of Transformation
                    Languages and Architecture</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="left" rowsep="1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="left" rowsep="1"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="left" rowsep="1"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard or Language</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Benefits</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Limitations</emphasis></entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>eXtensible Stylesheet Language Transformation (XSLT)</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Robust language </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Easily extensible via extension functions and
                                            calls</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Auto matches templates to data</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Easy tooling</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Good documentation</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Transformation specifications are difficult to read
                                            and understand</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Transformations are syntactic </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>XML input only, other formats not translated </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>FHIR Mapping Language (FML)</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Supports input formats other XML</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Semantic DAGs can be rendered in variety of
                                            syntaxes</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Concise and easy to read mapping specifications</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Input and output outside of FHIR logical models
                                            require extra custom programming</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Only XML and JSON supported as output syntaxes,
                                            otherwise custom programming is required</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>To date, only one implementation </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Limited tools needed for editing and authoring
                                            scripts</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Limited documentation sources</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Limited pool of knowledgeable programmers</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>QVT</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Great flexibility and configurability to create custom
                                            transformation languages</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Limited learning resources making it difficult to
                                            learn and understand</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Model Driven Message Interoperability (MDMI)</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Any-to-any transformations support reuse of
                                            transformation models for different use cases</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Minimal changes to other models if model
                                            changes</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Simplifies development, tooling supports development
                                            by SMEs and not dependent on developers</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Enables automation tooling for models</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Available open-source models for HL7 formats</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Limited experience working with transformations of
                                            detailed clinical models.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Lacking user documentation</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Complex runtime tool</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para> </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Bodenreider O, Cornet R, Vreeman DJ. Recent Developments in Clinical
                        Terminologies - SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm. Yearb Med Inform. 2018
                        Aug;27(1):129-139. doi: 10.1055/s-0038-1667077. Epub 2018 Aug 29. PMID:
                        30157516; PMCID: PMC6115234.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>McDonald C, Huff SM, Suico J, Mercer K. Logical Observation Identifiers
                        Names and Codes (LOINC) users’ guide. <emphasis role="italic">Indianapolis:
                            Regenstrief Institute. </emphasis>2004</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SNOMED Owl Toolkit [Internet]. IHTSDO. June 3 2022. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://github.com/IHTSDO/snomed-owl-toolkit"
                            >IHTSDO/snomed-owl-toolkit: The official SNOMED CT OWL Toolkit. OWL
                            conversion, classification and authoring support.
                        (github.com)</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>OWL refsets preview [Internet]. IHTSDO. Sept 28 2022. Available from:
                            <link
                            xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/mag/owl-refsets-preview"
                            >https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/mag/owl-refsets-preview</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>MED-RT Documentation [Internet]. NIH., May 2021 Version. Available from:
                            <link
                            xlink:href="https://evs.nci.nih.gov/ftp1/MED-RT/MED-RT%20Documentation.pdf#:%7E:text=RxNorm,%20a%20formal%20standardized%20medication%20terminology%20published%20by,structural%20classification%20and%20therapeutics%20indexing;%20and%20the%20Systematized"
                            >MED-RT Documentation (nih.gov)</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>HL7 Balloting [Internet]. HL7. March 3 2021. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://confluence.hl7.org/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=19136726"
                            >https://confluence.hl7.org/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=19136726</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cimino, J J. Desiderata for controlled medical vocabularies in the
                        twenty-first century. Methods of information in medicine vol. 37,4-5 (1998):
                        394-403.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Spackman K, Guillermo R. Examining SNOMED from the perspective of formal
                        ontological principles: Some preliminary analysis and observations. KR-MED
                        2004 Proceedings 2004; 72-80. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Campbell KE. Distributed development of a logic based controlled medical
                        Terminology. PhD Dissertation, Stanford University, June 1997. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cornet R, Chute CG. Health Concept and Knowledge Management: Twenty-five
                        Years of Evolution. Yearb Med Inform. 2016 Aug 2;Suppl 1(Suppl 1):S32-41.
                        doi: 10.15265/IYS-2016-s037. PMID: 27488404; PMCID: PMC5171511.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Rudolph S. Foundations of Description Logics. Krlsruhe Institute of
                        Technology [Internet]. 2011 May [cited 2022 Jul 7]. Available from:
                        https://www.aifb.kit.edu/images/1/19/DL-Intro.pdf </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Stram M, Seheult J, Sinard J, et al. ; Members of the Informatics
                        Committee, College of American Pathologists. A survey of LOINC code
                        selection practices among participants of the College of American
                        Pathologists Coagulation (CGL) and Cardiac Markers (CRT) proficiency testing
                        programs. Arch Pathol Lab Med 2020; 144 (5): 586–96.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Enhancing the drug ontology with semantically-rich representation of
                        National Drug codes and RxNorm unique concept identifiers [Internet]. BMC
                        Bioinformatics. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-019-3192-8"
                            >https://bmcbioinformatics.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12859-019-3192-8</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Bietenbeck A, Boeker M, Schulz S. NPU, loinc, and SNOMED CT: A comparison
                        of terminologies for laboratory results reveals individual advantages and a
                        lack of possibilities to encode interpretive comments [Internet]. De
                        Gruyter. De Gruyter; 2018 [cited 2022Oct19]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.1515/labmed-2018-0103/html?lang=en"
                        />
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SHIELD Participants. Discussion on LOINC Challenges. [Personal interview,
                        6 May] Zoom; 2022 (unpublished).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Lin M, Vreeman D, McDonald C, et al. Auditing consistency and usefulness
                        of LOINC use among three large institutions—using version spaces for
                        grouping LOINC codes. J Biomed Inform 2012; 45 (4): 658–66.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Lin M, Vreeman D, McDonald C, et al. A characterization of local LOINC
                        mapping for laboratory tests in three large institutions. Methods Inf Med
                        2011; 50 (2): 105–14.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cholan RA, Pappas G, Rehwoldt G, Sills AK, Korte ED, Appleton IK, Scott
                        NM, Rubinstein WS, Brenner SA, Merrick R, Hadden WC, Campbell KE, Waters MS.
                        Encoding laboratory testing data: case studies of the national
                        implementation of HHS requirements and related standards in five
                        laboratories. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2022 May 25:ocac072. doi:
                        10.1093/jamia/ocac072. Epub ahead of print. PMID: 35639494.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Adamusiak T, Bodenreider O. Quality assurance in LOINC using Description
                        Logic. AMIA Annu Symp Proc. 2012;2012:1099-108. Epub 2012 Nov 3. PMID:
                        23304386; PMCID: PMC3540427.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LOINC Document Ontology. Regenstrief [Internet]. 2022 [cited 2022 Jul 7].
                        Available from: https://loinc.org/document-ontology/ </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LOINC Hierarchy Browser [Internet]. Regenstrief. Available from:
                        https://loinc.org/tree/?about </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LOINC License [Internet]. Copyright Notice and License. Regenstrief. 2020.
                        Available from: https://loinc.org/kb/license/ </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Campbell J, Campbell WS. Nebraska Lexicon Release Notes: Cancer Protocols
                        and Observables Ontology [Internet]. 2017 Mar [cited 2022 Jul 7]. Available
                        from:
                        https://app1.unmc.edu/pathmicro/umls/docs/Nebraska_Lexicon_Release_Notes_20170331.pdf
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LOINC Submission Queue Stats [Internet]. Regenstreif. July 6 2022.
                        Available from: <link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/submissions/stats/"
                            >https://loinc.org/submissions/stats/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Nelson SJ, Zeng K, Kilbourne J, Powell T, Moore R. Normalized names for
                        clinical drugs: RxNorm at 6 years. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2011
                        Jul-Aug;18(4):441-8. doi: 10.1136/amiajnl-2011-000116. Epub 2011 Apr 21.
                        PMID: 21515544; PMCID: PMC3128404.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Termlex. LOINC and SNOMED CT: LOINC SNOMED CT Extension - why, what and
                        how [Internet]. LinkedIn. 2022 [cited 2022Oct19]. Available from:
                        https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/loinc-snomed-ct-extension-why-what-how-termlex/?trackingId=XkAk09Q2Xn3Y0kj2HUSnXg%3D%3D </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Covid-19 value sets in VSAC [Internet]. U.S. National Library of Medicine.
                        National Institutes of Health; [cited 2023Mar10]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/vsac/support/usingvsac/covid19valuesets.html"
                            >https://www.nlm.nih.gov/vsac/support/usingvsac/covid19valuesets.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
