<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Global Health and International Collaboration</title>
    <section>
        <title>IKM Relevance to Global Health and International Collaboration</title>
        <para>Before shifting our discussion to the topic of health and IKM collaboration at the
            global scale, the intention of this section is to take a moment to summarize our
            discussion at the national level before discussing various aspects of international
            collaboration. The previous parts of this work define the importance of IKM in
            healthcare to achieve coordinated and standardized ways to integrate healthcare data
            across systems. In addition, the volume series on <link xlink:href="http://ikm.dev"
                >IKM.dev</link> explore the course of data management in various service lines,
            highlighting emerging IT challenges and legal issues for maintaining and exchanging
            healthcare data. We can summarize the challenges we have discussed in two main areas: a
            challenge in the clinical setting and a challenge in the laboratory setting. </para>
        <para>In the clinical setting, Healthcare IT is intended to ease provider workload and
            ultimately improve patient care. However, the current inconsistencies can impact patient
            safety, provider efficiency, and other areas of patient care. For example, a patient’s
            primary care physician discovers a potentially pre-malignant mole on the patient’s back
            and flags it for follow up. When this patient moves across the country and receives care
            at a different healthcare system, the patient’s information is transferred to their new
            provider. Yet, this is where the “pre-malignant” description of the mole is lost because
            of a difference in the systems’ encoding standards. Neither the clinician nor the
            patient receives further signals to revisit the dermatologist for follow-up on the
            pre-malignant mole. The patient later presents with lower back pain and the mole is
            determined to be malignant and metastatic. Although the rapid development of healthcare
            IT has enabled organizations to transfer and exchange patient data at a more advanced
            level, the quality and accuracy of that transfer is impacted by the use of disparate
            terminology standards and differences between healthcare systems.</para>
        <para> In the laboratory setting, the goal has always been to move laboratory data through
            numerous systems while maintaining the data’s original structure and meaning. However,
            ever-increasing system complexity and reliance on low-quality data has ultimately
            decreased the quality of care across the healthcare ecosystem. While lab data is
            analyzed and transferred from the Laboratory Information System (LIS) to Provider EHRs
            to appropriate end users, much of the meaning of the original report is lost. Only 22 -
            26% of the single-trip data integrity is achieved, highlight the need for greater
            interoperability standards. [1]</para>
        <para>Efforts to standardize clinical terminology systems is often impacted by data siloes
            and incompatible Healthcare IT systems that make data difficult to exchange and
            interpret at a national level. [2] Health information specialists around the world noted
            the lack of interoperability standards between different systems during the COVID-19
            pandemic. Recently, we have seen a growing awareness and recognition of the need to
            standardize clinical terminology across the US and around the world. This chapter
            intends to explore various ongoing efforts to achieve interoperability at the
            international level, the current utilization of IKM in the areas of global health,
            on-going international collaborations, challenges, and potential opportunities for
            further international collaboration to improve the quality of healthcare around the
            world.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction </title>
        <para>Numerous international organizations have been established to collaborate on global
            health initiatives and to expand upon certain areas of focus, like public health. [3]
            This chapter will introduce the overall landscape of international healthcare
            organizations participating in global health, on-going efforts to achieve international
            interoperable digital health infrastructure, challenges with global interoperability,
            and potential solutions. Healthcare IT has been one of the rapidly growing areas that
            has gained further momentum following the COVID-19 global pandemic.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Brief History of Global Health</title>
        <para>Global health originates from efforts to control infectious diseases and individual
            health through the delivery of healthcare to 16<superscript>th</superscript> and
                17<superscript>th</superscript> century European colonies. [4] Great Britain,
            France, and Portugal established colonies in India, China, Africa and elsewhere, where
            infectious diseases were devastating to both the native and European colonist
            populations. [5] Diseases spread rapidly, wiping out large portions of the population in
            the first years of colonization and giving birth to the field of Tropical Medicine. [6]
            Tropical Medicine bloomed throughout much of the 19<superscript>th</superscript> century
            and expanded to the field of public health with the development of military medicine and
            medical missions as more people traveled across the world. </para>
        <para>The formation of three organizations served as the precursor to forming a Health
            Committee under the League of Nations after World War II. [7] The International Sanitary
            Convention was formed in 1851 to create an international code for containing epidemics
            when a series of six cholera pandemics claimed the lives of thousands of tradesmen on
            the Silk Road between Rome and China. The Pan-American Sanitary Bureau was formed by the
            US and their trade partners in Central and South American in 1924, addressing the
            outbreak of yellow fever and starting the immigration health conversation. [8] The third
            group was the Rockefeller Foundation International Board of Health in 1913 as the single
            largest funder of global health in the early part of the 20<superscript>th</superscript>
            century, constructing public health schools in North America and Europe to train
            personnel to send to Latin America and the Caribbean to treat “tropical diseases”.
            [9]</para>
        <para>After World War II, the United Nations (UN) was formed and approved a constitution for
            the formation of the WHO that provided a wide range of aid to developing countries in
            the midst of the Cold War. After World War II, the creation and participation of
            Non-Governmental Organizations (NGOs), such as the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and
            the World Bank, increased to support re-building global infrastructure in the post-war
            era. [10] [11] </para>
        <para> Much of global health in the earlier years was shaped around tropical medicine and
            the public health work of overseas colonies. This trend was expanded to the work of
            medical missions and military medicine that provided a strong foundation for
            international collaboration in the latter half of the 21<superscript>st</superscript>
            century. [12] </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>International Organizations Collaborating on Healthcare IT</title>
        <para>The global trend of adopting computerized medical record systems was spearheaded by
            digital movements in the United States. In 2003, the Institute of Medicine, a division
            of the national Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine chose to coin the term,
                <emphasis role="italic">electronic health records</emphasis>, with the goal of
            computerizing medical records to improve safety and quality of patient-centered care. In
            2005, the World Health Assembly adopted the resolution WHA58.28 on electronic Health
            (eHealth) and urged Member States “to consider drawing up a long-term strategic plan for
            developing and implementing eHealth services… to develop the infrastructure for
            information and communication technologies for health … to promote equitable, affordable
            and universal access to their benefits.” [13] Passing this resolution encouraged more
            than 120 Member States, including low-and middle-income countries, to direct their
            efforts towards implementing eHealth to meet their country’s health priorities and
            resources through action-oriented steps. </para>
        <para>The U.S. federal government’s announcement of Health Information Technology for
            Economic and Clinical Health (HITECH) Act in 2009 set aside $27 billion for an incentive
            program that encouraged hospitals and healthcare systems to adopt EHRs. [14] In 2010,
            WHO and SNOMED International initiated a formal collaborative relationship. SNOMED
            International and WHO began aligning their respective standards by enabling SNOMED CT®
            users to use WHO classifications, creating a joint and interoperable medical terminology
            system. [15] </para>
        <para>Additional United Nations Health Assembly sessions in 2013 and 2018 continued
            encouraging Member States to adopt eHealth strategies and identify priority areas,
            creating online public forums, providing technical consultations, and utilizing WHO
            regional committees to improve the global strategy on digital health. [16] </para>
        <para>Below is a list of several international organizations that have joined collective
            efforts to achieve standardization in a particular domain of healthcare and are actively
            collaborating with one another worldwide. While this list provides some key examples, it
            is not exhaustive and there are many other international organizations that contribute
            to standardizing clinical terminology or language in healthcare.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Digital Imaging and Communication in Medicine (DICOM)</title>
            <para>DICOM provides the international standard for medical images and related
                information, defining formats for medical images that “can be exchanged with the
                data and quality necessary for clinical use”. [17] Established in 1993, DICOM has
                been an established name in cardiology imaging, radiology, dentistry, ophthalmology,
                and other medical service lines that involve any radiologic devices including X-ray,
                CT, MRI, and ultrasound. DICOM drove efforts to replace X-ray film with digital
                images, eliminating industry waste and improving the transfer of high-quality
                images. [17] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Global Medical Device Nomenclature Agency (GMDN)</title>
            <para>When a medical device is developed, it needs to go through a number of regulatory
                approval steps. GMDN provides a standardized common language for all medical
                technology and collaborates with medical device regulators, manufacturers, and other
                relevant healthcare stakeholders to incorporate and develop established standards.
                Established in 1991 as the Global Harmonization Task Force that took over its
                precursor organization called the International Medical Device Regulatory Forum
                (IMDRF), GMDN helps accelerate and standardize medical device regulation globally
                with more than 70 national medical device regulators across more than 145 member
                countries worldwide. [18] [19] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Health Level Seven International (HL7)</title>
            <para>Founded in 1987, Health Level Seven International (HL7) is a not-for-profit
                standard-development organization that provides a digital framework and relevant
                standards “for the exchange, integration, sharing and retrieval of electronic health
                information that supports clinical practice and the management, delivery and
                evaluation of health services.” [20] HL7 collaborates with over 25 benefactors from
                both private and public spheres across the US and around the world. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Integrating the Healthcare Enterprise (IHE)</title>
            <para>Integrating the Healthcare Enterprise (IHE) is an international organization with
                the vision of “enabling seamless and secure access to health information that is
                usable whenever and wherever needed”. Established in 17 countries around the globe
                with IHE national deployment committees and other stakeholder organizations from 21
                countries, members come from four main sources: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Health IT and Consulting Companies</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Government Agencies or Not-for-Profit Organizations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Provider or Research Organizations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Standards Development Organizations [21] </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>Healthcare professionals and relevant stakeholders collaborate to configure the
                way computer systems in healthcare share information through the coordinated use of
                DICOM and HL7. [21] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>International Council for Harmonization of Technical Requirements for
                Pharmaceuticals for Human Use (ICH)</title>
            <para>International Council for Harmonization of Technical Requirements for
                Pharmaceuticals for Human Use (ICH) owns a Medical Dictionary for Regulatory
                Activities (MedDRA) in the United Kingdom and supports the approval of regulatory
                activities for medical devices by developing highly specific standardized medical
                terminology to facilitate sharing of regulatory information globally. ICH uses
                MedDRA to catalyze the process of registration, documentation, and safety monitoring
                of medical products before and after a medical device is fully authorized for use.
                MedDRA focuses on key pharmacovigilance terms from the European Medicines Agency and
                the UK’s Medicines &amp; Healthcare products Regulatory Agency. [22]</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>LOINC®</title>
            <para>As we have discussed in the previous chapters, LOINC®, is an effort by the
                Regenstrief Institute, a non-profit international research organization that
                successfully collaborated with SNOMED International. The collaboration resulted in
                producing a LOINC®/SNOMED CT® Expression Association and Map Sets file based on
                SNOMED CT® International Release, July 2017 and version 2.58 of LOINC® in December
                2016. Their 2022 collaboration also produced The LOINC Ontology: A LOINC® and SNOMED
                CT® interoperability solution, a standardized terminology system that combines
                clinical and regulatory requirements in a single solution. SNOMED CT® provides the
                computerized framework while LOINC® provides laboratory and pathology content in
                easy-to-read format to countries that have not adopted LOINC® yet. [23]</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED International</title>
            <para>SNOMED started in 1965 as a Systematized Nomenclature Pathology (SNOP) and created
                SNOMED CT® in 1991 and SNOMED International in 2007. [24] SNOMED International is
                the trading name for a not-for-profit organization called The International Health
                Terminology Standards Development Organization (IHTSDO). [25] The purpose of IHTSDO
                is to support safe, accurate, and effective health information exchange, with over
                29 member countries that support four major areas; customer relations, operations,
                products and services, and strategy.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Medical Terminology Standards Used in Healthcare IT Collaboration</title>
        <para>Below is a list of common terminology standards used in health information and
            technology.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Current Procedural Terminology (CPT®) </title>
            <para>Current Procedural Terminology (CPT®) is a code set by the American Medical
                Association to bill outpatient and office procedure. [27] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Healthcare Common Procedure Coding System (HCPCS)</title>
            <para>The Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) generates the Healthcare
                Common Procedure Coding System (HCPCS), a collection of standardized codes that
                represent medical procedures, supplies, products and services. Health insurance
                entities utilize the HCPCS to process claims by Medicare and other insurers. Level I
                of HCPCS consists of Current Procedural Terminology® (HCPT). Level II of HCPCS
                includes the Current Dental Terminology (HDT) codes. [28] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Tenth Revision International Classification of Disease (ICD-10)</title>
            <para>The tenth revision of the International Classification of Disease (ICD-10) is
                designed primarily for validating mortality statistics. ICD-10 promotes
                international comparability for collecting, processing, classifying and presenting
                mortality data. ICD-10 consists of tabular lists containing cause-of-death titles
                and codes, inclusion and exclusion terms for cause-of-death titles, an alphabetical
                index to diseases and nature of injury, external causes of injury, table of drugs
                and chemicals, and description, guidelines, and coding rules. [29] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>LOINC®</title>
            <para>The Regenstrief in Germany started the Logical Observation Identifiers Names and
                Codes in 1994 with Clem McDonald’s idea of developing a common terminology for
                laboratory and clinical observations because the growing trend demonstrated the use
                of laboratory data not only for clinical care but also for research and management
                purposes. The terminology system that began at Indiana University now collaborates
                with HL7 to send numerous lab results with painstaking efforts to continue
                standardizing existing codes with the addition of new codes or other codes from the
                growing number of various other sources. [30] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>MEDCIN</title>
            <para>MEDCIN is an electronic medical record engine that allows healthcare workers to
                enter, retrieve, and maintain relevant clinical information efficiently at the point
                of care, store information as coded data elements, and produce narrative reports
                from the same data. Medicomp Systems, Inc. created MEDCIN and continues developing
                the advanced version available for healthcare providers. As a leading provider of
                clinical documentation tools, Medicomp has spent over 45 years with the goal of
                driving better patient care through better management of patient’s clinical data and
                is now looking into adopting artificial intelligence (IA) technologies and
                interoperability to enhance its current documentation technology. [31] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Radiology Lexicon (RadLex)</title>
            <para>Radiology Lexicon (RadLex) is a radiology terminology system by the Radiologic
                Society of North America (RSNA). It is a reservoir for a unified language of
                radiology terms for standardized indexing and retrieval of radiologic information
                resources. It unifies and supplements other lexicons and standards including SNOMED
                CT® and DICOM. [15] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>RxNorm</title>
            <para>RxNorm is one of the Unified Medical Language System®. The NIH website describes
                it as a source of “normalized names for clinical drugs and links its names to many
                of the drug vocabularies commonly used in pharmacy management and drug interaction
                software, including those of First Databank, Micromedex, Multum, and Gold Standard
                Drug Database.” [15] The National Library of Medicine started the RxNorm Project in
                2001 and has continued to grow the effort with collaboration from HL7. [15] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SNOMED CT®</title>
            <para>SNOMED CT® was created in 1999 and released in 2002. The Systematized Nomenclature
                of Pathology (SNOP), founded in 1965, is the origin of SNOMED that developed its own
                terminology system and gave the name SNOMED CT® that has been widely used in the
                United States. In 2013, EHR systems in the United States were required to include
                SNOMED CT® for the Stage 2 Meaningful Use certification of the clinical software
                systems installed in medical settings. [15] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>United Code for Units of Measure (UCUM)</title>
            <para>The United Code for Units of Measure (UCUM) is a code system intended to include
                all units of measures being contemporarily used in international science,
                engineering, and business. [15] </para>
            <para>The list of the commonly used healthcare standards is growing faster than ever
                before. One challenging aspect of developing global healthcare standards is that the
                act of developing the standard needs to start somewhere on a small scale with
                testing, iterative improvements, and gaining credibility before it can expand. It
                takes both time and painstaking efforts to develop a standard and tool that delivers
                the standard to end users. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Application of IKM in Global Health and International Collaboration During the
            COVID-19 Pandemic </title>
        <para>While efforts to standardize various types of healthcare terminology are underway, the
            Covid-19 pandemic demonstrated the need for interoperable and lossless data
            transfer.</para>
        <section>
            <title>eHealth Exchange to improve the exchange of patient data between agencies and
                medical entities</title>
            <para>eHealth Exchange is an interoperability system a “one connection-to-many” model,
                creating the principal network that connects federal agencies and non-federal
                organizations, including over 75% of U.S. hospitals, health systems, and clinics of
                various types and sizes, to share patient records for better access of care of
                better quality. [34] The eHealth Exchange further supports reporting of the social
                determinants of health, such as public health reporting, quality reporting, and
                disability and insurance determinations. The eHealth Exchange uses InterSystems
                    HealthShare<superscript>TM</superscript> Managed Solutions to make a more
                powerful information exchange, scale its network and maintain added features such as
                push notifications and discrete data-level queries using HL7 Fast Healthcare
                Interoperability Resources (FHIR®). [34] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Working with a better early warning system for emerging infectious
                diseases</title>
            <para>The Covid-19 pandemic also provided an opportunity to catalyze an existing
                data-sharing methodology. WHO’s Epidemic Intelligence from Open Sources (EIOS) was
                established 2017 with the purpose of building a global community of public health
                stakeholders to share ideas, expertise, and best practices for facilitating early
                threat detection. WHO then launched its hub for Pandemic and Epidemic Intelligence
                which empowered traditional data sharing with artificial intelligence, further
                contributing to the exchange of emerging information about coronavirus throughout
                the pandemic. This system is activated not only for COVID-19 but other infectious
                diseases including zoonotic diseases around the globe now. [35] </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Challenges in global collaboration</title>
            <para>Many international organizations discuss the importance of interoperability and
                the dire need for connected and translatable systems to exchanges health data,
                scripts, and imaging in a standardized format. In this section, we discuss the
                challenges of interoperability in general and at the international level and
                potential solutions. </para>
            <para>The first challenge is the sheer amount and types of data that must be made
                interoperable. There is a wide range of data, disciplines, and file types in
                healthcare, all of which must be exchanged without losing structure or meaning. As
                demonstrated by the different terminology languages and respective organizations,
                there are a multitude of areas that require standardization, such as laboratory and
                pathology reports and images, diagnostic imaging reports, medication management,
                electronic prescriptions, patient access, and regulatory approval for medical
                devices. Determining the priority for which data to make interoperable first or
                which components would provide patients and providers with the greatest value add is
                a difficult question. [36] </para>
            <para>The next challenge is that efforts to improve interoperability require extensive
                research, trial and error, time, and resources to create a successful model. The
                desire to achieve interoperable EHRs or Electronic Medical Records (EMRs) has been
                around for a long time in many developed countries like the United States, Canada,
                and United Kingdom, but even in these developed countries, the existing EMR has a
                long way to go to achieve the data quality needed to provide safe patient care and
                improve provider satisfaction. [36] Even before discussing interoperability, rolling
                out EHRs can pose a challenge in many countries. </para>
            <para>Third, we need to provide a more equitable approach for middle or low-income
                countries, instead of merely generalizing the implementation of IKM with the promise
                of unconditionally improving the quality of medical care. [36]. Some countries do
                not have the necessary medical professionals due to brain drain or the lack of
                medical infrastructures and cannot afford to have a separate pool of IT
                professionals or researchers in the field of medicine. International organizations
                need to assess different situations in different parts of the world, research every
                situation judiciously, and allocate appropriate IKM resources to provide impactful
                assistance. </para>
            <para>Fourth, not all nations in the world have the equal need for all interoperable
                systems or a-la-carte terminology systems in all service lines. [36] While some
                nations have a more need for the standardized clinical terminology in the field of
                tropical medicine, other nations have a more need for standardized cancer
                terminology and relevant interoperable system to exchange lab data and radiologic
                images. Achieving the global interoperability may neglect what’s most needed in a
                particular area of the world or at the scale of each continent. </para>
            <para>Finally, new technologies evolve more rapidly than ever before, bringing new legal
                and logistical challenges over data management, including emerging healthcare or
                well-being apps, telemedicine, and managing international patient data. [36] We need
                reliable international organizations that oversee these emerging interdisciplinary
                areas while identifying and developing standardization and technical tools for
                deployment around the world. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Summary on Lessons Learned</title>
            <para>According to the research survey conducted by the Global Digital Health
                Partnership, the following four top-three barriers in advancing the global
                interoperability were identified (Items 3 and 4 were tied): [36] </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>EHRs lack the capability to take action based on exchanged data</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Poor usability and negative impact on providers’ workflows</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Difficulty managing coordinated collective action among multiple
                        organizations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Increasing cost due to interoperability that entities cannot afford
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>Most countries have systems that generate and communicate data to other providers
                but they lack the necessary functions to achieve truly interoperable data exchange
                and management. One area for the global effort to improve healthcare IT to focus on
                is recognizing the lack of EHR capabilities as the most important barrier to
                overcome. This barrier is directly tied to the “poor usability” barrier in cases
                where EHRs possess capabilities that are underused because adopting the new language
                takes significant training and time. [36] Redesigning clinical process is often an
                external quality improvement initiative in addition to implementing a good EHR
                system, adding more burden and disrupting the on-going flow within the existing EHR
                capability. </para>
            <para>Interoperability in healthcare is inherently more complex than in any other fields
                because achieving the purpose of interoperability involves multiple stakeholders on
                different sectors within healthcare and each of their agreement with the following
                stakeholders: payers, providers and pharmaceutical components. In addition,
                different countries operate on various models of healthcare insurance and network
                management that its own EHR system and interoperability planning need to scrutinize.
                Local, state, and federal regulations must cooperate with private and NGO
                institutions to solve these challenges. [36] </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cholan RA, Pappas G, Rehwoldt G, Sills AK, Korte ED, Appleton K, Scott NM,
                        Rubinstein WS, Brenner SA, Merrick R, Hadden WC, Campbell KE, Waters MS.
                        Encoding laboratory testing data: case studies of the national
                        implementation of HHS requirements and related standards in five
                        laboratories. [internet]. USA; 2022 [cited 2024 March 20]. Available from:
                            <link
                            xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article/29/8/1372/6592172"
                            >https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article/29/8/1372/6592172</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Bernstam EV, Warner JI, Krauss JC, Ambinder E, Rubinstein WS, Komatsoulis
                        G, Miller RS, Chen JL. Quantitating and assessing interoperability between
                        electronic health records. [internet]. USA; 2022 [cited 2024 March 19].
                        Available from: <link xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35015861/"
                            >https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35015861/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Greene DN, McClintock, Durant TJS. Interoperability: COVID-19 as an
                        Impetus for Change. [internet]. Clinical Chemistry. United States; 2021
                        [cited 2024 March 22]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7929044/"
                            >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7929044/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hoist J. Global Health – emergence, hegemonic trends and biomedical
                        reductionism. [internet]. Global Health. United States; 2020 [cited 2024
                        March 25]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7201392/"
                            >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7201392/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Palilonis MA. An Introduction to Global Health and Global Health Ethics: A
                        Brief History of Global Health. [internet] Wake Forest University; 2020
                        [cited 2024 March 21]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://cbhs.wfu.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/Topic-3-A-Brief-History-of-Global-Health.pdf"
                            >https://cbhs.wfu.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/Topic-3-A-Brief-History-of-Global-Health.pdf</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Farmer P, Kleinman A, Kim J, Balisico M. Reimagining Global Health – An
                        Introduction. United States (US): California Series in Public Anthropology;
                        2013. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Boudreau FG. Health Committee of the League of Nations. United States
                        (US): The Milbank Memorial Fund Quarterly, 1933. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.milbank.org/wp-content/uploads/mq/volume-13/issue-01/13-1-Health-Work-of-the-League-of-Nations.pdf"
                            >https://www.milbank.org/wp-content/uploads/mq/volume-13/issue-01/13-1-Health-Work-of-the-League-of-Nations.pdf</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Pan American Health Organization. History of PAHO. [internet]. WHO; 2024
                        [cited 2024 March 26] Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.paho.org/en/who-we-are/history-paho"
                            >https://www.paho.org/en/who-we-are/history-paho</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Institution: International Health Board. [internet]. Rockefeller Archive
                        Center: 2024 [cited 2024 March 26]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://resource.rockarch.org/institutions/international-health-board/"
                            >https://resource.rockarch.org/institutions/international-health-board/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>International Monetary Fund. What is the IMF? [internet]. 2024 [cited 2024
                        March 26]. Available from:
                        https://www.imf.org/en/About/Factsheets/IMF-at-a-Glance</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>World Bank Group. Explore History. The World Bank; 2024 [cited 2024 March
                        26]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.worldbank.org/en/archive/history"
                            >https://www.worldbank.org/en/archive/history</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Nungarai N. The Changing Face of Healthcare Missions: Opportunities and
                        Challenges in the 21<superscript>st</superscript></para>
                    <para> Century. [internet] Lausanne Global Analysis; 2024 January [cited 2024
                        March 26]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://lausanne.org/content/lga/2024-01/the-changing-face-of-healthcare-missions-opportunities-and-challenges-in-the-21st-century"
                            >https://lausanne.org/content/lga/2024-01/the-changing-face-of-healthcare-missions-opportunities-and-challenges-in-the-21st-century</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>World Health Organization. Global strategy on digital health 2020-2025.
                        [internet]. WHO; 2021 [cited 2024 March 27]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/documents/gs4dhdaa2a9f352b0445bafbc79ca799dce4d.pdf"
                            >https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/documents/gs4dhdaa2a9f352b0445bafbc79ca799dce4d.pdf</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Commonwealth Fund. The Federal Government Has Put Billions into
                        Promoting electronic Health Record Use: How is it Going? [internet].
                        Improving Health Care Quality; 2021 [cited 2024 March 27]. Available from:
                            <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.commonwealthfund.org/improving-health-care-quality"
                            >https://www.commonwealthfund.org/improving-health-care-quality</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SNOMED International: Leading healthcare terminology, worldwide. Our
                        Partners. [internet]. Our partners. [cited 2024 March 27]. Available from:
                            <link xlink:href="https://www.snomed.org/our-partnerships"
                            >https://www.snomed.org/our-partnerships</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>World Health Organization. World Health Assembly. [internet]. WHO; 2024
                        [cited 2024 March 27]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.who.int/about/accountability/governance/world-health-assembly"
                            >https://www.who.int/about/accountability/governance/world-health-assembly</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>DICOM. About Digital Imaging and Communication in Medicine (DICOM):
                        Overview. [internet]. 2021. [cited 2024 March 23]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.dicomstandard.org/about-home"
                            >https://www.dicomstandard.org/about-home</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>IMDRF. About International Medical Device Regulator Forum. [internet] 2021
                        [cited 2024 March 21]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.imdrf.org/about"
                            >https://www.imdrf.org/about</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Global Medical Device Nomenclature (GMDN). What is GMDN? [internet] 2024
                        [cited 2024 March 25]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.gmdnagency.org/what-we-do/"
                            >https://www.gmdnagency.org/what-we-do/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>HL7 International. About HL7. [internet] 2024 [cited 2024 March 24].
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.hl7.org/about/index.cfm?ref=nav"
                            >https://www.hl7.org/about/index.cfm?ref=nav</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Integrating the Healthcare Enterprise (IHE) International. Frequently
                        Asked Questions. [internet] 2024 [cited 2024 March 25]. Available from:
                            <link xlink:href="https://www.ihe.net/about_ihe/faq/"
                            >https://www.ihe.net/about_ihe/faq/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA). Welcome to MedDRA.
                        [internet] 2024 [cited 2024 March 25]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.meddra.org/"
                        >https://www.meddra.org/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SNOMED International. SNOMED International determines global standards for
                        health terms, an essential part of improving the health of humankind.
                        [internet] Regenstrief Institute Inc. and SNOMED International; 2024 [cited
                        2024 March 25]. Available from: <link xlink:href="https://www.snomed.org/"
                            >https://www.snomed.org/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cornet R, Keizer N. Forty years of SNOMED: a literature review. [internet]
                        BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making. 2008 Oct [cited 2024 March 25].
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2582789/"
                            >https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2582789/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SNOMED International. Frequently Asked Questions. [internet] Regenstrief
                        Institute Inc. and SNOMED International; 2024 [cited 2024 March 25].
                        Available from: <link xlink:href="https://www.snomed.org/"
                            >https://www.snomed.org/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SNOMED International. International Health Terminology Standards
                        Development Organization. [internet] Regenstrief Institute Inc. and SNOMED
                        International; 2024 [cited 2024 March 25]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/International+Health+Terminology+Standards+Development+Organisation"
                            >https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCGLOSS/International+Health+Terminology+Standards+Development+Organisation</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>American Medical Association (AMA). CPT®. [internet] 2024 [cited 2024
                        March 27]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.ama-assn.org/practice-management/cpt"
                            >https://www.ama-assn.org/practice-management/cpt</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>UMLS Vocabularies. HCPCS (HCPCS- Healthcare Common Procedure Coding
                        System) – Synopsis. [internet] 2024 [cited 2024 March 27]. Available from:
                            <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/research/umls/sourcereleasedocs/current/HCPCS/index.html#:~:text=The%20Healthcare%20Common%20Procedure%20Coding,%2C%20supplies%2C%20products%20and%20services"
                            >https://www.nlm.nih.gov/research/umls/sourcereleasedocs/current/HCPCS/index.html#:~:text=The%20Healthcare%20Common%20Procedure%20Coding,%2C%20supplies%2C%20products%20and%20services</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. International Classification
                        of Disease, Tenth Revision (ICD-10). [internet] USA; 2021 [cited 2024 March
                        26]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/icd/icd10.htm"
                            >https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/icd/icd10.htm</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>LOINC – The freely available standard for identifying health measurements,
                        observations, and documents [internet]. Loinc.org 2019. Available from:
                            <link xlink:href="https://loinc.org/">https://loinc.org/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Medicomp Systems. Medicomp Systems: A History of Innovation. [internet].
                        2024 [cited 2024 March 26]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://medicomp.com/history/"
                            >https://medicomp.com/history/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>HIMSS. Terminology Standards. [internet] 2024 [cited 2024 March 26].
                        Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.himss.org/terminology-standards"
                            >https://www.himss.org/terminology-standards</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>eHealth Exchange. Barriers to Health IT Interoperability Are Not Just
                        Technical; They Also Include Legal and Policy Impediments. 2024 [cited 2024
                        March 27]. Available from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://ehealthexchange.org/what-we-do/governance/"
                            >https://ehealthexchange.org/what-we-do/governance/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>FHIR Fact Sheets | HealthIT.gov [Internet]. www.healthit.gov. Available
                        from: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.healthit.gov/topic/standards-technology/standards/fhir-fact-sheets"
                            >https://www.healthit.gov/topic/standards-technology/standards/fhir-fact-sheets</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>World Health Organization. The Epidemic Intelligence from Open Source
                        Initiative. [internet] WHO; 2024 [cited 2024 March 26] Available from: <link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/initiatives/eios"
                            >https://www.who.int/initiatives/eios</link></para>
                    
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Global Digital Health Partnership (GDNP). Advancing Interoperability
                        Together Globally: GDHP White Paper on Interoperability. [internet] GDHP;
                        July 2020 [cited 2024 March 26]. Available from:
                        https://gdhp.health/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/GDHP-Interop-Final.pdf</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    
</chapter>