<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1">
    <title>Healthcare Data Management</title>
    <sect1>
        <?oxy_comment_start author="tocrow" timestamp="20240712T150553-0400" comment="Probably need ot fix intro, but will sync with Rania"?>
        <title>Introduction to Healthcare Data Management</title>
        <para>The healthcare data management landscape is rapidly evolving, driven by advances in
            technology and the increasing demand for comprehensive, interoperable healthcare
            systems. Data management in healthcare encompasses the practices, processes, and
            technologies used to collect, store, manage, and analyze health-related information.
            With the ultimate goal of improving patient care, healthcare data management supports
            clinical decision-making, research, and policy development. The integration of data from
            diverse sources, including EHRs, medical imaging, genomic data, and wearable technology,
            presents both opportunities and challenges to improve data quality, privacy, and
            security. [1]</para>
        <para>The importance of data in clinical and research settings cannot be overstated.
            High-quality, accessible, and secure data is foundational to evidence-based medicine and
            enables healthcare providers to make informed decisions, improves patient outcomes, and
            enhances the efficiency of healthcare services. Moreover, in research settings, data
            management plays a crucial role in the discovery of new treatments and understanding
            health trends and disease patterns. [2]</para>
        <para>IKM emerges as a pivotal concept to address the complexities of healthcare data
            management. IKM refers to the systematic management of knowledge and information across
            different sources and formats to facilitate the creation, sharing, and application of
            knowledge within the healthcare sector. The implementation of IKM strategies can
            significantly enhance the interoperability of healthcare systems, ensuring that data is
            not only accessible and usable across different platforms and institutions but also
            consistent and reliable. [3]<?oxy_comment_end?></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Mental Health Data Management</title>
        <para>Mental health data management is a critical aspect of healthcare that involves the
            collection, storage, analysis, and sharing of information related to mental health
            services and outcomes. Given the sensitive nature of mental health data, its management
            poses unique challenges in terms of privacy, security, and ethical considerations.
            Employing IKM principles can significantly enhance the effectiveness and efficiency of
            mental health data management, ensuring that patient information is handled with the
            utmost care and respect. [4]</para>
        <para>The collection of mental health data provokes inevitable challenges, primarily due to
            the stigma associated with mental illness and the resultant reluctance of individuals to
            share personal information. Privacy concerns are paramount, as the disclosure of mental
            health information can have significant social and personal consequences for
            individuals. [5] Ensuring the confidentiality and security of mental health data is,
            therefore, a critical concern that requires robust data management practices. To address
            these challenges, healthcare organizations must implement comprehensive data management
            strategies that prioritize patient privacy and data security. This includes the adoption
            of advanced encryption methods for data transmission, secure data storage solutions, and
            strict access controls. Additionally, fostering a culture of trust and transparency with
            patients can encourage the sharing of vital health information, thereby improving the
            quality of mental health services. [6]</para>
        <para>Integrating EHRs with mental-health specific modules is an example of the successful
            application of IKM principles in mental health data management. This application has
            enabled healthcare providers to access comprehensive patient profiles, facilitating
            personalized treatment plans and improving patient outcomes. Moreover, the use of
            standardized data formats and terminologies, as advocated by IKM, has improved the
            interoperability of mental health data across different healthcare systems, enhancing
            collaborative care and research efforts. [7] With mental health data in particular,
            healthcare systems must carefully monitor data access and usage to navigate potential
            patient rights, privacy, and data access issues, including involuntary admissions,
            restraint and seclusion records. [8] Improvements to mental health data management and
            the quality of mental health data can have impacts on real world data that would then
            support policy makers and make more informed decisions that can be tailored to mental
            health data and data management approaches per type of mental health treatment settings
            – hospital inpatient, residential and outpatient – and levels of care. [9] </para>
        <para>Another major challenge for mental health data management and IKM is keeping up with
            and integrating emerging technology. Today, more than 10,000 mental or behavioral health
            apps are publicly available on the iOS App Store with roughly 69% of them focusing on
            providing therapy, collecting self-assessment information, and monitoring symptoms. [10]
            The recently updated guidance on cellphones, health information, and the Health
            Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) by the U.S. Department of Health
            and Human Services (HHS) dictates that HIPAA Privacy Act does not apply to most health
            apps as these apps are not “covered entities” under the law. Currently, only official
            healthcare system patient portals that exchange messages with providers and store test
            results are protected by HIPAA. [11] As technology continues to improve and be
            implemented across the healthcare ecosystem, it is critical that data management efforts
            work to ensure that self-reported, at home, and other non-traditional methods of data
            collection meet required privacy, storage, and transmission standards.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Population Health Management (PHM)</title>
        <para>Population health management (PHM) is an approach aimed at improving the health
            outcomes of a specifically defined group. PHM relies heavily on the aggregation,
            analysis, and application of health data to drive decision-making and resource
            allocation. The integration of IKM principles into PHM can significantly enhance the
            ability to analyze complex datasets, identify health trends, and implement effective
            interventions. [12]</para>
        <para>Population health data encompasses a wide range of information, including healthcare
            utilization, outcomes, and social determinants of health. This data is crucial for
            identifying health disparities, managing chronic diseases, and improving community
            health. Effective PHM requires a robust data management system that can handle the
            volume and variety of data continually generated by healthcare systems and patient
            interactions. [13] </para>
        <para>Advanced analytics, including predictive modeling and machine learning, are key to
            extracting actionable insights from population health data. These techniques allow
            healthcare providers and policymakers to predict health outcomes, optimize resource
            allocation, and tailor interventions to specific populations. Implementing IKM
            principles ensures that real-world data from disparate sources is standardized and
            interoperable, facilitating comprehensive analyses and informed decision-making.
            [14]</para>
        <para>The application of IKM in PHM has the potential to transform healthcare delivery.
            Healthcare organizations can improve the accuracy of health assessments, enhance the
            effectiveness of interventions, and ultimately, achieve better health outcomes at lower
            costs by employing IKM to ensure data interoperability and leverage advanced analytics.
            Moreover, IKM supports continuous improvements to data quality and the adoption of PHM
            best practices. [15]</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Health Disparities</title>
            <para>Health disparity is a complex and nuanced topic that covers the differences in the
                way population groups access, receive, and experience various aspects of healthcare.
                These inequalities are caused by social, economic, environmental, and a variety of
                other factors and are constantly evolving as healthcare and the factors themselves
                change. [16]
                IKM offers an opportunity to not only identity health disparities but to also
                understand the various causes of the inequality. By improving the quality and
                interoperability of health data, researchers, public health officials, and providers
                could more accurately identify health disparities, develop personalized solutions to
                address the specific needs of population groups, and track changes to population
                groups using real-world data to maintain high-quality care and solutions. While IKM
                offers a wide array of information sources and data that could be used to support
                disparate communities, it is essential that patient privacy, ethics, and safety
                remain as driving factors. [17]</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Pediatric Data Management</title>
        <para>Pediatric data management focuses on the unique healthcare needs and challenges
            associated with collecting, storing, and utilizing health information for children. This
            area requires special attention due to the distinct physiological, developmental, and
            psychological characteristics of pediatric populations. The application of IKM
            principles can significantly improve the management and use of pediatric health data,
            ensuring that healthcare providers can deliver age-appropriate care that supports the
            healthy development of children. [18] </para>
        <para>Pediatric health data encompasses a broad spectrum of information, from birth records
            and immunizations to growth charts and developmental milestones. Managing this data
            effectively requires systems that can adapt to the rapid changes in health status and
            needs that characterize childhood and adolescence. Additionally, pediatric data
            management must address consent and privacy issues, particularly as they relate to the
            rights of minors and the involvement of parents or guardians. [19] </para>
        <para>Consent and ethical considerations are paramount in pediatric data management.
            Healthcare providers must navigate the complex legal and ethical landscape surrounding
            the collection and use of health data from minors, ensuring compliance with regulations
            that protect children’s privacy while simultaneously facilitating necessary medical
            care. IKM can support this process by providing frameworks for managing consent
            documentation and ensuring that data use policies are clearly communicated and followed.
            [20] </para>
        <para>An area of particular interest for pediatric data management is school, a core site of
            care for children aged five through 17 years old. Less than half of the US children have
            an assigned healthcare provider, but over 95% of children aged five through 17 years old
            go to school. [21] Evidence-based research suggests that healthy students earn better
            grades and have better attendance, stressing the opportunity for healthcare
            organizations, health partners, or schools themselves to use school as an opportunity to
            provide health screenings or address gaps in students’ care. Approximately 17% of public
            schools in the US offered telehealth services to students in the 2021-2022 school year,
            and this trend is projected to go up. IKM can support advancements in pediatric data
            management by coordinating care between clinics, schools, and other health systems
            involved in the delivery of care. [21]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Infectious Disease Research and Management  </title>
        <para>Infectious disease management and research are pivotal in the global healthcare
            landscape, especially in the wake of recent pandemics. Effective management requires the
            collection, analysis, and transfer of vast amounts of data to track disease spread,
            identify outbreaks, and inform public health responses in real time. IKM principles can
            enhance infectious disease management by ensuring high-quality, standardized, and
            interoperable real-world data that can be used by organizations to outline actionable
            management plans. [22] </para>
        <para>Infectious disease data management and research track the spread of infectious
            diseases, enabling health authorities to identify outbreaks quickly and implement
            containment measures. Real-time data collection and analysis are essential for
            monitoring disease patterns, responding to outbreaks, and predicting future health
            patterns. IKM facilitates the integration of data from multiple sources, including
            healthcare facilities, laboratories, public health departments, and non-traditional data
            collection methods like at home testing, to ensure a comprehensive view of the disease
            landscape across the US and around the world. [23] </para>
        <para>The integration of research and clinical data is vital for developing effective
            treatments and vaccines for infectious diseases. IKM principles support the
            standardization of data formats and terminologies, making it easier for researchers to
            aggregate and analyze data from diverse studies. IKM accelerates the translation of
            research findings into clinical practice, improving patient outcomes and public health
            responses around the world. [24] </para>
        <para>One notable example of a data-driven approach to infectious disease management is the
            global response to the COVID-19 pandemic. Health organizations worldwide utilized IKM
            principles to standardize data reporting, enabling the effective tracking of cases,
            vaccination rates, and emerging variants. This coordinated effort facilitated rapid
            research, informed public health policies, and guided the allocation of resources to
            areas most in need. [25] Another example of how IKM principles can support improved
            infectious disease management is the work by the Infectious Diseases Data Observatory
            (IDDO). IDDO is a scientifically independent, multi-disciplinary coalition that has been
            trying to identify and collate de-identified individual patient data (IPD) in a
            format-agnostic way. IKM could facilitate and support their efforts to track
            surveillance data in an established system for a wide range of infectious diseases, such
            as: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>COVID-19</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Malaria</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Visceral leishmaniasis</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Medicine quality</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Antimicrobial resistance</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Chagas disease</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ebola</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Schistosomiasis</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Soil-transmitted helminthiasis</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Lymphatic filariasis</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>HIV</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Trachoma</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Mycetoma</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>NOMA</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Melioidosis</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Scrub typhus [26]</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Rare Disease Research and Management</title>
        <para>Rare disease research and management present unique challenges due to the low
            prevalence of each condition, making data collection and analysis particularly
            difficult. The scarcity of data, combined with its often fragmented nature, hinders the
            development of effective treatments and care strategies. The application of IKM
            principles facilitates the aggregation, standardization, and sharing of rare disease
            data across health systems that may not normally have access. [27] </para>
        <para>Data plays a crucial role in the identification and research of rare diseases.
            Comprehensive data collection and analysis are essential for understanding the genetic
            and environmental factors associated with rare diseases, developing diagnostic tools,
            and identifying potential treatments. IKM can enhance the quality and accessibility of
            rare disease data, enabling researchers and clinicians to uncover patterns and
            connections that would otherwise remain obscured. [28] IKM principles advocate for the
            use of standardized data formats and terminologies to facilitate data sharing and
            collaboration among researchers worldwide. This approach not only improves the
            efficiency of data collection but also increases the chances of breakthroughs in
            understanding and treating rare diseases. [29] </para>
        <para>IKM plays a pivotal role in advancing rare disease research and improving patient
            care. IKM enables the integration of research findings into clinical practice more
            rapidly by supporting interoperable and easily accessible data from various sources.
            This integration is vital for developing effective treatment protocols and care
            strategies for rare diseases, ultimately improving patient outcomes and quality of life.
            [30] In addition, IKM can support efforts to improve rare disease management and
            research with the goal of obtaining more complete datasets, as shown in the work of the
                <emphasis role="italic">Task Force on Clinical Research Networks for Rare
                Diseases</emphasis> by the International Rare Diseases Research Consortium (IRDRC).
            The IRDRC designed the task force with the objective of analyzing the quality of data to
            be obtained via the growing global network, removing communication and technical
            barriers in managing and sharing rare disease data globally. [31] The National
            Institutes of Health (NIH) reports more than 7,000 rare diseases. Lurie Children's
            Hospital of Chicago states that one in 10 Americans has a rare disease. About half of
            these Americans are children. [32]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Cross-Disciplinary Data Integration and Management</title>
        <para>Cross-disciplinary data integration and management are essential for addressing
            complex health issues that span multiple areas of expertise. Integrating data from
            various disciplines, such as genomics, epidemiology, and social sciences can lead to a
            more comprehensive understanding of health and disease. The IKM principals can
            facilitate this integration, ensuring that data is not only interoperable but also
            meaningful across different research and clinical contexts. [33]</para>
        <para>The integration of data across disciplines is crucial for developing a holistic
            approach to patient care and public health. It allows for the consideration of a wide
            range of factors affecting health, from genetic predispositions to environmental and
            social determinants. IKM supports this integration by standardizing data formats and
            terminologies, enabling seamless data exchange and analysis across diverse fields. [34]
            Implementing IKM to support cross-disciplinary efforts will involve adopting common data
            standards, utilizing interoperable platforms, and fostering collaboration among
            stakeholders from different disciplines. These strategies ensure that data is not only
            accessible but also usable for all parties involved, facilitating multidisciplinary
            research and care initiatives. [35] </para>
        <para>Numerous examples of integrated data management have led to improved patient outcomes.
            For instance, combining clinical data with social and environmental information has
            enabled healthcare providers to offer more personalized care plans that address the
            broader context of patients' lives. Similarly, integrating epidemiological data with
            genomic research has accelerated the identification of disease markers and the
            development of targeted therapies. These successes underscore the value of IKM in
            enhancing the effectiveness of health interventions across disciplines. [36]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Future Direction for Healthcare Data Management and IKM</title>
        <para>As healthcare continues to evolve, the future of data management and IKM looks toward
            leveraging emerging technologies and methodologies to further enhance the quality,
            accessibility, and interoperability of health data. These advancements promise to
            transform healthcare delivery, research, and policy-making, driving improvements in
            patient outcomes and healthcare efficiency. [37] </para>
        <para>As the healthcare sector prepares for these advancements, it faces challenges such as
            ensuring data privacy and security, managing the ethical implications of AI and big
            data, and addressing disparities in access to technology. However, these challenges also
            present opportunities to redefine healthcare practices, improve patient engagement, and
            foster a more data-driven and patient-centric healthcare ecosystem. Embracing IKM
            principles will be crucial in navigating these changes, ensuring that data management
            practices continue to evolve in alignment with technological advancements and healthcare
            needs. [38]</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology. Health
                    IT Playbook [Internet]. USA; 2023 [cited 2023 Feb 20] Available from: <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.healthit.gov/playbook/"
                        >https://www.healthit.gov/playbook/</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Kwok CS, Muntean EA, Mallen CD, Borovac JA. Data Collection Theory in
                    Healthcare Research: The Minimum Dataset in Quantitative Studies. [Internet]
                    Clinical Practice; 2022 [cited 2023 Feb 20] Available from
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9680355/ </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Somasundaram P. How is knowledge management used in healthcare? [Internet]
                    Document360; 2022 [cited 2023 Feb 19]. Available from
                    https://document360.com/blog/knowledge-management-in-healthcare/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>World Health Organization. Mental Health: Strengthening Our Response.
                    [Internet] WHO; 2023 [cited 2024 Feb 23] Available from:
                    https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/mental-health-strengthening-our-response</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Stronge I. The complex challenges in sharing mental health data. [Internet]
                    National Elf Service. 2022. [cited 2024 Feb 23] Available from:
                    https://www.nationalelfservice.net/commissioning/technology/sharing-mental-health-data/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Lustgarten SD, Garrison YL, Sinnard MT, Flynn AW. Digital privacy in mental
                    healthcare: current issues and recommendations for technology use. [Internet].
                    Current Opinion in Psychology; 2020 [cited 2024 Feb 27]. Available from
                    https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32361651/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Golay P, Bonsack C, Silva B, Pauli G, de Boer E, Morandi S. Patterns of
                    Service Use in Intensive Case Management: A Six Year Longitudinal Study.
                    [Internet] Administration and Policy in Mental Health and Mental Health Services
                    Research. 2022 May; [cited 2024 Feb 28] Available from:
                    https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10488-022-01198-y </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Tracy N. Types of Mental Health Facilities. [Internet] HealthyPlace; October
                    2019 [cited 2024 Feb 28]. Available from:
                    https://www.healthyplace.com/other-info/mental-illness-overview/types-of-mental-health-facilities
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Insel T. Digital mental health care: five lessons from Act 1 and a preview of
                    Acts 2-5. [Internet] Nature; January 2023 [cited 2024 Mar 5]. Available from:
                    https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-023-00760-8</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Iqbal M. App Download Data. [Internet] Business of Apps; January 2024 [cited
                    2024 Mar 7]. Available from:
                    https://www.businessofapps.com/data/app-statistics/#:~:text=Today%2C%20there%20are%20over%20four,of%20sub%2Dgenres%20and%20niches</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>American Psychiatric Association. Thousands of Mental Health Apps Available:
                    Supporting Evidence Not So Plentiful. [Internet] Patients and Families; July
                    2019 [cited 2024 Mar 8]. Available from:
                    https://www.psychiatry.org/news-room/apa-blogs/mental-health-apps-evidence-not-so-plentiful#:~:text=There%20are%20more%20than%2010%2C000,%E2%80%9D%20(1)%20Several%20recent%20studies</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Tewari S. How to Navigate Mental Health Apps That May Share Your Data.
                    [Internet]. American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU); Sept 2022 [cited 2024 Mar 7].
                    Available from:
                    https://www.aclu.org/news/privacy-technology/how-to-navigate-mental-health-apps-that-may-share-your-data</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Hujala T. Laihonen H. Knowledge management in a regional integrated health and
                    social care system. [Internet] Journal of Integrated Care; December 2023 [cited
                    2024 Feb 27]. Available from:
                    https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/JICA-06-2022-0032/full/html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. Data Management in Health Care.
                    [Internet] Data Analytics; 2023 [cited 2024 Feb 26] Available from:
                    https://www.ahrq.gov/data/resources/index.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Lee K. What is population health management (PHM)? | Definition from
                    TechTarget. [Internet] Health IT; June 2017 [cited 2024 Feb 24]. Available from:
                    https://www.techtarget.com/searchhealthit/definition/Population-health-management-PHM</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>DISPARITIES IN HEALTHCARE. In: 2021 National Healthcare Quality and
                    Disparities Report [Internet] [Internet]. Agency for Healthcare Research and
                    Quality (US); 2021 [cited 2024 May 23]. Available from:
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK578532/ </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Breen N, Berrigan D, Jackson JS, Wong DWS, Wood FB, Denny JC, et al.
                    Translational Health Disparities Research in a Data-Rich World. Health Equity
                    [Internet]. 2019 Nov 1 [cited 2024 May 23];3(1):588–600. Available from:
                    https://www.liebertpub.com/doi/10.1089/heq.2019.0042 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>McIsaac JLD, Penney TL, Storey KE, et al. Integrated knowledge translation in
                    population health intervention research: a case study of implementation and
                    outcomes from a school-based project. [Internet] Health Research Policy and
                    Systems; August 2018 [cited 2024 Feb 26]. Available from:
                    https://health-policy-systems.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12961-018-0351-8</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Anziolotti A. What Is a Medical Record? [Internet] Nemours KidsHealth; January
                    2021 [cited 2024 Feb 25]. Available from:
                    https://www.aap.org/en/patient-care/pediatric-health-records/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>U.S. Department of Health &amp; Human Services. Understanding HIPAA Privacy
                    For Individuals. [Internet] Health Information Privacy; June 2017 [cited 2024
                    Feb 26]. Available from:
                    https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/for-individuals/index.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Healthcare Information and Management Systems Society. Interoperability in
                    Healthcare; 2023 [cited 2024 Feb 18]. Available from:
                    https://www.himss.org/resources/interoperability-healthcare</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Obregon R, Slighton E, Krasniansky A. Next gen innovation: Opportunities in
                    pediatric digital health. [Internet] Rock Health; November 2023 [cited 2024 Mar
                    6] Available from:
                    https://rockhealth.com/insights/next-gen-innovation-opportunities-in-pediatric-digital-health/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Data and Statistics on Infectious
                    Disease. [Internet] 2023 [cited 2024 Feb 24]. Available from:
                    https://www.cdc.gov/datastatistics/index.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>World Health Organization. Global Health Observatory (GHO) Data. [Internet]
                    WHO; 2023 [cited 2024 Feb 24]. Available from:
                    https://www.who.int/data/gho</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>National Institutes of Health. NIH Data Sharing Repositories. [Internet] NIH;
                    2023 [cited 2024 Feb 22]. Available from:
                    https://www.nlm.nih.gov/NIHbmic/nih_data_sharing_repositories.html</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Johns Hopkins University &amp; Medicine. Ongoing Johns Hopkins COVID-19
                    Resources [Internet] Coronavirus Resource Center; March 2023 [cited 2024 Feb
                    23]. Available from: https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Infectious Diseases Data Observatory. Research Themes [Internet] IDDO; 2024
                    [cited 2024 March 1] Available from: https://www.iddo.org/research-themes</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Griggs RC, Batshaw M, Dunkle M, et al. Clinical research for rare disease:
                    opportunities, challenges, and solutions. [Internet] Molecular Genetics and
                    Metabolism; January2009 [cited 2024 Feb 27]; Available from:
                    https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1096719208002539</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Liu J, Barrett JS, Leonardi ET, et al. Natural History and Real‐World Data in
                    Rare Diseases: Applications, Limitations, and Future Perspectives. [Internet]
                    Journal of Clinical Pharmacology; December 2022 [cited 2024 Mar 13]. Available
                    from: https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36461748/ </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Orphanet. Knowledge of rare diseases and orphan drugs [Internet] Orphanet
                    Access Our Services; February 2024 [cited 2024 Feb 22]. Available from:
                    https://www.orpha.net/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Subbiah VThe next generation of evidence-based medicine [Internet] Nature
                    Medicine; February 2024 [cited 2024 Mar 7]. Available from:
                    https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-022-02160-z</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Nabbout R, Zanello G, Baker D, Balck L, Branbilla I, Buske O, Conklin L,
                    Davies E. Julkowska D, Kim Y, Klopstock T, Nakamura H, Nielsen K, Pariser A,
                    Pastor J, Scarpa M, Smith M, Taruscio D, Groft S. [Internet] Orphanet Journal of
                    Rare Diseases; May 2023 [cited 2024 Feb 29]. Available from:
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10169162/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ann &amp; Robert H. Lurie Children's Hospital of Chicago. Lurie Children's
                    Hospital First in Illinois to Be Designated as a Rare Disease Center of
                    Excellence by National Organization for Rare Disorders (NORD). [Internet] News
                    Release; May 2023 [cited 2024 Feb 29]. Available from:
                    https://www.luriechildrens.org/en/news-stories/lurie-childrens-hospital-first-in-illinois-to-be-designated-as-a-rare-disease-center-of-excellence-by-national-organization-for-rare-disorders-nord/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Interdisciplinary Standards for Systematic Data Integration. [Internet]
                    Guidelines for Data Integration Across Disciplines; 2023 [cited 2024 Feb 23].
                    Available from: https://www.issdi.org/guidelines-for-data-integration</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Green BN, Johnson CD. Interprofessional collaboration in research, education,
                    and clinical practice: working together for a better future. [Internet] Journal
                    of Chiropractic Education; March 2015 [cited 2024 Feb 23]. Available from:
                    https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4360764/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Zaugg I. Top 10 Strategies for Successful Data Science Teamwork. [Internet]
                    The Data Science Institute at Columbia University; March 2021 [cited 2024 Feb
                    23]. Available from:
                    https://datascience.columbia.edu/news/2021/top-ten-advice-for-successful-data-science-teamwork/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Caizon B. 24 Real Life Examples of Big Data In Healthcare Analytics.
                    [Internet] Business Intelligence; June 2013 [cited 2024 Feb 23]. Available from:
                    https://www.datapine.com/blog/big-data-examples-in-healthcare/</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ginburg PB, Loera-Brust A, Brandt C, Durak A. The opportunities and challenges
                    of data analytics in health care. [Internet] Brookings; November 2018 [cited
                    2024 Feb 23]. Available from:
                    https://www.brookings.edu/articles/the-opportunities-and-challenges-of-data-analytics-in-health-care/</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>