<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<glossary xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="gloss">
    <title>Glossary</title>
    <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*" align="left"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1.56*"/>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>Terminology</entry>
                    <entry>A set of concept identifiers, descriptors, and relationships used to
                        capture domain information in an information system.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Standard Terminology</entry>
                    <entry>A terminology developed and published for use across organizational
                        boundaries.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Enterprise Terminology</entry>
                    <entry>The set of terminology assets that are specific to and maintained by a
                        healthcare organization, including, locations and services and their
                        relationships to standard terminologies.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Tinkar</entry>
                    <entry>Terminology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar) is intended to provide an
                        architecture that delivers integrated terminology to the enterprise and its
                        information systems. Tinkar addresses the differences in management and
                        structure across reference terminology, and with local concepts and code
                        lists/value sets.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Logical Model</para>
                        <para> </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>A model expressed independently of a particular implementation
                        technology.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Tinkar Reference Model</para>
                        <para> </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>A logical model that describes the standardized model for terminology and
                        change management.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Coordinate</entry>
                    <entry>A dimension of context in which a user wishes to view terminology
                        assets.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>STAMP</entry>
                    <entry>Status, time, author, module, path (STAMP) are the precise version
                        coordinates that govern granular change control for Tinkar assets. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Path</entry>
                    <entry>A set of assets under version control that can be managed distinctly from
                        other assets. Paths “branch” from other paths when established, and can be
                        “merged” with other paths as well.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Branch</entry>
                    <entry>“Branch” as commonly used in version control, implies a tree structure,
                        where a version configuration is allowed to only have one origin. In many
                        instances, supported version configuration has more than one origin. For
                        example, a mapping configuration may have an origin of T1 on System A, and
                        T2 on System B (based on the release schedules of Systems A and B). A Path,
                        which is more general, allows multiple origins of a version
                        configuration.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Publish</entry>
                    <entry>To move a set of assets to a “published” branch and support its export to
                        an interoperable payload technology. Publication implies that the publisher
                        has exercised some editorial judgment and warrants the validity and
                        consistency of the publication. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Export</entry>
                    <entry>To serialize a set of content to an interoperable payload technology.
                        Export does not carry the same quality expectations as publication.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Import</entry>
                    <entry>To replicate an exported set of content into a repository. This activity
                        implies the implementation of rules and constraints asserted by both native
                        and imported content. </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Configuration Requirements</entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Functionality required to make a Tinkar repository operational.</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>UML</entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>The Object Management Group (OMG) Unified Modeling Language (UML)
                            specification defines a graphical language for specifying and
                            documenting the artifacts of systems.</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*" align="left"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1.56*"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Minimally Required Content</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>The set of minimal content a Tinkar repository must implement to
                            support operations. A Tinkar implementation must be furnished with the
                            following content: (a) One root concept; (b) One module dependency
                            graph; (c) Infrastructure concepts a.k.a Tinkar Model Concepts to
                            support the core patterns listed above; (d) Import rules to support
                            import of standard terminologies.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Tinkar Model Concepts (a.k.a Infrastructure concepts)</entry>
                        <entry>Minimally required content that are concepts.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Separation of Concerns</entry>
                        <entry>A design principle that allows a complete system to be subdivided
                            into distinct sections or components with well-defined functionality and
                            dependencies. This approach allows individual sections to be reused, as
                            well as worked on and updated independently to address new requirements
                            and use cases.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Foundation Layer of Knowledge Architecture</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>The Foundation layer provides the common elements of interoperability
                            such as object identity, versioning, modularity, and knowledge
                            representation. It includes the foundation and building blocks of the
                            common model and how the modules of the architecture are tightly version
                            controlled over time.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Terminology Layer of Knowledge Architecture</entry>
                        <entry>The Terminology Knowledge Layer provides structured sets of medical
                            terms and codes that define concepts of interest. This includes
                            descriptions, dialects, language, and semantic hierarchy; Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT®),
                            Logical Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes (LOINC®), and RxNorm are part of this layer.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Solor</para>
                            <para> </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>System of Logical Representation (SOLOR) is a project sponsored by the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) and
                            Logica Health that represents and brings together terminology standards
                            in a single model that can encompass any customized content. Solor
                            allows informaticists and developers to convert user-supplied
                            terminologies into a single model using open-source software to produce
                            Solor content.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Komet </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Knowledge Management Environment (Komet) is an example
                                implementation of the Tinkar model, and shows how terminologies like
                                SNOMED CT®, LOINC®, RxNorm shall be represented. Using the Komet
                                browser users can view and search concepts, view concept details,
                                and navigate hierarchies, among many other functions.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>UUID </entry>
                        <entry>Universally Unique Identifier (UUID) is a 128-bit number used to
                            identify information in computer systems.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>FHIR </entry>
                        <entry>Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resource (FHIR) is a standard
                            describing data formats and elements and an application programming
                            interface for exchanging electronic health records. </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Capability Maturity Model</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>A development model that can be viewed as a set of structured
                                levels that describe how well the behaviors, practices, and
                                processes of an organization can reliably and sustainably produce
                                required outcomes. There are five levels defined along the continuum
                                of the capability maturity model and the model provides a
                                theoretical continuum along which process maturity can be developed
                                incrementally from one level to the next.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
    </para>
    
</glossary>
