<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
  <title>Key Takeaways</title>
  <para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Terminology Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar) intends to integrate clinical terminology
          and local concepts to support increased data quality for interoperable clinical
          information. Quality clinical data enables healthcare systems across the enterprise to
          conduct robust and meaningful data analysis and increase overall interoperability, which
          ultimately enhances quality of care across all medical facilities. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A Tinkar specification provides a standardized model for terminology and change
          management. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Tinkar Reference Model could provide a single representation for all terminologies
          required in the U.S. (e.g., SNOMED CT®, LOINC® , RxNorm). </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Tinkar provides the foundation of a knowledge architecture that delivers integrated
          terminology to the enterprise and its information systems. In doing so, it addresses the
          differences in management and structure across reference terminology, local concepts, and
          code lists/value sets. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Tinkar aims to be both self-describing and completely machine processed:</para>
        <orderedlist numeration='loweralpha'>
          <listitem>
            <para>Self-describing machine-readable representation of terminology, such that if an
              application can process the metadata, it should be able to import the content/concepts
              and make it available to enterprise applications.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The machine-readable terminology could generate human-readable documentation so
              that business analysts and developers can understand and apply it correctly.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If HL7 so desired, Tinkar could be used as the format by which all HL7 terminology is
          exported. It is believed that current HL7 content can be converted to Tinkar with no loss;
          further work would need to be done to verify that if HL7 was interested in that
          path.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In practice, the Tinkar logical model can be used to create practical implementation
          guidance in the future (e.g., implementation guides, profiles, value sets), and can be
          applied to design change management solutions.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>

</chapter>
